<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-635"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-635"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35-635"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-635/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-635/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-635/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-635/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Revenue</heading>
        <article eId="chp_35__art_635">
          <num>35 ILCS 635/</num>
          <heading>Telecommunications Infrastructure Maintenance Fee Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>Short title</heading>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be cited as the Telecommunications Infrastructure Maintenance Fee Act.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-5">
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>Legislative intent</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The General Assembly imposed a tax on
invested capital of utilities to partially replace the personal property tax
that was abolished by the Illinois Constitution of 1970.  Since that tax was
imposed, telecommunications retailers have evolved from utility status into an
increasingly competitive industry serving the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Act is intended to
abolish the invested capital tax on telecommunications retailers (that is,
persons engaged in the business of transmitting messages and acting as a
retailer of telecommunications as defined in Section 2 of the
Telecommunications Excise Tax Act).  Cellular telecommunications retailers have
already been excluded from application
of the invested capital tax by earlier legislative action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the period prior to the effective date of this amendatory Act of
the 92nd General Assembly, this Act is also intended to
abolish municipal franchise fees with
respect to telecommunications retailers,
create a uniform system for the collection and
distribution of fees associated with the privilege of use of the public right
of way for telecommunications activity, and provide municipalities
with
a comprehensive method of compensation for telecommunications activity
including
the recovery of reasonable costs of regulating the use of the public
rights-of-way for telecommunications activity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the period from the effective date of this amendatory Act of the
92nd General Assembly through December 31, 2002, it is the
intent of the General Assembly
that the municipal infrastructure maintenance fee and its rate are subject only
to the limits prescribed in Section 20, and that the fee and the rate of the
fee do not relate to use of the public rights-of-way or the costs associated
with maintaining and regulating the use of the public rights-of-way.  It is
also the intent of the General Assembly that proceeds of the municipal
infrastructure maintenance fee may be used for any lawful corporate purpose.
It is not the intent of the General Assembly that the municipal infrastructure
maintenance fee is in any way compensation for use of the public rights-of-way.
 It is the intent of the General Assembly that the fee be paid by all
telecommunications retailers, regardless of whether they have equipment in the
public rights-of-way.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-5__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This amendatory Act of the 92nd
General Assembly is intended to repeal the municipal
infrastructure maintenance fee and the optional infrastructure
maintenance fee effective January 1, 2003.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 91-533, eff. 8-13-99; 92-526, eff. 2-8-02.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-10">
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>Definitions</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>"Gross charges" means the amount paid to a telecommunications retailer for the act or privilege of originating or receiving telecommunications in this State and for all services rendered in connection therewith, valued in money whether paid in money or otherwise, including cash, credits, services, and property of every kind or nature, and shall be determined without any deduction on account of the cost of such telecommunications, the cost of the materials used, labor or service costs, or any other expense whatsoever. In case credit is extended, the amount thereof shall be included only as and when paid. "Gross charges" for private line service shall include charges imposed at each channel termination point within this State, charges for the channel mileage between each channel termination point within this State, and charges for that portion of the interstate inter-office channel provided within Illinois. Charges for that portion of the interstate inter-office channel provided in Illinois shall be determined by the retailer as follows:</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for interstate inter-office channels having 2 channel termination points, only one of which is in Illinois, 50% of the total charge imposed; or (ii) for interstate inter-office channels having more than 2 channel termination points, one or more of which are in Illinois, an amount equal to the total charge multiplied by a fraction, the numerator of which is the number of channel termination points within Illinois and the denominator of which is the total number of channel termination points. Prior to January 1, 2004, any method consistent with this paragraph or other method that reasonably apportions the total charges for interstate inter-office channels among the states in which channel terminations points are located shall be accepted as a reasonable method to determine the charges for that portion of the interstate inter-office channel provided within Illinois for that period. However, "gross charges" shall not include any of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any amounts added to a purchaser's bill because of a charge made under:</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the fee imposed by this Section, (ii) additional charges added to a purchaser's bill under Section 9-221 or 9-222 of the Public Utilities Act, (iii) the tax imposed by the Telecommunications Excise Tax Act, (iv) 911 surcharges,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the tax imposed by Section 4251 of the Internal Revenue Code, or (vi) the tax imposed by the Simplified Municipal Telecommunications Tax Act.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges for a sent collect telecommunication received outside of this State.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges for leased time on equipment or charges for the storage of data or information or subsequent retrieval or the processing of data or information intended to change its form or content. Such equipment includes, but is not limited to, the use of calculators, computers, data processing equipment, tabulating equipment, or accounting equipment and also includes the usage of computers under a time-sharing agreement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges for customer equipment, including such equipment that is leased or rented by the customer from any source, wherein such charges are disaggregated and separately identified from other charges.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges to business enterprises certified under Section 9-222.1 of the Public Utilities Act to the extent of such exemption and during the period of time specified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity. (5.1) Charges to business enterprises certified under Section 95 of the Reimagining Energy and Vehicles in Illinois Act, to the extent of the exemption and during the period of time specified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity. (5.2) Charges to business enterprises certified under Section 110-95 of the Manufacturing Illinois Chips for Real Opportunity (MICRO) Act, to the extent of the exemption and during the period of time specified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity. (5.3) Charges to entities certified under Section 605-1115 of the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity Law of the Civil Administrative Code of Illinois to the extent of the exemption and during the period of time specified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges for telecommunications and all services and equipment provided in connection therewith between a parent corporation and its wholly owned subsidiaries or between wholly owned subsidiaries, and only to the extent that the charges between the parent corporation and wholly owned subsidiaries or between wholly owned subsidiaries represent expense allocation between the corporations and not the generation of profit other than a regulatory required profit for the corporation rendering such services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Bad debts ("bad debt" means any portion of a debt that is related to a sale at retail for which gross charges are not otherwise deductible or excludable that has become worthless or uncollectible, as determined under applicable federal income tax standards; if the portion of the debt deemed to be bad is subsequently paid, the retailer shall report and pay the tax on that portion during the reporting period in which the payment is made).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges paid by inserting coins in coin-operated telecommunication devices.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_v__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Charges for nontaxable services or telecommunications if</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>those charges are aggregated with other charges for telecommunications that are taxable, (ii) those charges are not separately stated on the customer bill or invoice, and (iii) the retailer can reasonably identify the nontaxable charges on the retailer's books and records kept in the regular course of business. If the nontaxable charges cannot reasonably be identified, the gross charge from the sale of both taxable and nontaxable services or telecommunications billed on a combined basis shall be attributed to the taxable services or telecommunications. The burden of proving nontaxable charges shall be on the retailer of the telecommunications. (a-5) "Department" means the Illinois Department of Revenue.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-10__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>"Telecommunications" includes, but is not limited to, messages or information transmitted through use of local, toll, and wide area telephone service, channel services, telegraph services, teletypewriter service, computer exchange services, private line services, specialized mobile radio services, or any other transmission of messages or information by electronic or similar means, between or among points by wire, cable, fiber optics, laser, microwave, radio, satellite, or similar facilities. Unless the context clearly requires otherwise, "telecommunications" shall also include wireless telecommunications as hereinafter defined. "Telecommunications" shall not include value added services in which computer processing applications are used to act on the form, content, code, and protocol of the information for purposes other than transmission. "Telecommunications" shall not include purchase of telecommunications by a telecommunications service provider for use as a component part of the service provided by him or her to the ultimate retail consumer who originates or terminates the end-to-end communications. Retailer access charges, right of access charges, charges for use of intercompany facilities, and all telecommunications resold in the subsequent provision and used as a component of, or integrated into, end-to-end telecommunications service shall not be included in gross charges as sales for resale. "Telecommunications" shall not include the provision of cable services through a cable system as defined in the Cable Communications Act of 1984 (47 U.S.C. Sections 521 and following) as now or hereafter amended or through an open video system as defined in the Rules of the Federal Communications Commission (47 C.D.F. 76.1550 and following) as now or hereafter amended. Beginning January 1, 2001, prepaid telephone calling arrangements shall not be considered "telecommunications" subject to the tax imposed under this Act. For purposes</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-595, eff. 6-26-24; 104-417, eff. 8-15-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-15">
            <num>15</num>
            <heading>State telecommunications infrastructure maintenance fees</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-15__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A State infrastructure maintenance fee is hereby imposed upon
telecommunications retailers as a replacement for the personal property tax in
an amount
specified in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-15__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of the State infrastructure maintenance fee imposed upon a
telecommunications retailer under this Section shall be equal to 0.5% of all
gross charges charged by the telecommunications retailer to service addresses
in this State for telecommunications, other than wireless telecommunications,
originating or received in this State.  However, the State infrastructure
maintenance fee is not imposed in any case in which the imposition of the fee
would violate the Constitution or statutes of the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-15__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>(Blank).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-15__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>(Blank).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-15__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State infrastructure maintenance fee authorized by this Section shall be collected,
enforced, and
administered as set forth in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-15__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of Section 25 of this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-20">
            <num>20</num>
            <heading>(Repealed)</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 2-8-02.  Repealed internally, eff. 1-1-03.) (35 ILCS 635/22)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 2-8-02.  Repealed internally, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-22">
            <num>22</num>
            <heading>Certificates</heading>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be unlawful for any person to engage
in business as a telecommunications retailer
in this State within the meaning of this Act without first having
obtained a certificate of registration to do so from the
Department.  Application for the certificate shall be made to the
Department in a form prescribed and furnished by the Department.
Each applicant for a certificate shall furnish to the Department
on a form prescribed by the Department and signed by the
applicant under penalties of perjury, the following information: (1) The name of the applicant. (2) The address of the location at which the applicant proposes to engage in business as a telecommunications retailer in this State. (3) Other information the Department may reasonably require. The Department, upon receipt of an application in proper
form, shall issue to the applicant a certificate, in a form
prescribed by the Department, which shall permit the applicant to
whom it is issued to engage in business as a telecommunications retailer
at the place shown on his or her application.
No certificate issued under this Act is transferable or
assignable.  No certificate shall be issued to any person
who is in default to the State of Illinois for moneys due under
this Act or any other tax Act administered by the Department.
Any person aggrieved by any decision of the Department under this
Section may, within 20 days after notice of such decision,
protest and request a hearing, whereupon the Department shall
give notice to such person of the time and place fixed for such
hearing and shall hold a hearing in conformity with the
provisions of this Act and then issue its final administrative
decision in the matter to such person.  In the absence of such a
protest within 20 days, the Department's decision shall become
final without any further determination being made or notice
given. The Department may, in its discretion, upon application,
authorize the payment of the fees imposed under this Act by any
telecommunications retailer not otherwise subject to the fees
imposed under this Act who, to the satisfaction of the
Department, furnishes adequate security to ensure payment of the
fees.  The telecommunications retailer shall be issued, without
charge, a certificate to remit the fees.  When so authorized, it
shall be the duty of the telecommunications retailer to remit the
fees imposed upon the gross charges charged by the
telecommunications retailer to service addresses in this State
for telecommunications in the same manner and subject to the same
requirements as a telecommunications retailer operating within
this State.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-16, eff. 6-28-01.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-24">
            <num>24</num>
            <heading>Certificate actions</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The Department may,
after notice and a hearing, revoke, cancel, or suspend the
certificate of registration of any telecommunications retailer
who violates any of the provisions of this Act or regulations
promulgated thereunder. The notice shall specify the alleged
violation or violations upon which the revocation, cancellation,
or suspension proceeding is based. The Department may, after notice and a hearing as provided
herein, revoke the certificate of registration of any person who
violates any of the provisions of this Act. Before revocation of
a certificate of registration the Department shall, within 90
days after non-compliance and at least 7 days prior to the date
of the hearing, give the person so accused notice in writing of
the charge against him or her, and on the date designated shall
conduct a hearing upon this matter. The lapse of such 90 day
period shall not preclude the Department from conducting
revocation proceedings at a later date if necessary. Any hearing
held under this Section shall be conducted by the Director of
Revenue or by any officer or employee of the Department
designated, in writing, by the Director of Revenue.
Upon the hearing of any such proceeding, the Director of
Revenue, or any officer or employee of the Department designated,
in writing, by the Director of Revenue, may administer oaths and
the Department may procure by its subpoena the attendance of
witnesses and, by its subpoena duces tecum, the production of
relevant books and papers. Any circuit court, upon application
either of the accused or of the Department, may, by order duly
entered, require the attendance of witnesses and the production
of relevant books and papers, before the Department in any
hearing relating to the revocation of certificates of
registration. Upon refusal or neglect to obey the order of the
court, the court may compel obedience thereof by proceedings for
contempt.
The Department may, by application to any circuit court,
obtain an injunction restraining any person who engages in
business as a telecommunications retailer without a certificate
(either because his or her certificate has been revoked,
canceled, or suspended or because of a failure to obtain a
certificate in the first instance) from engaging in that business
until that person, as if that person were a new applicant for a
certificate, complies with all of the conditions, restrictions,
and requirements of Section 22 of this Act and qualifies for
and obtains a certificate. Refusal or neglect to obey the order
of the court may result in punishment for contempt.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-562, eff. 12-16-97.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-25">
            <num>25</num>
            <heading>Collection, enforcement, and administration of State
telecommunications infrastructure maintenance fees</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-25__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A telecommunications retailer shall charge each customer an additional
charge equal to the State infrastructure
maintenance fee attributable to that customer's service address.  Such additional charge shall be shown separately
on the bill to each customer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-25__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The State infrastructure maintenance fee shall be designated as a replacement for the personal
property
tax and shall be remitted by the telecommunications retailer to the Department; provided, however, that the
telecommunications retailer
may retain an amount not to exceed 2% of the State infrastructure maintenance
fee paid to the
Department, with a timely paid and timely filed return to reimburse itself for
expenses incurred in collecting, accounting for, and remitting the fee. Beginning on the first day of the first calendar month to occur on or after the effective date of this amendatory Act of the 98th General Assembly, an amount equal to 1/12 of 5% of the cash receipts collected during the preceding fiscal year by the Audit Bureau of the Department from the tax under this Act shall be paid each month into the Tax Compliance and Administration Fund to be used, subject to appropriation, to fund additional auditors and compliance personnel at the Department of Revenue. All
remaining amounts herein remitted to the Department shall be paid into the Personal
Property Tax Replacement Fund in the State Treasury.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 98-1098, eff. 8-26-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-27">
            <num>27</num>
            <heading>Returns by telecommunications retailer; extensions</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Except as
provided
hereinafter in this Section, on or before the 30th day of each
month each telecommunications retailer maintaining a place of business in this
State
shall make a return and payment of fees to the Department for the
preceding calendar month on a form prescribed and furnished by
the Department. The return shall be signed by the telecommunications retailer
under
penalties of perjury and shall contain the following information: 1. His or her name; 2. The address of his or her principal place of business, or the address of the principal place of business (if that is a different address) from which he or she engages in the business of transmitting telecommunications; 3. The total amount of gross charges charged by him or her during the preceding calendar month for providing telecommunications during such calendar month; 4. The total amount received by him or her during the preceding calendar month on credit extended; 5. Deductions allowed by law; 6. Gross charges that were charged by him or her during the preceding calendar month and upon the basis of which the State infrastructure maintenance fee is imposed; 7. (Blank); 8. Amounts of fees due; 9. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. If the telecommunications retailer's average monthly liability to the
Department does not exceed $100, the Department may authorize his
or her returns to be filed on a quarter annual basis, with the return
for January, February, and March of a given year being due by
April 15 of such year; with the return for April, May, and June of
a given year being due by July 15 of such year; with the return
for July, August, and September of a given year being due by
October 15 of such year; and with the return of October, November,
and December of a given year being due by January 15 of the
following year. Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act concerning
the time within which a telecommunications retailer may file his or her return,
in the case
of any telecommunications retailer who ceases to engage in a kind of business
which
makes him or her responsible for filing returns under this Act, such
telecommunications retailer shall file a final return under this Act with the
Department not more than one month after discontinuing such
business. In making such return, the telecommunications retailer shall determine the
value of any consideration other than money received by him or her and
he or she shall include such value in his or her return. Such determination
shall be subject to review and revision by the Department in the
manner hereinafter provided for the correction of returns. If any payment provided for in this Section exceeds the
telecommunications retailer's liabilities under this Act, as shown on an
original
monthly return, the Department may
authorize the telecommunications retailer to credit such excess payment
against liability subsequently to be remitted to the Department
under this Act, in accordance with reasonable rules and
regulations prescribed by the Department. If the Department
subsequently determines that all or any part of the credit taken
was not actually due to the telecommunications retailer, the telecommunications
retailer's 2% discount
shall be reduced by 2% of the difference between the credit taken
and that actually due, and that telecommunications retailer shall be liable for
penalties and interest on such difference. Any telecommunications retailer required to make payments under this Section
may make the payments by electronic funds transfer. The
Department shall adopt rules necessary to effectuate a program of
electronic funds transfer.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-30">
            <num>30</num>
            <heading>Validity of existing franchise fees and agreements</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-30__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No new franchise fees or other charges
for the use of the public rights-of-way, including charges for the recovery of
reasonable costs of regulating the use of the public rights-of-way,
shall be imposed upon, levied on, or otherwise required of telecommunications
retailers by ordinance, resolution, or contract, nor shall any other
new charges be required from telecommunications retailers by
municipalities from and
after the effective date of this Act.
Nothing in this Act shall excuse any person or entity from obligations imposed
under any law concerning generally applicable taxes or standards for
construction on, over, under, or within, use of or
repair of the public rights-of-way, including standards relating to free
standing towers and other structures upon the public way, nor shall any
person or entity be excused
from any liability imposed by any such law for the failure to comply with such
generally applicable taxes or standards governing construction on, over, under,
or within, use of or repair of the
public rights-of-way.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-30__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Agreements between telecommunications retailers and municipalities
entered into before the effective date of this Act regarding use of
the public ways shall remain valid according to and for their stated terms,
except as to fees or charges waived under Section 5-60 of the Simplified
Municipal Telecommunications Tax Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-30__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The regulation of the terms and conditions upon which poles, conduits,
and other facilities located in the public way may be shared by or between
telecommunications retailers shall be committed exclusively to the jurisdiction
of the Illinois Commerce Commission and the Federal Communications Commission,
and such regulation shall not be among the home rule powers and functions
described in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-30__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of Section 6 of Article VII of the Illinois
Constitution.  Moreover, no municipality may enter into any
contract or agreement with a telecommunications retailer with respect to the
terms and conditions upon which poles, conduits, and other facilities located
in
the public way may be shared by or between telecommunications retailers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-35">
            <num>35</num>
            <heading>Home rule</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-635-35__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of
Section 6 of Article VII of the Illinois Constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-526, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-40">
            <num>40</num>
            <heading>Severability</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If any provision of this Act or its application to
any person or circumstance is held invalid, the invalidity of the provision or
application does not affect other provisions or applications of the Act that
can be given effect without the invalid provision or application.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-154, eff. 1-1-98.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-905">
            <num>905</num>
            <heading>The Messages Tax Act is amended by repealing Section 2a</heading>
            <content>
              <p>1.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-154, eff. 1-1-98.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-910">
            <num>910</num>
            <heading>(Amendatory provisions; text omitted)</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 90-154, eff. 1-1-98; text omitted.) (35 ILCS 635/915)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-154, eff. 1-1-98; text omitted.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-915">
            <num>915</num>
            <heading>(Amendatory provisions; text omitted</heading>
            <content>
              <p>)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-154, eff. 1-1-98; text omitted.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-635-920">
            <num>920</num>
            <heading>(Amendatory provisions; text omitted</heading>
            <content>
              <p>)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-154, eff. 1-1-98; text omitted.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>