<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-50"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-50"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="305-50"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_305">
        <num>305</num>
        <heading>Public Aid</heading>
        <article eId="chp_305__art_50">
          <num>305 ILCS 50/</num>
          <heading>Scientific Job Training Evaluation Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_305-50-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>Short title</heading>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be cited as the Scientific Job Training Evaluation Act.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 89-389, eff. 1-1-96.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_305-50-5">
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>Evaluation</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_305-50-5__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Aid shall contract for a scientific evaluation
of the effectiveness of its job training and education programs for recipients
of aid under Article IV of the Illinois Public Aid Code.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_305-50-5__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The methodology of the evaluation shall consist of a controlled
experiment in which a statistically significant group of recipients of aid who
are eligible for or volunteering to participate in the program is divided into
2 groups by a random assignment: an experimental group (which participates in
the program) and a control group (which does not participate in the program).
The effect of the program on its participants shall be evaluated by comparing
the control and experimental groups.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_305-50-5__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this Section, "random assignment" means any established
method that divides a population into 2 or more groups on a random
statistical basis, thereby assuring initial homogeneity between
experimental and control groups necessary for scientific comparison.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_305-50-5__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, within the 3 years preceding the effective date of this Act, the
Department has done a scientific evaluation of a program with a statistically
significant sample, using both a control group and an experimental group,
then the Department is not required to repeat that evaluation under this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_305-50-5__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an evaluation required under this Section is not
completed before July 1, 1997, the Department of Human Services (acting as
successor to the Department of Public Aid under the Department of Human
Services Act) shall ensure that the evaluation is completed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 89-380, eff. 1-1-96; 89-507, eff. 7-1-97.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_305-50-10">
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>AFDC; separate analysis</heading>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of any education and
training program for recipients of aid under Article IV of the Illinois Public
Aid Code,
the Department of Public Aid shall contract for both an experimental evaluation
as described in Section 5 of this Act and a separate statistical analysis to
determine whether the availability of the education and training program has
led
to an increase or decrease in the number of applications for aid under Article
IV of the Illinois Public Aid Code.  If the evaluation and statistical
analysis required under this Section are
not completed before July 1, 1997, the Department of Human Services (acting
as successor to the Department of Public Aid under the Department of Human
Services Act) shall ensure that the evaluation and statistical analysis are
completed.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 89-389, eff. 1-1-96; 89-507, eff. 7-1-97.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_305-50-15">
            <num>15</num>
            <heading>Waiver</heading>
            <content>
              <p>In the event that scientific evaluation of a particular
program is prohibited by federal law or regulation, the evaluations will not
begin until the necessary waivers have been obtained from the appropriate
federal department.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 89-389, eff. 1-1-96.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_305-50-90">
            <num>90</num>
            <heading>Repeal</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sections 5-1 and 5-5 of Public Act 88-412, which are
known as the Job Training Evaluation Act, are repealed.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 89-389, eff. 1-1-96.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>