<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-515"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-515"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35-515"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-515/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-515/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-515/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-515/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Revenue</heading>
        <article eId="chp_35__art_515">
          <num>35 ILCS 515/</num>
          <heading>Mobile Home Local Services Tax Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>(a)  As used in this Act, &quot;manufactured home&quot; means a factory-assembled, completely integrated structure designed for permanent habitation, with a permanent chassis, and so constructed as to permit its transport, on wheels temporarily or permanently attached to its frame, and is a movable or portable unit that is (i) 8 body feet or more in width, (ii) 40 body feet or more in length, and (iii) 320 or more square feet, constructed to be towed on its own chassis (comprised of frame and wheels) from the place of its construction to the location, or subsequent locations, at which it is connected to utilities for year-round occupancy for use as a permanent habitation, and designed and situated so as to permit its occupancy as a dwelling place for one or more persons, and specifically includes a &quot;manufactured home&quot; as defined in subdivision (53) of Section 9-102 of the Uniform Commercial Code</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Mobile homes and manufactured homes that</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-1__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>are located outside of mobile home parks and (ii) are taxed under this Act on the effective date of this amendatory Act of the 96th General Assembly must continue to be taxed under this Act and shall not be assessed and taxed as real property until the home is sold, transferred, or relocated to a different parcel of land outside of a mobile home park.  If a mobile home or manufactured home described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-1__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is sold, transferred, or relocated to a different parcel of land outside of a mobile home park, then the home must be assessed and taxed as real property whether or not the mobile home or manufactured home is affixed to a permanent foundation as defined in Section 5-5 of the Conveyance and Encumbrance of Manufactured Homes as Real Property and Severance Act and whether or not the mobile home or manufactured home is real property as defined in Section 5-35 of the Conveyance and Encumbrance of Manufactured Homes as Real Property and Severance Act.  Mobile homes and manufactured homes that are located outside of mobile home parks and assessed and taxed as real property on the effective date of this amendatory Act of the 96th General Assembly must continue to be assessed and taxed as real property whether or not the mobile homes and manufactured homes are affixed to a permanent foundation as defined in Section 5-5 of the Conveyance and Encumbrance of Manufactured Homes as Real Property and Severance Act or installed on permanent foundations and whether or not the mobile homes and manufactured homes are real property as defined in Section 5-35 of the Conveyance and Encumbrance of Manufactured Homes as Real Property and Severance Act.  If a mobile or manufactured home that is located outside of a mobile home park is relocated to a mobile home park, the home must be taxed according to the Mobile Home Local Services Tax Act.  The owner of a mobile home or manufactured home that is located outside of a mobile home park may file a request with the county that the home be assessed and taxed as real property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-1__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Mobile homes and manufactured homes that are located in mobile home parks must be taxed according to this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 98-749, eff. 7-16-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-2">
            <num>2</num>
            <heading>As used in this Act, the phrase &quot;mobile home park&quot; has the meaning
ascribed to it by Section 2</heading>
            <content>
              <p>5 of &quot;An Act to provide for, license and
regulate mobile homes and mobile home parks and to repeal an Act named
herein&quot;, approved September 8, 1971, as amended.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 78-375 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-3">
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>Mobile homes in addition to such taxes as provided in the &quot;Use Tax Act&quot;
shall be subject to the following privilege tax only, and to no ad
valorem tax</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in Section 7 and in those cases where the owner notifies the local assessing authority, by sworn affidavit, that the mobile home is uninhabited and will no longer be used for human habitation, the owner of each 
mobile home shall pay to the county treasurer of the county in which such
mobile home is located an annual tax to be
computed at the rate shown in the table below: TAX YEAR FOLLOWING MODEL YEAR          TAX PER SQUARE FOOT OF MOBILE HOME model year and 1st and 2nd year following:                               15¢ 3rd, 4th and 5th years following model year:                                 13.5¢ 6th, 7th and 8th years following model year:                                   12¢ 9th, 10th and 11th years following model year:                                 10.5¢ 12th, 13th and 14th years following model year:                                    9¢ 15th year following model year and subsequent years:                        7.5¢ For purposes of this Act, the square-footage shall be based upon the
 outside dimensions of the mobile home excluding the length of the tongue
and hitch.  The owner of a mobile home on January 1 of any year shall be
liable for the tax of that year,
except that the owner of a mobile home on July 1, 1976, shall be liable
for the tax for the period of
July 1, 1976, to December 31, 1976.
This is not a limitation on any home rule county.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 94-606, eff. 8-16-05.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-4">
            <num>4</num>
            <heading>The owner of each inhabited mobile home or manufactured home located in this State, but not located inside of a mobile home park, on the
effective date of this amendatory Act of the 96th General Assembly shall, within 30 days after such date, record with the Office of the Recorder in the county where the mobile home or manufactured home is located a mobile home
registration form containing the information hereinafter specified, subject to the county's recording fees</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Mobile home
park operators shall forward a copy of the mobile home registration form
provided in Section 12 of &quot;An Act to provide for, license and regulate mobile
homes and mobile home parks and to repeal an Act named herein&quot;, approved
September 8, 1971, as amended, to the township assessor, if any, or to
Supervisor of Assessments or county assessor if there is no township assessor,
or to the county assessor in those counties in which a county assessor is
elected pursuant to Section 3-45 of the Property Tax Code, within 5 days of the entry of a mobile home into such
park. The owner of a mobile home or manufactured home not located in a mobile home park, other than a mobile home or manufactured home with respect to which the requirements of Section 5-30 of the Conveyance and Encumbrance of Manufactured Homes as Real Property and Severance Act and the requirements of Section 3-116.1 or Section 3-116.2 of the Illinois Vehicle Code, as applicable, have been satisfied unless with respect to the same manufactured home there has been recorded an affidavit of severance pursuant to Section 5-50 of the Conveyance and Encumbrance of Manufactured Homes as Real Property and Severance Act, shall,
within 30 days after initial placement of such mobile home or manufactured home in any county and
within 30 days after movement of such mobile home or manufactured home to a new location, record with the Office of the Recorder in the county where the mobile home or manufactured home is located a mobile home registration showing the name and address of the
owner and every occupant of the mobile home or manufactured home, the location of the mobile home or manufactured home,
the year of manufacture, and the square feet of floor space contained in such
mobile home or manufactured home together with the date that the mobile home or manufactured home became inhabited, was
initially installed and set up in the county, or was moved to a new location. Such
registration shall also include the license number of such mobile home or manufactured home and of
the towing vehicle, if there be any, and the State issuing such licenses, subject to the county's recording fees. In the case of a mobile home or manufactured home not located in a mobile home park, the
registration shall be signed by the owner or occupant of the mobile home or manufactured home. Failure to record the registration shall not prevent the home from being assessed and taxed as real property. It is
the duty of each township assessor, if any, and each Supervisor of Assessments
or county assessor if there is no township assessor, or the county assessor in
those counties in which a county assessor is elected pursuant to Section 3-45
of the Property Tax Code, to require timely
filing of a properly completed registration for each mobile home or manufactured home located in a mobile home park in his
or her township or county, as the case may be. Any person furnishing misinformation
for purposes of registration or failing to record a required registration is
guilty of a Class A misdemeanor. This Section applies only when the tax
permitted by Section 3 has been imposed on mobile homes and manufactured homes located inside mobile home parks.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 98-749, eff. 7-16-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-5">
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>The township assessor, county assessor or supervisor of assessments,
within 7 days after filing of a registration, shall deliver such
registration to the county clerk</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 78-375 .) (35 ILCS 515/6) (from Ch. 120, par. 1206)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 78-375 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-6">
            <num>6</num>
            <heading>Computation, certification, and distribution of tax</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Except as
otherwise provided in this Section, within 60 days of
receipt of each registration form, the county clerk or, in counties in
which a county assessor is elected pursuant to Section 3-45 of the Property
Tax Code, the county assessor shall compute
the tax due, as provided in Section 3, and certify the tax to the county
treasurer who shall mail the tax bill to the owner of such mobile home at the
time he receives the certification or on the annual billing date, whichever
occurs later. If the registration form is accompanied by a receipt for
privilege taxes paid in Illinois for the current tax year, no further privilege
tax shall be imposed for the remainder of the current tax year.  If the mobile
home is initially harbored after the annual liability date, as provided in
Section 3 of this Act, the county clerk or county assessor shall reduce such
tax 1/12 for each month that has passed since such annual liability date.  A
mobile home harbored after the first day of such month shall be considered
to have been harbored for the entire month for the purposes of this
Section.  Thereafter, for taxable years prior to taxable year 2003,
except for the year 1976, the county clerk or county
assessor shall compute such tax as of the first day of June of each year
and certify the tax to the county treasurer.
For taxable year 2003 and thereafter, the county clerk or county assessor
shall compute the tax as of the first day of March of each year and certify the
tax to the county treasurer.
Such tax shall be due and
payable to the county treasurer within 60 days after the treasurer mails
the tax bill to the address of record.  The first tax bill mailed for taxable
year 2003 shall include the following notice: &quot;The manner in which delinquent
taxes on mobile homes are collected has been changed by the enactment of the
Mobile Home Local Services Tax Enforcement Act.  Failure to pay this tax can
result in a penalty of $25 per month.&quot;  The county treasurer shall distribute
such taxes to the local taxing districts within the boundaries
of which such mobile homes are located, in the same proportion as the
property taxes collectible for each such taxing district in the prior year. In order to effect the change of the annual billing date and the date of
liability, provided for by this amendatory Act of 1975, the county clerk
shall compute such  tax as of July 1, 1976, for the 1/2 year period from
July 1, 1976, through December 31, 1976, at 1/2 the amount of the annual
tax.  The tax for such period shall be certified, billed, collected and
distributed in the same manner as is provided in this Section
as taxes for a full year, and shall be subject to a proportionate reduction
if the mobile home is initially harbored after July 1, 1976 and before January
1, 1977.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-807, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-7">
            <num>7</num>
            <heading>The local services tax for owners of mobile homes who (a) are
actually residing in such mobile homes, (b) hold title to such mobile
home as provided in the Illinois Vehicle Code, and (c) are 65 years of age or older or are persons with disabilities within the meaning of Section 3</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>I actually reside in the mobile home ....</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>I hold title to the mobile home as provided in the Illinois
Vehicle Code ....</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>I reached the age of 65 on or before either January 1 (or July
1) of the year in which this statement is filed.  My date of birth is: ...</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Persons with Disabilities</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>I actually reside in the mobile home...</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>I hold title to the mobile home as provided in the Illinois
Vehicle Code ....</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-7__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>I became a person with a total disability on ... and have remained a person with a disability until
the date of this application.  My Social Security, Veterans, Railroad or
Civil Service Total Disability Claim Number is ...  The undersigned
declares under the penalty of perjury that the above statements are true
and correct. Dated (insert date). ........................... Signature of owner ........................... (Address) ........................... (City)  (State)  (Zip) Approved by: ............................. (Assessor) This application shall be accompanied by a copy of the applicant's
most recent application filed with the Illinois Department on Aging
under the Senior Citizens and Persons with Disabilities Property Tax Relief Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 98-463, eff. 8-16-13; 99-143, eff. 7-27-15.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-8">
            <num>8</num>
            <heading>Failure to pay tax; lien</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-8__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>unless the county treasurer files  with the county
recorder of the county in which the mobile home is located a notice of
lien within one year of such tax due date or (ii) if the county
treasurer
applies for judgment and order of sale for delinquent taxes on mobile homes
pursuant to the provisions of the Mobile Home Local Services Tax Enforcement
Act and the taxes are sold.  From the time of the
filing, the amount set forth in the certificate also constitutes a lien
upon all property of the taxpayer then owned by him or thereafter
acquired by him in the period before the expiration of the lien. Such
liens have the same force, effect and priority as a judgment lien and
continue for 10 years from the date of the recording unless sooner
released or otherwise discharged.  The county treasurer may, at any
time, release all or any portion of the property subject to any lien
provided for in this Act or subordinate the lien to other liens if he
determines that the taxes are sufficiently secured by a lien or other
property of the taxpayer or that the release or subordination of the
lien will not endanger or jeopardize the collection of the taxes. If the owner of a mobile home upon which the tax has not been paid does
not make payment within 6 months after a lien has been filed, civil action
may be instituted by the collector for the amount of the tax, plus interest,
penalties and costs.  If sale of the property is ordered, the court may
direct the sale to be made in cash or on such terms as it may deem in the
best interests of all parties.  The court may direct that such sale be held
by the sheriff or in open court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-807, eff. 1-1-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-9">
            <num>9</num>
            <heading>Additional charge for delinquent taxes; penalty for fraud</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-9__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>$100 or (ii) 50% of the original tax imposed. In all counties, if such failure to pay such tax
is the result of fraud, there shall be added to the tax as a penalty an
amount equal to 50% of the deficiency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 101-454, eff. 8-23-19.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-10">
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>Mobile home dealers shall within 10 days after any retail
sale and delivery of a mobile home, notify the county clerk of the
county in which the point of delivery is located of the sale, the name
of the purchaser, year of manufacture, the point at which delivery to the
purchaser was made,
and the serial number and exterior measurements of the mobile home</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 81-1137.) (35 ILCS 515/10.1) (from Ch. 120, par. 1210.1) Sec. 10.1. Notice to assessor of ownership change. An operator of a mobile home park licensed under the provisions
of the Mobile Home Park Act and any land owner on which an inhabited mobile
home is located shall notify the township assessor, if any, or the
Supervisor
of Assessments or county assessor if there is no township assessor, or
the county assessor in those counties in which a county assessor is elected
pursuant to Section 3-45 of the Property Tax Code, when a change in ownership
occurs in a mobile home located in such a park or on such land.  Such
notification shall include the same information for the new owner
as that contained in the registration form required of mobile home park
operators and mobile home owners by Section 4 of this Act. (Source: P.A. 92-807, eff. 1-1-03.) (35 ILCS 515/11) (from Ch. 120, par. 1211)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 81-1137.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-11">
            <num>11</num>
            <heading>Before any mobile home subject to the tax imposed by this
Act may be moved, the transporting company must obtain a permit from the
county treasurer certifying that the tax on the mobile home has been
paid for the current tax period and all previous tax periods for which taxes
remain due</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-515-11__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>any person or entity who moves a mobile
home
or causes it to be moved pursuant to a court order, nor does this
Section apply to any person or municipality that moves a mobile home under the
Abandoned Mobile Home Act or (ii) a mobile home park owner that moves an abandoned mobile home for its disposal as scrap or otherwise without further use as a mobile home.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 94-358, eff. 7-29-05.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-12">
            <num>12</num>
            <heading>It shall be a Class B misdemeanor to fail to submit
information required under this Act or to knowingly submit any false
information under this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 79-1184.) (35 ILCS 515/13) (from Ch. 120, par. 1213)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 79-1184.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-13">
            <num>13</num>
            <heading>If any provision of this Act or the application thereof
to any person or circumstance is held invalid, such invalidity does not affect
other provisions or applications of this Act which can be given effect without the
invalid application or provision, and to this end the provisions of this Act
are declared to be severable</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 79-1184.) (35 ILCS 515/14) (from Ch. 120, par. 1214)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 79-1184.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-515-14">
            <num>14</num>
            <heading>This Act shall be known and may be cited as the &quot;Mobile Home
Local Services Tax Act&quot;</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 79-1184.) This site is maintained for the Illinois General Assembly by the
                        Legislative Information System, 705 Stratton Building, Springfield, Illinois 62706. Co</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 79-1184.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>