<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-105"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-105"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35-105"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-105/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-105/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-105/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-105/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Revenue</heading>
        <article eId="chp_35__art_105">
          <num>35 ILCS 105/</num>
          <heading>Use Tax Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>This Act shall be known and may be cited as the &quot;Use Tax Act&quot;</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.) (35 ILCS 105/1.05) Sec. 1.05. Legislative intent; leases. It is the intent of the General Assembly in enacting this amendatory Act of the 103rd General Assembly to apply the tax imposed under this Act, except as otherwise provided in this Act, to the privilege of using in this State tangible personal property, other than motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and semitrailers, as defined in Section 1-187 of the Illinois Vehicle Code, that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, leased at retail from a retailer, for leases in effect, entered into, or renewed on or after January 1, 2025. (Source: P.A. 103-592, eff. 1-1-25 .) (35 ILCS 105/1a) (from Ch. 120, par. 439.1a)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-1a">
            <num>1a</num>
            <heading>A person who is engaged in the business of leasing or renting
motor vehicles to others and who, in connection with such business sells
any used motor vehicle to a purchaser for his use and not for the purpose
of resale, is a retailer engaged in the business of selling tangible personal
property at retail under this Act to the extent of the value of the vehicle
sold</heading>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of this Section, &quot;motor vehicle&quot; has the meaning prescribed
in Section 1-157 of the Illinois Vehicle Code, as now or hereafter amended.
(Nothing provided herein shall affect liability incurred under this Act
because of the use of such motor vehicles as a lessor.)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 80-598 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-2">
            <num>2</num>
            <heading>Definitions</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>which is sold in the regular course of business or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>which the person incorporating such ingredient or constituent therein has undertaken at the time of such purchase to cause to be transported in interstate commerce to destinations outside the State of Illinois: Provided that the property purchased is deemed to be purchased for the purpose of resale, despite first being used, to the extent to which it is resold as an ingredient of an intentionally produced product or by-product of manufacturing. &quot;Lease&quot; means a transfer of the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use, but not title to, tangible personal property for a fixed or indeterminate term for consideration, regardless of the name by which the transaction is called. &quot;Lease&quot; does not include a lease entered into merely as a security agreement that does not involve a transfer of possession or control from the lessor to the lessee. On and after January 1, 2025, the term &quot;sale&quot;, when used in this Act, includes a lease. &quot;Watercraft&quot; means a Class 2, Class 3, or Class 4 watercraft as defined in Section 3-2 of the Boat Registration and Safety Act, a personal watercraft, or any boat equipped with an inboard motor. &quot;Purchase at retail&quot; means the acquisition of the ownership of, the title to, the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use, tangible personal property through a sale at retail. &quot;Purchaser&quot; means anyone who, through a sale at retail, acquires the ownership of, the title to, the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use, tangible personal property for a valuable consideration. &quot;Sale at retail&quot; means any transfer of the ownership of or title to tangible personal property to a purchaser, for the purpose of use, and not for the purpose of resale in any form as tangible personal property to the extent not first subjected to a use for which it was purchased, for a valuable consideration: Provided that the property purchased is deemed to be purchased for t</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-592, eff. 1-1-25; 104-6, eff. 6-16-25; 104-417, eff. 8-15-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-2a">
            <num>2a</num>
            <heading>&quot;Pollution control facilities&quot; means any system, method,
construction, device or appliance appurtenant thereto sold or used or
intended for the primary purpose of eliminating, preventing, or reducing
air and water pollution as the term &quot;air pollution&quot; or &quot;water pollution&quot; is
defined in the &quot;Environmental Protection Act&quot;, enacted by the 76th General
Assembly, or for the primary purpose of treating, pretreating, modifying or
disposing of any potential solid, liquid or gaseous pollutant which if
released without such treatment, pretreatment, modification or disposal
might be harmful, detrimental or offensive to human, plant or animal life,
or to property</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2003, the purchase, employment and transfer of such
tangible personal property
as pollution control facilities is not a purchase, use or sale of tangible
personal property.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 93-24, eff. 6-20-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-2b">
            <num>2b</num>
            <heading>&quot;Selling price&quot; shall not include any amounts added to prices by sellers
on account of the seller's duty to collect any tax imposed under the
&quot;Regional Transportation Authority Act&quot;, enacted by the 78th General
Assembly</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 78-3rd S.S.-12.) (35 ILCS 105/2c) (from Ch. 120, par. 439.2c)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 78-3rd S.S.-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-2c">
            <num>2c</num>
            <heading>For purposes of this Act, a corporation, limited liability
company, society, association,
foundation or institution organized and operated exclusively for educational
purposes shall include:  all tax-supported public schools; private schools
which offer systematic instruction in useful branches of learning by methods
common to public schools and which compare favorably in their scope and
intensity
with the course of study presented in tax-supported schools; licensed day
care centers as defined in Section 2</heading>
            <content>
              <p>09 of the Child Care Act of 1969 which
are operated by a not for profit corporation, society, association,
foundation, institution or organization; vocational
or technical schools or institutes organized and operated exclusively to
provide a course of study of not less than 6 weeks duration and designed
to prepare individuals to follow a trade or to pursue a manual, technical,
mechanical, industrial, business or commercial occupation. However, a corporation, limited liability company, society, association,
foundation or institution
organized and operated for the purpose of offering professional, trade or
business seminars of short duration, self-improvement or personality
development
courses, courses which are avocational or recreational in nature, courses
pursued entirely by open circuit television or radio, correspondence courses,
or courses which do not provide specialized training within a specific
vocational
or technical
field shall not be considered to be organized and operated exclusively for
educational purposes.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-480.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-2d">
            <num>2d</num>
            <heading>Marketplace facilitators and marketplace sellers</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this Section: &quot;Affiliate&quot; means a person that, with respect to another person:</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>has a direct or indirect ownership interest of more than 5 percent in the other person; or (ii) is related to the other person because a third person, or a group of third persons who are affiliated with each other as defined in this subsection, holds a direct or indirect ownership interest of more than 5% in the related person. &quot;Marketplace&quot; means a physical or electronic place, forum, platform, application, or other method by which a marketplace seller sells or offers to sell items. &quot;Marketplace facilitator&quot; means a person who, pursuant to an agreement with an unrelated third-party marketplace seller, directly or indirectly through one or more affiliates facilitates a retail sale by an unrelated third party marketplace seller by:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>listing or advertising for sale by the marketplace seller in a marketplace, tangible personal property that is subject to tax under this Act; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>either directly or indirectly, through agreements or arrangements with third parties, collecting payment from the customer and transmitting that payment to the marketplace seller regardless of whether the marketplace facilitator receives compensation or other consideration in exchange for its services. &quot;Marketplace seller&quot; means a person that sells or offers to sell tangible personal property through a marketplace operated by an unrelated third-party marketplace facilitator.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning on January 1, 2020 and through December 31, 2025, a marketplace facilitator who meets either of the following thresholds is considered the retailer for each sale of tangible personal property made through its marketplace:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cumulative gross receipts from sales of tangible personal property to purchasers in Illinois by the marketplace facilitator and by marketplace sellers selling through the marketplace are $100,000 or more; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the marketplace facilitator and marketplace sellers selling through the marketplace cumulatively enter into 200 or more separate transactions for the sale of tangible personal property to purchasers in Illinois. A marketplace facilitator shall determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether the marketplace facilitator meets the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this subsection</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for the preceding 12-month period. If the marketplace facilitator meets the threshold of either paragraph</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a 12-month period, the marketplace facilitator is considered a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State and is required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act and file returns for one year. At the end of that one-year period, the marketplace facilitator shall determine whether the marketplace facilitator met the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during the preceding 12-month period. If the marketplace facilitator met the threshold in either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the preceding 12-month period, the marketplace facilitator is considered a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State and is required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act and file returns for the subsequent year. If at the end of a one-year period a marketplace facilitator that was required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act determines that the marketplace facilitator did not meet the threshold in either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during the preceding 12-month period, the marketplace facilitator shall subsequently determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether the marketplace facilitator meets the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the preceding 12-month period. (b-5) Beginning on January 1, 2026, a marketplace facilitator whose cumulative gross receipts from sales of tangible personal property to purchasers in Illinois by the marketplace facilitator and by marketplace sellers selling through the marketplace are $100,000 or more is considered the retailer for each sale of tangible personal property made through its marketplace. A marketplace facilitator shall determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether the marketplace facilitator meets the threshold in this subsection (b-5) for the preceding 12-month period. If the marketplace facilitator meets the threshold for a 12-month period, the marketplace facilitator is considered a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State and is required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act and file returns for one year. At the end of the one-year period, the marketplace facilitator shall determine whether the marketplace facilitator met the threshold during the preceding 12-month period. If the marketplace facilitator met the threshold for the preceding 12-month period, the marketplace facilitator is considered a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State and is required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act and file returns for the subsequent year. If at the end of a one-year period a marketplace facilitator that was required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act determines that the marketplace facilitator did not meet the threshold during the preceding 12-month period, the marketplace facilitator shall subsequently determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether the marketplace facilitator meets the threshold for the preceding 12-month period.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning on January 1, 2020 a marketplace facilitator considered to be the retailer pursuant to subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b-5) of this Section is considered the retailer with respect to each sale made through its marketplace and is liable for collecting and remitting the tax under this Act on all such sales. The marketplace facilitator who is considered to be the retailer under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b-5) for sales made through its marketplace has all the rights and duties, and is required to comply with the same requirements and procedures, as all other retailers maintaining a place of business in this State who are registered or who are required to be registered to collect and remit the tax imposed by this Act with respect to such sales.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A marketplace facilitator shall:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certify to each marketplace seller that the marketplace facilitator assumes the rights and duties of a retailer under this Act with respect to sales made by the marketplace seller through the marketplace; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect taxes imposed by this Act as required by Section 3-45 of this Act for sales made through the marketplace.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A marketplace seller shall retain books and records for all sales made through a marketplace in accordance with the requirements of Section 11.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A marketplace seller shall furnish to the marketplace facilitator information that is necessary for the marketplace facilitator to correctly collect and remit taxes for a retail sale. The information may include a certification that an item being sold is taxable, not taxable, exempt from taxation, or taxable at a specified rate. A marketplace seller shall be held harmless for liability for the tax imposed under this Act when a marketplace facilitator fails to correctly collect and remit tax after having been provided with information by a marketplace seller to correctly collect and remit taxes imposed under this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the marketplace facilitator demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Department that its failure to correctly collect and remit tax on a retail sale resulted from the marketplace facilitator's good faith reliance on incorrect or insufficient information provided by a marketplace seller, it shall be relieved of liability for the tax on that retail sale. In this case, a marketplace seller is liable for any resulting tax due.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>(Blank).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-2d__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Section does not affect the tax liability of a pu</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-3">
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>Tax imposed</heading>
            <content>
              <p>A tax is imposed upon the privilege of using in this State tangible personal property purchased, which, on and after January 1, 2025, includes leased, at retail from a retailer, including computer software, and including photographs, negatives, and positives that are the product of photoprocessing, but not including products of photoprocessing produced for use in motion pictures for commercial exhibition. Beginning January 1, 2001, prepaid telephone calling arrangements shall be considered tangible personal property subject to the tax imposed under this Act regardless of the form in which those arrangements may be embodied, transmitted, or fixed by any method now known or hereafter developed. Purchases of (1) electricity delivered to customers by wire; (2) natural or artificial gas that is delivered to customers through pipes, pipelines, or mains; and (3) water that is delivered to customers through pipes, pipelines, or mains are not subject to tax under this Act. The provisions of this amendatory Act of the 98th General Assembly are declaratory of existing law as to the meaning and scope of this Act. The imposition of the tax under this Act on the privilege of using tangible personal property leased at retail applies to leases of tangible personal property in effect, entered into, or renewed on or after January 1, 2025. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor, in collecting the tax, may collect for each tax return period, only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. The inclusion of leases in the tax imposed under this Act by this amendatory Act of the 103rd General Assembly does not, however, extend to motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and semitrailers, as defined in Section 1-187 of the Illinois Vehicle Code, that are required to be registered with an agency of this State. The taxation of these items shall continue in effect as prior to the effective date of the changes made to this Section by this amendatory Act of the 103rd General Assembly (i.e. dealers owe retailers' occupation tax, lessors owe use tax, and lessees are not subject to retailers' occupation or use tax).</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-592, eff. 1-1-25 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-3a">
            <num>3a</num>
            <heading>The tax imposed by the Act shall when collected be stated as
a distinct item separate and apart from the selling price of the tangible
personal property</heading>
            <content>
              <p>However, where it is not possible to state the sales
tax separately in situations such as sales from vending machines or sales
of liquor by the drink the Department may by rule exempt such sales from
this requirement so long as purchasers are notified by a sign that the tax
is included in the selling price. In addition, retailers who sell items that would have been taxed at the 1% rate but for the 0% rate imposed under this amendatory Act of the 102nd General Assembly shall, to the extent feasible, include the following statement on any cash register tape, receipt, invoice, or sales ticket issued to customers: &quot;From July 1, 2022 through July 1, 2023, the State of Illinois sales tax on groceries is 0%.&quot;. If it is not feasible for the retailer to include the statement on any cash register tape, receipt, invoice, or sales ticket issued to customers, then the retailer shall  post the statement on a sign that is clearly visible to customers. The sign shall be no smaller than 4 inches by 8 inches.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 102-700, eff. 4-19-22.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-4">
            <num>4</num>
            <heading>Evidence that tangible personal property was sold by any person for
delivery to a person residing or engaged in business in this State shall be
prima facie evidence that such tangible personal property was sold for use
in this State</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.) (35 ILCS 105/5) (from Ch. 120, par. 439.5)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-5">
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>Except as to motor vehicles and other items of tangible personal
property that must be titled or registered under an Illinois
law, but that cannot be so titled or registered without a use
tax receipt or exemption determination from the Department, every retailer
maintaining a place of business in this State and making sales of tangible
personal property for use in this State (whether those sales
are made within or without this State) shall, when collecting the tax as
provided in Section 3-45 of this Act from the purchaser, give to
the purchaser (if demanded by the purchaser) a receipt for the tax in
the manner and form prescribed by the Department</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The receipt shall
be sufficient to relieve the purchaser from further
liability for the tax to which the receipt may refer. Each retailer
shall list with the Department the names and addresses of
all of his or her agents operating in this State and the location
of any and all of his or her distribution or sales houses, offices,
or other places of business in this State.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 86-1475.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-6">
            <num>6</num>
            <heading>A retailer maintaining a place of business in this State, if
required to register under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, need not
obtain an additional Certificate of Registration under this Act, but shall
be deemed to be sufficiently registered by virtue of his being registered
under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Every retailer maintaining a place
of business in this State, if not required to register under the Retailers'
Occupation Tax Act, shall apply to the Department (upon a form prescribed
and furnished by the Department) for a Certificate of Registration under
this Act. In completing such application, the applicant shall furnish such
information as the Department may reasonably require. Upon approval of an
application for Certificate of Registration, the Department shall issue,
without charge, a Certificate of Registration to the applicant. Such
Certificate of Registration shall be displayed at the address which the
applicant states in his application to be the principal place of business
or location from which he will act as a retailer in this State. If the
applicant will act as a retailer in this State from other places of
business or locations, he shall list the addresses of such additional
places of business or locations in this application for Certificate of
Registration, and the Department shall issue a Sub-Certificate of
Registration to the applicant for each such additional place of business or
location. Each Sub-Certificate of Registration shall be conspicuously
displayed at the place for which it is issued. Such Sub-Certificate of
Registration shall bear the same registration number as that appearing upon
the Certificate of Registration to which such Sub-Certificates relate.
Where a retailer operates more than one place of business which is subject
to registration under this Section and such businesses are substantially
different in character or are engaged in under different trade names or are
engaged in under other substantially dissimilar circumstances (so that it
is more practicable, from an accounting, auditing or bookkeeping
standpoint, for such businesses to be separately registered), the
Department may require or permit such person to apply for and obtain a
separate Certificate of Registration for each such business or for any of
such businesses instead of registering such person, as to all such
businesses, under a single Certificate of Registration supplemented by
related Sub-Certificates of Registration. No Certificate of Registration
shall be issued to any person who is in default to the State of Illinois
for moneys due hereunder. The Department may, in its discretion, upon application, authorize the
collection of the tax herein imposed by any retailer not maintaining a
place of business within this State, who, to the satisfaction of the
Department, furnishes adequate security to insure collection and payment of
the tax. Such retailer shall be issued, without charge, a permit to collect
such tax. When so authorized, it shall be the duty of such retailer to
collect the tax upon all tangible personal property sold to his knowledge
for use within this State, in the same manner and subject to the same
requirements, including the furnishing of a receipt to the purchaser (if
demanded by the purchaser), as a retailer maintaining a place of business
within this State. The receipt given to the purchaser shall be sufficient
to relieve him from further liability for the tax to which such receipt may
refer. Such permit may be revoked by the Department as provided herein.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-7">
            <num>7</num>
            <heading>It is unlawful for any retailer to advertise or hold out or state to the
public or to any purchaser, consumer or user, directly or indirectly, that
the tax or any part thereof imposed by Section 3 hereof will be assumed or
absorbed by the retailer or that it will not be added to the selling price
of the property sold, or if added that it or any part thereof will be
refunded other than when the retailer refunds the selling price and tax
because of the merchandise's being returned to the retailer or other than
when the retailer credits or refunds the tax to the purchaser to support a
claim filed with the Department under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act or
under this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Any person violating any of the provisions of this Section
within this State shall be guilty of a Class A misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 77-2830 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-8">
            <num>8</num>
            <heading>Any retailer required to collect the tax imposed by this Act shall
be liable to the Department for such tax, whether or not the tax has been
collected by the retailer, except when the retailer is relieved of the duty of
remitting the tax to the Department by virtue of having paid a tax imposed by
the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act upon his or her gross receipts from the
same transactions</heading>
            <content>
              <p>To the extent that a retailer required to collect the tax
imposed by this Act has actually collected that tax, such tax is held in trust
for the benefit of the Department.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 91-203, eff. 7-20-99.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-9">
            <num>9</num>
            <heading>Except as to motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, each retailer required or authorized to collect the tax imposed by this Act shall pay to the Department the amount of such tax (except as otherwise provided) at the time when he is required to file his return for the period during which such tax was collected, less a discount of 2</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-9__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 49 U.S.C. 47133. When determining the discount allowed under this Section, retailers shall include the amount of tax that would have been due at the 1% rate but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700. In the case of retailers who report and pay the tax on a transaction by transaction basis, as provided in this Section, such discount shall be taken with each such tax remittance instead of when such retailer files his periodic return, but, beginning with returns due on or after January 1, 2025, the discount allowed under this Section and the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, including any local tax administered by the Department and reported on the same transaction return, shall not exceed $1,000 per month for all transaction returns filed during the month. The discount allowed under this Section is allowed only for returns that are filed in the manner required by this Act. The Department may disallow the discount for retailers whose certificate of registration is revoked at the time the return is filed, but only if the Department's decision to revoke the certificate of registration has become final. A retailer need not remit that part of any tax collected by him to the extent that he is required to remit and does remit the tax imposed by the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, with respect to the sale of the same property. Where such tangible personal property is sold under a conditional sales contract, or under any other form of sale wherein the payment of the principal sum, or a part thereof, is extended beyond the close of the period for which the return is filed, the retailer, in collecting the tax (except as to motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State), may collect for each tax return period only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor, in collecti</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-154, eff. 6-30-23; 103-363, eff. 7-28-23; 103-592, Article 75, Section 75-5, eff. 1-1-25; 103-592, Article 110, Section 110-5, eff. 6-7-24; 103-1055, eff. 12-20-24; 104-6, Article 5, Section 5-10, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-9">
            <num>9</num>
            <heading>Except as to motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, each retailer required or authorized to collect the tax imposed by this Act shall pay to the Department the amount of such tax (except as otherwise provided) at the time when he is required to file his return for the period during which such tax was collected, less a discount of 2</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-9__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 49 U.S.C. 47133. When determining the discount allowed under this Section, retailers shall include the amount of tax that would have been due at the 1% rate but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700. In the case of retailers who report and pay the tax on a transaction by transaction basis, as provided in this Section, such discount shall be taken with each such tax remittance instead of when such retailer files his periodic return, but, beginning with returns due on or after January 1, 2025, the discount allowed under this Section and the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, including any local tax administered by the Department and reported on the same transaction return, shall not exceed $1,000 per month for all transaction returns filed during the month. The discount allowed under this Section is allowed only for returns that are filed in the manner required by this Act. The Department may disallow the discount for retailers whose certificate of registration is revoked at the time the return is filed, but only if the Department's decision to revoke the certificate of registration has become final. A retailer need not remit that part of any tax collected by him to the extent that he is required to remit and does remit the tax imposed by the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, with respect to the sale of the same property. Where such tangible personal property is sold under a conditional sales contract, or under any other form of sale wherein the payment of the principal sum, or a part thereof, is extended beyond the close of the period for which the return is filed, the retailer, in collecting the tax (except as to motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State), may collect for each tax return period only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor, in collecti</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-154, eff. 6-30-23; 103-363, eff. 7-28-23; 103-592, Article 75, Section 75-5, eff. 1-1-25; 103-592, Article 110, Section 110-5, eff. 6-7-24; 103-1055, eff. 12-20-24; 104-6, Article 35, Section 35-20, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-10">
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>Except as to motor vehicles, aircraft, watercraft, and
trailers, and except as to cigarettes as defined in the Cigarette Use Tax Act, when tangible personal
property is
purchased from a retailer for use in this State by a purchaser
who did not pay the tax imposed by this Act to the retailer, and a purchaser who does not
file returns with the Department as a retailer under Section 9 of this
Act, such purchaser (by the last day of the month following the calendar
month in which such purchaser makes any payment upon the selling price of
such property) shall, except as otherwise provided in this Section, file
a return with the Department and pay the tax upon that portion of the
selling price so paid by the purchaser during the preceding calendar month</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-105-10__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a
purchaser of motor vehicles,
aircraft, watercraft, or trailers who is a retailer of motor vehicles,
aircraft, watercraft, or trailers purchases more than one motor vehicle,
aircraft, watercraft, or trailer for the purpose of resale or (ii) a purchaser
of motor vehicles, aircraft, watercraft, or trailers purchases more
than one motor vehicle, aircraft, watercraft, or trailer for use as qualifying
rolling stock as provided in Section 3-55 of this Act, then the purchaser may
report the purchase of all motor vehicles, aircraft, watercraft, or trailers
involved in that transaction to the Department on a single return prescribed by
the Department.  Such return in the case of motor vehicles and
aircraft must show the name and address of the seller, the name, address of
purchaser, the amount of the selling price including the amount allowed by
the retailer for traded in property, if any; the amount allowed by the
retailer for the traded-in tangible personal property, if any, to the
extent to which Section 2 of this Act allows an exemption for the value of
traded-in property; the balance payable after deducting such trade-in
allowance from the total selling price; the amount of tax due from the
purchaser with respect to such transaction; the amount of tax collected
from the purchaser by the retailer on such transaction (or satisfactory
evidence that such tax is not due in that particular instance if that is
claimed to be the fact); the place and date of the sale, a sufficient
identification of the property sold, and such other information as the
Department may reasonably require. Such return shall be filed not later than 30 days after such motor
vehicle or aircraft is brought into this State for use. For purposes of this Section, &quot;watercraft&quot; means a Class 2, Class 3, or
Class 4 watercraft as defined in Section 3-2 of the Boat Registration and
Safety Act, a personal watercraft, or any boat equipped with an inboard
motor. The return and tax remitt</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-321, eff. 8-24-17; 100-1171, eff. 1-4-19.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-10a">
            <num>10a</num>
            <heading>Notwithstanding any other provision to the contrary, any person
who is required to file a bond pursuant to any provision of this Act and
who has continuously complied with all provisions of this Act for 24 or
more consecutive months, shall no longer be required to comply with the
bonding provisions of this Act so long as such person continues his compliance
with the provisions of this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 84-1408.) (35 ILCS 105/10.5) Sec. 10.5. Individual use tax amnesty. The Department shall establish an amnesty program for all individual taxpayers owing any tax imposed under this Act for their purchases of tangible personal property from a retailer for use in this State (eligible taxes). The amnesty program shall be for a period from January 1, 2011 through October 15, 2011. The amnesty program shall provide that, upon payment by an individual taxpayer of all eligible taxes due from that taxpayer under this Act for any taxable period ending after June 30, 2004 and prior to January 1, 2011, the Department shall abate and not seek to collect any interest or penalties that may be applicable and the Department shall not seek civil or criminal prosecution for any taxpayer for these taxes for the period of time for which amnesty has been granted to the taxpayer. Failure to pay all eligible taxes due to the State for a taxable period shall invalidate any amnesty granted under this Section. Amnesty shall be granted only if all amnesty conditions are satisfied by the taxpayer. Amnesty shall not be granted to business taxpayers. Amnesty shall not be granted to taxpayers who are a party to any criminal investigation or to any civil or criminal litigation that is pending in any circuit court or appellate court or the Supreme Court of this State for nonpayment, delinquency, or fraud in relation to eligible taxes under this Act.  Amnesty shall not be granted to any taxpayer who is under audit for eligible taxes or who is contacted in writing by the Department concerning eligible taxes prior to the taxpayer reporting and paying the eligible taxes. Voluntary payments made under this Section shall be made by cash, check, guaranteed remittance, or ACH debit. (Source: P.A. 96-1388, eff. 7-29-10.) (35 ILCS 105/11) (from Ch. 120, par. 439.11)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 84-1408.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-11">
            <num>11</num>
            <heading>Every retailer required or authorized to collect taxes hereunder
and every person using in this State tangible personal property purchased
at retail from a retailer on or after the effective date hereof shall keep
such records, receipts, invoices and other pertinent books, documents,
memoranda and papers as the Department shall require, in such form as the
Department shall require</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The Department may adopt rules that establish
requirements, including record forms and formats, for records required to be
kept and maintained by taxpayers. For purposes of this Section, &quot;records&quot; means
all data maintained by the taxpayer, including data on paper, microfilm,
microfiche or any type of machine-sensible data compilation. For the purpose of
administering and enforcing the provisions hereof, the Department, or any
officer or employee of the Department designated, in writing, by the Director
thereof, may hold investigations and hearings concerning any matters covered
herein and may examine any books, papers, records, documents or memoranda of
any retailer or purchaser bearing upon the sales or purchases of tangible
personal property, the privilege of using which is taxed hereunder, and may
require the attendance of such person or any officer or employee of such
person, or of any person having knowledge of the facts, and may take testimony
and require proof for its information. Any person who fails to keep books and records or fails to produce books and records for examination, as required by this Section and the rules adopted by the Department, is liable to pay to the Department, for deposit into the Tax Compliance and Administration Fund, a penalty of $1,000 for the first failure to keep books and records or produce books and records for examination and a penalty of $3,000 for each subsequent failure to keep books and records or produce books and records for examination as required by this Section and the rules adopted by the Department. The penalties imposed under this Section shall not apply if the taxpayer shows that he or she acted with ordinary business care and prudence. The Department may adopt rules to administer the penalties under this Section.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-940, eff. 8-17-18.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-12">
            <num>12</num>
            <heading>Applicability of Retailers' Occupation Tax Act and Uniform Penalty and Interest Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>All of the provisions of Sections 1d, 1e, 1f, 1i, 1j, 1j.1, 1k, 1m, 1n, 1o, 2-6, 2-12, 2-29, 2-54, 2a, 2b, 2c, 3, 4 (except that the time limitation provisions shall run from the date when the tax is due rather than from the date when gross receipts are received), 5 (except that the time limitation provisions on the issuance of notices of tax liability shall run from the date when the tax is due rather than from the date when gross receipts are received and except that in the case of a failure to file a return required by this Act, no notice of tax liability shall be issued on and after each July 1 and January 1 covering tax due with that return during any month or period more than 6 years before that July 1 or January 1, respectively), 5a, 5b, 5c, 5d, 5e, 5f, 5g, 5h, 5j, 5k, 5l, 5m, 5n, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 and 12 of the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act and Section 3-7 of the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act, which are not inconsistent with this Act, shall apply, as far as practicable, to the subject matter of this Act to the same extent as if such provisions were included herein.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 102-700, eff. 4-19-22; 103-9, eff. 6-7-23; 103-595, eff. 6-26-24.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-12a">
            <num>12a</num>
            <heading>Any non-resident of this State who accepts the privilege extended
by the laws of this State to non-residents of acting as a retailer
maintaining a place of business in this State within the meaning of Section
2 of this Act, and any resident of this State who incurs tax liability
under this Act as a seller and who subsequently removes from this State or
conceals his whereabouts, and any person (resident or non-resident) who
incurs tax liability under this Act as a user in this State and who removes
from this State or conceals his whereabouts, shall be deemed thereby to
appoint the Secretary of State of Illinois his agent for the service of
process or notice in any judicial or administrative proceeding under this
Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Such process or notice shall be served by the Department on the
Secretary of State by leaving, at the office of the Secretary of State at
least 15 days before the return day of such process or notice, a true and
certified copy thereof, and by sending to the taxpayer by registered or
certified mail, postage prepaid, a like and true certified copy, with an
endorsement thereon of the service upon said Secretary of State, addressed
to such taxpayer at his last known address. Service of process or notice in the manner provided for in this Section,
under the circumstances specified in this Section, shall be of the same
force and validity as if served upon the taxpayer personally within this
State. Proof of such service upon the taxpayer in this State through the
Secretary of State as his agent and by mailing to the last known address of
the taxpayer may be made in such judicial or administrative proceeding by
the affidavit of the Director of Revenue, or by his duly authorized
representative who made such service, with a copy of the process or notice
that was so served attached to such affidavit.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1961, p. 1945.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-12b">
            <num>12b</num>
            <heading>The Illinois Administrative Procedure Act is hereby expressly
adopted and shall apply to all administrative rules and procedures of the
Department of Revenue under this Act, except that (1) paragraph (b) of Section
5-10 of the Illinois Administrative Procedure Act does not apply
to final orders, decisions and opinions of the Department, (2) subparagraph
(a)2 of Section 5-10 of the Illinois Administrative Procedure Act
does not apply to forms established by the Department for use under this Act,
and (3) the provisions of Section 10-45 of the Illinois
Administrative Procedure Act regarding proposals for decision are excluded and
not applicable to the Department under this Act to the extent Section 10-45 applies to hearings not otherwise delegated to the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.) (35 ILCS 105/13) (from Ch. 120, par. 439.13)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-13">
            <num>13</num>
            <heading>Whenever any retailer not maintaining a place of business in this
State, to whom a permit to collect the tax hereby imposed has been issued
pursuant to Section 6 hereof, fails to comply with any of the provisions
hereof or any orders, rules or regulations of the Department prescribed and
adopted hereunder, or when the Department considers the security furnished
by such retailer to be inadequate or considers that the tax can be
collected more effectively from persons using such property in this State,
the Department may, upon notice and hearing as herein provided, by order
revoke the permit issued to such retailer</heading>
            <content>
              <p>No order authorized by this
Section shall be made until the retailer is given an opportunity to be
heard and to show cause why such order shall not be made, and he shall be
given at least 7 days' notice of the time, place and purpose of such
hearing. The Department shall have the power in its discretion to issue a
new permit pursuant to Section 6 hereof after such revocation.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-14">
            <num>14</num>
            <heading>When the amount due is under $300, any person subject to
the provisions hereof who fails to file a
return, or who violates any other provision of Section 9 or Section 10 hereof,
or who fails to keep books and records as required herein, or who files a
fraudulent return, or who wilfully violates any rule or regulation of the
Department for the administration and enforcement of the provisions hereof,
or any officer or agent of a corporation or manager, member, or agent of a
limited liability company subject hereto who signs a fraudulent return filed on
behalf of such corporation or limited liability company, or any accountant or
other agent who knowingly enters false information on the return of any
taxpayer under this Act, or any person who violates any of the provisions
of Sections 3, 5 or 7 hereof, or any purchaser who obtains a registration
number or resale number from the Department through misrepresentation, or
who represents to a seller that such purchaser has a registration number or
a resale number from the Department when he knows that he does not, or who
uses his registration number or resale number to make a seller believe that
he is buying tangible personal property for resale when such purchaser in
fact knows that this is not the case, is guilty of a Class 4 felony</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who violates any provision of Section 6 hereof, or who
engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail
after his Certificate of Registration under this Act has been revoked in
accordance with Section 12 of this Act, is guilty of a Class 4 felony.
Each day any such person is engaged in business in violation of Section 6,
or after his Certificate of Registration under this Act has been revoked,
constitutes a separate offense. When the amount due is under $300, any person who accepts money that
is due to the Department under this Act from a taxpayer for the purpose of
acting as the taxpayer's agent to make the payment to the Department, but who
fails to remit such payment to the Department when due is guilty of a Class 4
felony.
Any such person who purports to make such payment by issuing or delivering
a check or other order upon a real or fictitious depository for the payment
of money, knowing that it will not be paid by the depository, shall be guilty
of a deceptive practice in violation of Section 17-1 of the Criminal Code
of 2012. When the amount due is $300 or more any person subject to the provisions
hereof who fails to file a return or who violates any other provision of
Section 9 or Section 10 hereof or who fails to keep books and records as
required herein or who files a fraudulent return, or who wilfully violates
any rule or regulation of the Department for the administration and
enforcement of the provisions hereof, or any officer or agent of a
corporation or manager, member, or agent of a limited liability company
subject hereto who signs a fraudulent return filed on behalf of
such corporation or limited liability company, or any accountant or other
agent who knowingly enters false information on the return of any taxpayer
under this Act or any person who violates any of the provisions of Sections 3,
5 or 7 hereof or any purchaser who obtains a registration number or resale
number from the Department through misrepresentation, or who represents to a
seller that such purchaser has a registration number or a resale number from
the Department when he knows that he does not or who uses his registration
number or resale number to make a seller believe that he is buying tangible
personal property for resale when such purchaser in fact knows that this is not
the case, is guilty of a Class 3 felony. When the amount due is $300 or more any person who accepts money that is
due to the Department under this Act from a taxpayer for the purpose of
acting as the taxpayer's agent to make the payment to the Department, but who
fails to remit such payment to the Department when due is guilty of a Class
3 felony.  Any such person who purports to make such payment by issuing or
delivering a check or other order upon a real or fictitious depository for
the payment of money, knowing that it will not be paid by the depository
shall be guilty of a deceptive practice in violation of Section 17-1 of the
Criminal Code of 2012. Any seller who collects or attempts to collect use tax measured by
receipts which such seller knows are not subject to use tax, or any seller
who knowingly over-collects or attempts to over-collect use tax in a
transaction which is subject to the tax that is imposed by this Act, shall
be guilty of a Class 4 felony for each such offense. This paragraph
does not apply to an amount collected by the seller as use tax on receipts
which are subject to tax under this Act as long as such collection is made
in compliance with the tax collection brackets prescribed by the Department
in its Rules and Regulations. Any taxpayer or agent of a taxpayer who with the intent to defraud
purports to make a payment due to the Department by issuing or delivering a
check or other order upon a real or fictitious depository for the payment
of money, knowing that it will not be paid by the depository, shall be
guilty of a deceptive practice in violation of Section 17-1 of the Criminal
Code of 2012. Any person who knowingly sells, purchases, installs, transfers, possesses, uses, or accesses any automated sales suppression device, zapper, or phantom-ware in this State is guilty of a Class 3 felony. For the purposes of this Section: &quot;Automated sales suppression device&quot; or &quot;zapper&quot; means a software program that falsifies the electronic records of an electronic cash register or other point-of-sale system, including, but not limited to, transaction data and transaction reports.  The term includes the software program, any device that carries the software program, or an Internet link to the software program. &quot;Phantom-ware&quot; means a hidden programming option embedded in the operating system of an electronic cash register or hardwired into an electronic cash register that can be used to create a second set of records or that can eliminate or manipulate transaction records in an electronic cash register. &quot;Electronic cash register&quot; means a device that keeps a register or supporting documents through the use of an electronic device or computer system designed to record transaction data for the purpose of computing, compiling, or processing retail sales transaction data in any manner. &quot;Transaction data&quot; includes: items purchased by a customer; the price of each item; a taxability determination for each item; a segregated tax amount for each taxed item; the amount of cash or credit tendered; the net amount returned to the customer in change; the date and time of the purchase; the name, address, and identification number of the vendor; and the receipt or invoice number of the transaction. &quot;Transaction report&quot; means a report that documents, without limitation, the sales, taxes, or fees collected, media totals, and discount voids at an electronic cash register and that is printed on a cash register tape at the end of a day or shift, or a report that documents every action at an electronic cash register and is stored electronically. A prosecution for any act in violation of this Section may be commenced
at any time within 3 years of the commission of that Act. This Section does not apply if the violation in a particular case also
constitutes a criminal violation of the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1150, eff. 1-25-13; 98-352, eff. 1-1-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-15">
            <num>15</num>
            <heading>The tax herein imposed shall be in addition to all other
occupation or privilege taxes imposed by the State of Illinois or by any
municipal corporation or political subdivision thereof</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Any taxpayer or agent of a taxpayer who with the intent to defraud
purports to make a payment due to the Department by issuing or delivering a
check or other order upon a real or fictitious depository for the payment
of money, knowing that it will not be paid by the depository, shall be
guilty of a deceptive practice in violation of Section 17-1 of the Criminal
Code of 2012.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1150, eff. 1-25-13.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-18">
            <num>18</num>
            <heading>If any clause, sentence, Section, provision or part of this Act or
the application thereof to any person or circumstance shall be adjudged to
be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act or its application to
persons or circumstances other than those to which it is held invalid,
shall not be affected thereby</heading>
            <content>
              <p>In particular, if any provision which
exempts or has the effect of exempting some class of users or some kind of
use from the tax imposed by this Act should be held to constitute or to
result in an invalid classification or to be unconstitutional for some
other reason, such provision shall be deemed to be severable, with the
remainder of this Act without said provision being held constitutional.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1955, p. 2027.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-19">
            <num>19</num>
            <heading>If it shall appear that an amount of tax or penalty or interest has
been paid in error hereunder to the Department by a purchaser, as distinguished
from the retailer, whether such amount be paid through a mistake of fact or
an error of law, such purchaser may file a claim for credit or refund with
the Department in accordance with Sections 6, 6a, 6b, 6c, and 6d of the
Retailers'
Occupation Tax Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If it shall appear that an amount of tax or penalty or
interest has been paid in error to the Department hereunder by a retailer
who is required or authorized to collect and remit the use tax, whether
such amount be paid through a mistake of fact or an error of law, such
retailer may file a claim for credit or refund with the Department in
accordance with Sections 6, 6a, 6b, 6c, and 6d of the Retailers' Occupation Tax
Act,
provided that no credit or refund shall be allowed for any amount paid by
any such retailer unless it shall appear that he bore the burden of such
amount and did not shift the burden thereof to anyone else (as in the case
of a duplicated tax payment which the retailer made to the Department and
did not collect from anyone else), or unless it shall appear that he or
she or his or her legal representative has unconditionally repaid such
amount to his vendee (1) who bore the burden thereof and has not shifted
such burden directly or indirectly in any manner whatsoever; (2) who, if he
has shifted such burden, has repaid unconditionally such amount to his or
her own vendee, and (3) who is not entitled to receive any reimbursement
therefor from any other source than from his vendor, nor to be relieved of
such burden in any other manner whatsoever. If it shall appear that an
amount of tax has been paid in error hereunder by the purchaser to a
retailer, who retained such tax as reimbursement for his or her tax
liability on the same sale under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, and who
remitted the amount involved to the Department under the Retailers'
Occupation Tax Act, whether such amount be paid through a mistake of fact
or an error of law, the procedure for recovering such tax shall be that
prescribed in Sections 6, 6a, 6b and 6c of the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act. Any credit or refund that is allowed under this Section shall bear interest
at the rate and in the manner specified in the Uniform Penalty and Interest
Act. Any claim filed hereunder shall be filed upon a form prescribed and
furnished by the Department. The claim shall be signed by the claimant (or
by the claimant's legal representative if the claimant shall have died or
become a person under legal disability), or by a duly authorized agent of
the claimant or his or her legal representative. A claim for credit or refund shall be considered to have been filed with
the Department on the date upon which it is received by the Department.
Upon receipt of any claim for credit or refund filed under this Act, any
officer or employee of the Department, authorized in writing by the
Director of Revenue to acknowledge receipt of such claims on behalf of the
Department, shall execute on behalf of the Department, and shall deliver or
mail to the claimant or his duly authorized agent, a written receipt,
acknowledging that the claim has been filed with the Department, describing
the claim in sufficient detail to identify it and stating the date upon
which the claim was received by the Department. Such written receipt shall
be prima facie evidence that the Department received the claim described in
such receipt and shall be prima facie evidence of the date when such claim
was received by the Department. In the absence of such a written receipt,
the records of the Department as to when the claim was received by the
Department, or as to whether or not the claim was received at all by the
Department, shall be deemed to be prima facie correct upon these questions
in the event of any dispute between the claimant (or his or her legal
representative) and the Department concerning these questions. In case the Department determines that the claimant is entitled to a
refund, such refund shall be made only from the Aviation Fuel Sales Tax Refund Fund or from such appropriation as may be
available for that purpose, as appropriate. If it appears unlikely that the amount available
 would permit everyone having a claim allowed during the period
covered by such appropriation or from the Aviation Fuel Sales Tax Refund Fund, as appropriate, to elect to receive a cash refund, the
Department, by rule or regulation, shall provide for the payment of refunds in
hardship cases and shall define what types of cases qualify as hardship cases. If a retailer who has failed to pay use tax on gross receipts from
retail sales is required by the Department to pay such tax, such retailer,
without filing any formal claim with the Department, shall be allowed to
take credit against such use tax liability to the extent, if any, to which
such retailer has paid an amount equivalent to retailers' occupation tax or
has paid use tax in error to his or her vendor or vendors of the same tangible
personal property which such retailer bought for resale and did not first
use before selling it, and no penalty or interest shall be charged to such
retailer on the amount of such credit. However, when such credit is allowed
to the retailer by the Department, the vendor is precluded from refunding
any of that tax to the retailer and filing a claim for credit or refund
with respect thereto with the Department. The provisions of this amendatory
Act shall be applied retroactively, regardless of the date of the transaction.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 101-10, eff. 6-5-19.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-20">
            <num>20</num>
            <heading>As soon as practicable after a claim for credit or refund is filed, the
Department shall examine the same and determine the amount of credit or
refund to which the claimant or the claimant's legal representative, in the
event that the claimant shall have died or become a person under legal
disability, is entitled
and shall, by its Notice of Tentative Determination of Claim, notify the
claimant or his or her legal representative of such determination, which
determination shall be prima facie correct</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Proof of such determination by
the Department may be made at any hearing before the Department or in any
legal proceeding by a reproduced copy of the Department's record relating
thereto, in the name of the Department under the certificate of the
Director of Revenue. Such reproduced copy shall, without further proof, be
admitted into evidence before the Department or in any legal proceeding and
shall be prima facie proof of the correctness of the Department's
determination, as shown therein. If such claimant, or the legal
representative of a deceased claimant or a claimant
who is a person under legal disability shall, within 60 days
after the Department's Notice of Tentative Determination of Claim, file a
protest thereto and request a hearing thereon, the Department shall give
notice to such claimant, or the legal representative of a deceased claimant,
or a claimant who is a person under legal disability
of the time and place fixed for such hearing, and
shall hold a hearing in conformity with the provisions of this Act.  On and after July 1, 2013, protests concerning matters that are subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal shall be filed with the Tax Tribunal in accordance with the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012, and hearings concerning those matters shall be held before the Tribunal in accordance with that Act.  With respect to protests filed with the Department prior to July 1, 2013 that would otherwise be subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal, the taxpayer may elect to be subject to the provisions of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012 at any time on or after July 1, 2013, but not later than 30 days after the date on which the protest was filed.  If made, the election shall be irrevocable.  The Department shall issue its Final Determination of the amount, if any,
found to be due as a result of a hearing before the Department or the Tribunal, to such claimant, or the legal
representative of a deceased claimant or a claimant
who is a person under legal disability. If a protest to the Department's Notice of Tentative Determination of
Claim is not filed within 60 days and a request for a hearing
thereon is
not made as provided herein, the said Notice shall thereupon become and
operate as a Final Determination; and, if the Department's Notice of
Tentative Determination, upon becoming a Final Determination, indicates no
amount due to the claimant, or, upon issuance of a credit or refund for the
amount, if any, found by the Department to be due, the claim in all its
aspects shall be closed and no longer open to protest, hearing, judicial
review, or by any other proceeding or action whatever, either before the
Department or in any court of this State. Claims for credit or refund
hereunder must be filed with and initially determined by the Department,
the remedy herein provided being exclusive; and no court shall have
jurisdiction to determine the merits of any claim except upon review as
provided in this Act.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-21">
            <num>21</num>
            <heading>As to any claim for credit or refund filed with the Department on and
after January 1 but on or before June 30 of any given year, no amount of
tax or penalty or interest erroneously paid (either in total or partial
liquidation of a tax or penalty or interest under this Act) more than 3
years prior to such January 1 shall be credited or refunded, and as to any
such claim filed on and after July 1 but on or before December 31 of any
given year, no amount of tax or penalty or interest erroneously paid
(either in total or partial liquidation of a tax or penalty or interest
under this Act) more than 3 years prior to such July 1 shall be credited or
refunded</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act to the contrary, for any period included in a claim for credit or refund for which the statute of limitations for issuing a notice of tax liability under this Act will expire less than 6 months after the date a taxpayer files the claim for credit or refund, the statute of limitations is automatically extended for 6 months from the date it would have otherwise expired. No claim shall be allowed for any amount paid to the Department,
whether paid voluntarily or involuntarily, if paid in total or partial
liquidation of an assessment which had become final before the claim for
credit or refund to recover the amount so paid is filed with the
Department, or if paid in total or partial liquidation of a judgment or order of court.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 102-40, eff. 6-25-21.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-105-22">
            <num>22</num>
            <heading>If it is determined that the Department should issue a credit or refund under this Act, the Department may first apply the amount thereof against any amount of tax or penalty or interest due hereunder, or under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, the Service Occupation Tax Act, the Service Use Tax Act, or any local occupation or use tax administered by the Department, from the person entitled to such credit or refund</heading>
            <content>
              <p>For this purpose, if proceedings are pending to determine whether or not any tax or penalty or interest is due under this Act or under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, the Service Occupation Tax Act, the Service Use Tax Act, or any local occupation or use tax administered by the Department, from such person, the Department may withhold issuance of the credit or refund pending the final disposition of such proceedings and may apply such credit or refund against any amount found to be due to the Department as a result of such proceedings. The balance, if any, of the credit or refund shall be issued to the person entitled thereto. Any credit memorandum issued hereunder may be used by the authorized holder thereof to pay any tax or penalty or interest due or to become due under this Act, or under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, the Service Occupation Tax Act, the Service Use Tax Act, or any local occupation or use tax administered by the Department, from such holder. Subject to reasonable rules of the Department, a credit memorandum issued hereunder may be assigned by the holder thereof to any other person for use in paying tax or penalty or interest which may be due or become due under this Act, or under the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act, the Service Occupation Tax Act, the Service Use Tax Act, or any local occupation or use tax administered by the Department, from the assignee. In any case in which there has been an erroneous refund of tax payable under this Act, a notice of tax liability may be issued at any time within 3 years from the making of that refund, or within 5 years from the making of that refund if it appears that any part of the refund was induced by fraud or the misrepresentation of a material fact. The amount of any proposed assessment set forth in the notice shall be limited to the amount of the erroneous refund.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>