<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="305-25"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/305-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_305">
        <num>305</num>
        <heading>Public Aid</heading>
        <article eId="chp_305__art_25">
          <num>305 ILCS 25/</num>
          <heading>State Blind or Deaf School Transportation Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_305-25-27">
            <num>27</num>
            <heading>If the parent, guardian or other person is unable to furnish a
child sent to a State school for the education of the blind or the deaf
with transportation or the proper and necessary clothing, but is eligible
for or receiving public assistance, the necessary expenditures for
transportation to the nearest appropriate public residential educational
facility and for the return of the child at suitable intervals and for the
proper and necessary clothing shall be provided for in the public
assistance grant</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If the parent, guardian, or other person is unable to
furnish such transportation or proper and necessary clothing, and is not
eligible for or receiving public assistance, then the circuit court for the
county in which the child resides or may be found, on application of any
citizen of the county, shall make an order directing that the child be
taken to such school as the court, in consultation with the parent,
guardian or other person deems for the best interest of the child, and for
the furnishing of transportation for that purpose including a custodian,
preferably the parent or guardian, and also for the furnishing of suitable
clothing, if necessary, which expense shall be advanced by the sheriff and
allowed by the county board. Such order shall also include an allowance for
the return of the child at suitable intervals.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1967, p. 3704.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>