<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-705"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-705"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35-705"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-705/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-705/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-705/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-705/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Revenue</heading>
        <article eId="chp_35__art_705">
          <num>35 ILCS 705/</num>
          <heading>Tax Collection Suit Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-705-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>At the request of any officer or agency charged with the
responsibility of collecting any tax that is imposed by this State or that
is collectible by this State on behalf of a political subdivision thereof,
the Attorney General of this State may bring suit, in the name of this
State or in the name of the officer or agency on whose behalf the suit is
brought, in the appropriate court of any other state, to collect any tax
legally due to this State or to the political subdivision on whose behalf
this State is required or authorized to act as a tax collector</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Any
political subdivision of this State or the appropriate officer thereof,
acting in its behalf, may bring suit in the appropriate court of any other
state to collect any tax legally due to such political subdivision.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1967, p. 1770.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-705-2">
            <num>2</num>
            <heading>The courts of this State shall recognize and enforce
liabilities for taxes lawfully imposed by any other state of the United
States, or a political subdivision of any such state, which state
extends a like comity to this State, and the duly authorized officer or
agency of any such other state, or political subdivision thereof, may
sue for the collection of such taxes in the courts of this State</heading>
            <content>
              <p>A certificate by the Secretary of State of such other state that the
officer or agency suing for the collection of such a tax is duly
authorized to collect the same shall be conclusive proof of such
authority.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1967, p. 1770.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-705-3">
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>For the purposes of this Act, the words &quot;tax&quot; and &quot;taxes&quot; shall
include interest and penalties due under any taxing statute, and liability
for such interest or penalties, or both, due under a taxing statute of
another state, or political subdivision thereof, shall be recognized and
enforced by the courts of this State to the same extent that the laws of
such other state permit the enforcement in its courts of liability for such
interest or penalties, or both, due under the tax laws of this State or any
political subdivision thereof</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: Laws 1967, p. 1770.) This site is maintained for the Illinois General Assembly by the
                        Legislative Information System, 705 Stratton Building, Springfield, Illinois 627</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1967, p. 1770.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>