<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-250"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-250"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35-250"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-250/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-250/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-250/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-250/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Revenue</heading>
        <article eId="chp_35__art_250">
          <num>35 ILCS 250/</num>
          <heading>Longtime Owner-Occupant Property Tax Relief Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>Short title</heading>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be cited as the Longtime Owner-Occupant Property Tax Relief Act.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-451.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-5">
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>Public policy</heading>
            <content>
              <p>In recognition of the severe economic circumstances
of certain longtime owner-occupants of residences who are faced with rising
living costs and constantly increasing tax burdens in areas where real property
values have risen markedly as a consequence of the renovation of other
deteriorating residences or the construction of new residences, the General
Assembly considers it to be a matter of sound public policy for counties having
a population of 100,000 or more to adopt uniform special real property tax
relief provisions in order to allow longtime owner-occupants of residences to
remain in peaceful possession of their homes.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-451.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-10">
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>Definitions</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-10__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Longtime owner-occupant&quot; means a person who for at least 10
continuous years has owned and has occupied the same dwelling place as a
principal residence and domicile, or any person who for at least 5 years
has owned and occupied the same dwelling place as a principal residence and
domicile if that person received assistance in the acquisition of the
property as part of a government or nonprofit housing program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-10__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Principal residence&quot; means the dwelling place of a person,
including the principal house and lot, and such lots as are used in
connection with the principal house and lot that contribute to its enjoyment,
comfort and convenience.  For purposes of this Act, the term may also include a
building with a maximum of one commercial establishment and a maximum of 3
residential units of which one residential unit must be the principal residence
of the longtime owner-occupant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-451.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-15">
            <num>15</num>
            <heading>Deferral or exemption authority</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-15__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporate authorities of a county shall have the power to provide,
by ordinance or resolution, for uniform
special real property tax relief provisions granting longtime owner-occupants a
deferral or exemption, or combination thereof, in the payment of that portion
of an increase of real property taxes which is due to an increase in the market
value of the real property as a consequence of the refurbishing or renovating
of other residences or the construction of new residences in long-established
residential areas or areas of deteriorated, vacant or abandoned homes and
properties.  A deferral or exemption, or combination thereof, may be granted
until the longtime owner-occupant transfers title to the property. The ordinance or resolution must include a provision requiring that
eligibility notification of the special real property tax relief be delivered
to the record owner of the property taxed.  The eligibility notification shall
be mailed to the address of the record owner on file with the county.  If the
notification is mailed by the county to a mortgagee because it is the only
address of the record owner filed with the county, then the mortgagee shall,
within 30 days of receipt, forward a copy of the notice to each mortgagor of
the property.  There
shall be no liability for the failure of the mortgagee to forward the notice to
each mortgagor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-15__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporate authority of a county is authorized to enact ordinances or
resolutions that provide for
the designation of areas eligible for the special real property tax relief
provisions under this Act.  Before enacting an ordinance or
resolution that proposes designating such an area, the corporate
authorities shall conduct a public hearing on the proposed ordinance or
resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-15__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>School districts and municipalities within a county have authority to
determine their participation in the
program of special real property tax relief within their taxing jurisdictions.
The provisions of this subsection shall not apply to municipalities and
school districts included under subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-15__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this Section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-15__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any provision to the contrary, if the corporate
authority of a county with 3,000,000 or more inhabitants enacts an ordinance or
resolution in accordance with subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-15__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of Section 6 of Article VII of the Illinois Constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-648, eff. 7-24-98; 91-894, eff. 1-1-01.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-20">
            <num>20</num>
            <heading>Conditions of deferral or exemption</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any deferral or exemption of payment of an increase in real property
taxes granted under this Act shall be limited to real property that meets both
of the following conditions:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The property is owned and occupied by a longtime owner-occupant.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The property is the principal residence and domicile of the longtime owner-occupant. The corporate authorities of a county, by ordinance or resolution, may
impose additional criteria for qualifying for a deferral or exemption under
this
Act including, but not limited to,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>requiring the owner-occupant to have
owned and occupied the same dwelling place as principal residence and domicile
for a period of more than 10 years, (ii) establishing age criteria for
eligibility of an owner-occupant, and (iii) establishing income criteria for
eligibility of an owner-occupant. A deferral or exemption, or combination thereof, under an ordinance or resolution adopted pursuant to this Act, may not exceed $20,000 in equalized assessed value per tax year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No penalties or interest shall accrue on the portion of any deferral
granted under this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-250-20__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of Section 15, school districts
and municipalities within a county to which this
Act applies may determine whether financial need, age, or both, of the
longtime owner-occupant shall be used to determine eligibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 93-715, eff. 7-12-04; 94-1074, eff. 12-26-06.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-25">
            <num>25</num>
            <heading>Retroactive application</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The corporate authorities of a
county to which this Act applies may use any county record or other
information that predates the effective date of this Act by up to 5 years
for the purpose of determining whether an increase in the market value of a
longtime owner-occupant's principal residence is a consequence of the
refurbishing or renovating of other residences or the construction of new
residences in long-established residential areas or areas of deteriorated,
vacant, or abandoned homes and properties.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-451.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-30">
            <num>30</num>
            <heading>(Amendatory provisions; text omitted)</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 88-451; text omitted.) (35 ILCS 250/99)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-451; text omitted.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-250-99">
            <num>99</num>
            <heading>This Act takes effect upon becoming law</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 88-451.) This site is maintained for the Illinois General Assembly by the
                        Legislative Information System, 705 Stratton Building, Springfield, Illinois 62706. Con</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-451.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>