<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="ILCS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-120"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-120"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#illinois-general-assembly"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-il"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35-120"/>
          <FRBRname value="ILCS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-120/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-120/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-120/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-il/act/ilcs/35-120/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="illinois-general-assembly" href="https://www.ilga.gov" showAs="Illinois General Assembly"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <chapter eId="chp_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Revenue</heading>
        <article eId="chp_35__art_120">
          <num>35 ILCS 120/</num>
          <heading>Retailers' Occupation Tax Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1">
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>Definitions</heading>
            <content>
              <p>As used in this Act: &quot;Sale at retail&quot; means any transfer of the ownership of, the title to, the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use tangible personal property to a purchaser, for the purpose of use or consumption, and not for the purpose of resale in any form as tangible personal property to the extent not first subjected to a use for which it was purchased, for a valuable consideration: Provided that the property purchased is deemed to be purchased for the purpose of resale, despite first being used, to the extent to which it is resold as an ingredient of an intentionally produced product or byproduct of manufacturing. For this purpose, slag produced as an incident to manufacturing pig iron or steel and sold is considered to be an intentionally produced byproduct of manufacturing. Transactions whereby the possession of the property is transferred but the seller retains the title as security for payment of the selling price shall be deemed to be sales. &quot;Sale at retail&quot; shall be construed to include any transfer of the ownership of, the title to, the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use tangible personal property to a purchaser, for use or consumption by any other person to whom such purchaser may transfer the tangible personal property without a valuable consideration, and to include any transfer, whether made for or without a valuable consideration, for resale in any form as tangible personal property unless made in compliance with Section 2c of this Act. Sales of tangible personal property, which property, to the extent not first subjected to a use for which it was purchased, as an ingredient or constituent, goes into and forms a part of tangible personal property subsequently the subject of a &quot;Sale at retail&quot;, are not sales at retail as defined in this Act: Provided that the property purchased is deemed to be purchased for the purpose of resale, despite first being used, to the extent to which it is resold as an ingredient of an intentionally produced product or byproduct of manufacturing. &quot;Sale at retail&quot; shall be construed to include any Illinois florist's sales transaction in which the purchase order is received in Illinois by a florist and the sale is for use or consumption, but the Illinois florist has a florist in another state deliver the property to the purchaser or the purchaser's donee in such other state. Nonreusable tangible personal property that is used by persons engaged in the business of operating a restaurant, cafeteria, or drive-in is a sale for resale when it is transferred to customers in the ordinary course of business as part of the sale of food or beverages and is used to deliver, package, or consume food or beverages, regardless of where consumption of the food or beverages occurs. Examples of those items include, but are not limited to nonreusable, paper and plastic cups, plates, baskets, boxes, sleeves, buckets or other containers, utensils, straws, placemats, napkins, doggie bags, and wrapping or packaging materials that are transferred to customers as part of the sale of food or beverages in the ordinary course of business. The purchase, employment and transfer of such tangible personal property as newsprint and ink for the primary purpose of conveying news (with or without other information) is not a purchase, use or sale of tangible personal property. A person whose activities are organized and conducted primarily as a not-for-profit service enterprise, and who engages in selling tangible personal property at retail (whether to the public or merely to members and their guests) is engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail with respect to such transactions, excepting only a person organized and operated exclusively for charitable, religious or educational purposes either (1), to the extent of sales by such person to its members, students, patients or inmates of tangible personal property to be used primarily for the purposes of such person, or (2), to the extent of sales by such person of tangible personal property which is not sold or offered for sale by persons organized for profit. The selling of school books and school supplies by schools at retail to students is not &quot;primarily for the purposes of&quot; the school which does such selling. The provisions of this paragraph shall not apply to nor subject to taxation occasional dinners, socials or similar activities of a person organized and operated exclusively for charitable, religious or educational purposes, whether or not such activities are open to the public. A person who is the recipient of a grant or contract under Title VII of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (P.L. 92-258) and serves meals to participants in the federal Nutrition Program for the Elderly in return for contributions established in amount by the individual participant pursuant to a schedule of suggested fees as provided for in the federal Act is not engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail with respect to such transactions. &quot;Lease&quot; means a transfer of the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use, but not title to, tangible personal property for a fixed or indeterminate term for consideration, regardless of the name by which the transaction is called. &quot;Lease&quot; does not include a lease entered into merely as a security agreement that does not involve a transfer of possession or control from the lessor to the lessee. On and after January 1, 2025, the term &quot;sale&quot;, when used in this Act, includes a lease. &quot;Purchaser&quot; means anyone who, through a sale at retail, acquires the ownership of, the title to, the possession or control of, the right to possess or control, or a license to use tangible personal property for a valuable consideration. &quot;Reseller of motor fuel&quot; means any person engaged in the business of selling or delivering or transferring title of motor fuel to another person other than for use or consumption. No person shall act as a reseller of motor fuel within this State without first being registered as a reseller pursuant to Section 2c or a retailer pursuant to Section 2a. &quot;Selling price&quot; or the &quot;amount of sale&quot; means the consideration for a sale valued in money whether received in money or otherwise, including cash, credits, property, other than as hereinafter provided, and services, but, prior to January 1, 2020 and beginning again on January 1, 2022, not including the value of or credit given for traded-in tangible personal property where the item that is traded-in is of like kind and character as that which is being sold; beginning January 1, 2020 and until January 1, 2022, &quot;selling price&quot; includes the portion of the value of or credit given for traded-in motor vehicles of the First Division as defined in Section 1-146 of the Illinois Vehicle Code of like kind and character as that which is being sold that exceeds $10,000. &quot;Selling price&quot; shall be determined without any deduction on account of the cost of the property sold, the cost of materials used, labor or service cost or any other expense whatsoever, but does not include charges that are added to prices by sellers on account of the seller's tax liability under this Act, or on account of the seller's duty to collect, from the purchaser, the tax that is imposed by the Use Tax Act, or, except as otherwise provided with respect to any cigarette tax imposed by a home rule unit, on account of the seller's tax liability under any local occupation tax administered by the Department, or, except as otherwise provided with respect to any cigarette tax imposed by a home rule unit on account of the seller's duty to collect, from the purchasers, the tax that is imposed under any local use tax administered by the Department. Effective December 1, 1985, &quot;selling price&quot; shall include charges that are added to prices by sellers on account of the seller's tax liability under</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-592, eff. 1-1-25; 103-983, eff. 1-1-25; 104-417, eff. 8-15-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1a">
            <num>1a</num>
            <heading>&quot;Pollution control facilities&quot; means any system, method,
construction, device or appliance appurtenant thereto sold or used or
intended for the primary purpose of eliminating, preventing, or reducing
air and water pollution as the term &quot;air pollution&quot; or &quot;water pollution&quot; is
defined in the &quot;Environmental Protection Act&quot;, enacted by the 76th General
Assembly, or for the primary purpose of treating, pretreating, modifying or
disposing of any potential solid, liquid or gaseous pollutant which if
released without such treatment, pretreatment, modification or disposal
might be harmful, detrimental or offensive to human, plant or animal life,
or to property</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2003, the purchase, employment and transfer of such
tangible personal property
as pollution control facilities is not a purchase, use or sale of tangible
personal property.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 93-24, eff. 6-20-03.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1c">
            <num>1c</num>
            <heading>A person who is engaged in the business of leasing or
renting motor vehicles or, beginning July 1, 2003, aircraft or, beginning September 1, 2004, watercraft to others and
who, in connection with such
business sells any used motor vehicle,
aircraft, or watercraft to a purchaser for his
use and not
for the purpose of resale, is a retailer engaged in the business of
selling tangible personal property at retail under this Act to the
extent of the value of the motor vehicle,
						aircraft, or watercraft sold</heading>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of
this
Section &quot;motor vehicle&quot; has the meaning prescribed in Section 1-157 of
the Illinois Vehicle Code, as now or hereafter amended.
For the purpose of this Section &quot;aircraft&quot; has the meaning prescribed in
Section
3 of the
Illinois Aeronautics Act.
For the purpose of this Section, &quot;watercraft&quot; has the meaning prescribed in Section 5-5 of the Watercraft Use Tax Law. (Nothing
provided herein shall affect liability incurred under this Act because
of the sale at retail of such motor vehicles, aircraft, or watercraft to a lessor.)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 93-24, eff. 6-20-03; 93-840, eff. 7-30-04.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1d">
            <num>1d</num>
            <heading>Subject to the provisions of Section 1f, all tangible personal
property to be used or consumed within an enterprise zone established
pursuant to the &quot;Illinois Enterprise Zone Act&quot;, as amended, or subject to
the provisions of Section 5</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1d__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the generation of electricity for wholesale or retail sale; (ii) the generation or treatment of natural or artificial gas for wholesale or retail sale that is delivered to customers through pipes, pipelines, or mains; or (iii) the treatment of water for wholesale or retail sale that is delivered to customers through pipes, pipelines, or mains.  The provisions of this amendatory Act of the 98th General Assembly are declaratory of existing law as to the meaning and scope of this exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 98-583, eff. 1-1-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1e">
            <num>1e</num>
            <heading>Subject to the provisions of Section 1f, or subject to the
provisions of Section 5</heading>
            <content>
              <p>5 of the Illinois Enterprise Zone Act, all tangible
personal property to be used or consumed in the operation of pollution
control facilities, as defined in Section 1a of this Act, within an
enterprise zone established pursuant to the &quot;Illinois Enterprise Zone Act&quot;,
as amended, shall be exempt from the tax imposed by this Act.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 85-1182.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1f">
            <num>1f</num>
            <heading>Except for High Impact Businesses, the exemption stated in
Sections 1d and 1e of this Act shall only apply to business enterprises which: (1) either (i) make investments which cause the creation of a minimum of 200 full-time equivalent jobs in Illinois or (ii) make investments which cause the retention of a minimum of 2000 full-time jobs in Illinois or (iii) make investments of a minimum of $40,000,000 and retain at least 90% of the jobs in place on the date on which the exemption is granted and for the duration of the exemption; and (2) are located in an Enterprise Zone established pursuant to the Illinois Enterprise Zone Act; and (3) are certified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity as complying with the requirements specified in clauses (1) and (2)</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1f__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>complied with the requirements specified in clause</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1f__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>above as of March 1, 2010, (ii) receives certification from the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity, (iii) was a Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity certified business enterprise in 2009,  and (iv) retained a minimum of 500 full-time equivalent jobs in Illinois in 2009 and 2010, 675 full-time equivalent jobs in Illinois in 2011, 850 full-time equivalent jobs in Illinois in 2012, and 1,000 full-time equivalent jobs in Illinois in 2013; those jobs must have been created in the manufacturing sector as defined by the North American Industry Classification System. Any business enterprise seeking to avail itself of the exemptions stated
in Sections 1d or 1e, or both, shall make application to the Department of
Commerce and Economic Opportunity in such form and providing such information
as may be prescribed by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity.
However, no business enterprise shall be required, as a condition for
certification under clause</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1f__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this Section, to attest that its decision
to invest under clause</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1f__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this Section and to locate under clause</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1f__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this Section is predicated upon the availability of the exemptions
authorized by Sections 1d or 1e. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall determine whether
the business enterprise meets the criteria prescribed in this Section.  If
the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity determines that such
business enterprise meets the criteria, it shall issue a certificate of
eligibility for exemption to the business enterprise in such form as is
prescribed by the Department of Revenue.  The Department of Commerce and
Economic Opportunity shall act upon such certification requests within 60 days
after receipt of the application, and shall file with the Department of
Revenue a copy of each certificate of eligibility for exemption. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall have the power to
promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the provisions of this
Section including the power to define the amounts and types of eligible
investments not specified in this Section which business enterprises
must make in order to receive the exemptions stated in Sections 1d and 1e
of this Act; and to require that any business enterprise that is granted a
tax exemption repay the exempted tax if the business enterprise fails to
comply with the terms and conditions of the certification. Such certificate of eligibility for exemption shall be presented by the
business enterprise to its supplier when making the initial purchase of
tangible personal property for which an exemption is granted by Section 1d or
Section 1e, or both, together with a certification by the business enterprise
that such tangible personal property is exempt from taxation under Section
1d or Section 1e and by indicating the exempt status of each subsequent
purchase on the face of the purchase order. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall determine the
period during which such exemption from the taxes imposed under this Act is
in effect </p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-1032, eff. 8-22-18.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1g">
            <num>1g</num>
            <heading>Application for exemption identification number</heading>
            <content>
              <p>On or before
December 31, 1986, except as hereinafter provided, each entity otherwise
eligible under exemption (11) of Section 2-5 of this Act and on and after the
effective date of this amendatory Act of the 92nd General Assembly each entity
otherwise eligible under exemption (9) of Section 2-5 of this Act shall make
application to the Department for an
exemption identification number. In the case of a corporation, society,
association, foundation, or institution organized and operated
exclusively for charitable purposes and that has more than 50
subsidiary organizations in Illinois, the Department, in its sole
discretion, may issue one exemption identification number to be used by the
parent organization and each subsidiary organization. Each exemption identification number or renewal number
shall be valid for 5 years after the first day of the month following the
month of issuance. Not less than 3 months before the
expiration date, an application for renewal shall be filed. Each application for an exemption identification number or a renewal
number shall contain information and be
accompanied by documentation as shall be requested by the Department.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 92-35, eff. 7-1-01.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1h">
            <num>1h</num>
            <heading>Upon request made on or after July 1, 1987, the Department
shall furnish to any county or municipality a list containing the name of
each corporation, society, association, foundation or institution organized
and operated exclusively for charitable, religious or educational purposes,
and each not-for-profit corporation, society, association, foundation,
institution or organization which has no compensated officers or employees
and which is organized and operated primarily for the recreation of persons
55 years of age or older, which had a valid exemption identification number
on the first day of January or July, as the case may be, proceeding the date
on which such request is received and which is located within the corporate
limits of such municipality or the unincorporated territory of such county,
except that the list need not include subsidiary organizations using an
exemption identification number issued to its parent organization as
provided by Section 1g of this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 97-813, eff. 7-13-12.) (35 ILCS 120/1i) (from Ch. 120, par. 440i)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-813, eff. 7-13-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1i">
            <num>1i</num>
            <heading>High Impact Service Facility means a facility used primarily
for the sorting, handling and
redistribution of mail, freight, cargo, or other parcels received from agents
or
employees of the handler or shipper for processing at a common location and
redistribution to other employees or agents for delivery to an ultimate
destination on an item-by-item basis, and which:  (1) will make an
investment in a business enterprise project of $100,000,000 dollars or more;
(2)
will cause the creation of at least 750 to 1,000 jobs or more in an
enterprise zone
established pursuant to the Illinois Enterprise Zone Act; and (3) is
certified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity as
contractually obligated to meet the requirements specified in divisions (1)
and (2) of this paragraph within the time period as specified by the
certification</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Any business enterprise project applying for the exemption
stated
in this Section shall make application to the Department of Commerce and
Economic Opportunity in such form and providing such information as may be
prescribed by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall determine whether
the business enterprise project meets the criteria prescribed in this
Section.  If
the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity determines that such
business enterprise project meets the criteria, it shall issue a
certificate of
eligibility for exemption to the business enterprise in such form as is
prescribed by the Department of Revenue.  The Department of Commerce and
Economic Opportunity shall act upon such certification requests within 60 days
after receipt of the application, and shall file with the Department of
Revenue a copy of each certificate of eligibility for exemption. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall have the power to
promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the provisions of this
Section and to require that any business enterprise that is granted a tax
exemption repay the exempted tax if the business enterprise fails to comply
with the terms and conditions of the certification. The certificate of eligibility for exemption shall be presented by the
business enterprise to its supplier when making
the initial purchase of machinery and equipment for which an exemption is
granted by Section 1j of this Act, together with a certification by the
business enterprise that such machinery and equipment is exempt from
taxation under Section 1j of this Act and by indicating the exempt status
of each subsequent purchase on the face of the purchase order. The certification of eligibility for exemption shall be presented by the
business enterprise to its supplier when making the purchase of jet fuel and
petroleum products for which an exemption is granted by Section 1j.1 of this
Act, together with a certification by the business enterprise that such jet
fuel and petroleum product, are exempt from taxation under Section 1j.1 of this
Act, and by indicating the exempt status of each subsequent purchase on the
face of the purchase order. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall determine the
period during which such exemption from the taxes imposed under this Act
will remain in effect.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 94-793, eff. 5-19-06.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1j">
            <num>1j</num>
            <heading>Exemption - Machinery or Equipment used in the operation of
high impact service facilities</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1j__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>motor
driven heavy equipment not considered rolling stock which is used for the
purpose of transporting parcels, machinery, or equipment, or
trailers used for the shipment of parcels, and equipment used to maintain
and provide in-house services, within the confines of the
facility, and (ii) automated machinery and equipment used for the
purposes of transporting parcels within the facility, along with all
components, parts, pieces, and computer software or hardware contained in
the electronic control systems related thereto.
The Department of Revenue shall promulgate such rules and regulations as
necessary to further define machinery and equipment eligible for exemption
in a high impact service facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 85-1409.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1k">
            <num>1k</num>
            <heading>Aircraft maintenance facility means a facility operated by an
interstate carrier for hire that is used primarily for the maintenance,
rebuilding or repair of aircraft, aircraft parts and auxiliary equipment
owned or leased by that carrier and used by that carrier as rolling stock
moving in interstate commerce, and which: (1) will make an investment by
the interstate carrier for hire of $400,000,000 or more in an enterprise
zone; (2) will cause the creation of at least 5,000 full-time jobs in that
enterprise zone; (3) is located in a county with population not less than
150,000 and not more than 200,000 and that contains 3 enterprise zones as
of December 31, 1990; (4) enters into a legally binding agreement with the
Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity to comply with clauses (1) and
(2) of this paragraph within a time period specified in the rules and
regulations promulgated pursuant to this Section; and (5) is certified by
the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity to be in compliance with
clauses (1), (2), (3) and (4) of this Section</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Any aircraft maintenance
facility applying for the exemption stated in this Section shall make
application to the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity in such
form and providing such information as may be prescribed by the Department
of Commerce and Economic Opportunity. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall determine whether
the facility meets the criteria prescribed in this Section.  If the
Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity determines
that the facility meets the criteria, it shall issue a certificate of
eligibility for exemption in the form prescribed by the Department of
Revenue to the business enterprise operating the facility.  The Department
of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall act upon certification request
within 60 days after receipt of application, and shall file with the
Department of Revenue a copy of each certificate of eligibility for exemption. The Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity shall promulgate rules
and regulations to carry out the provisions of this Section, and to require
that any business enterprise that is granted a tax exemption pay the
exempted tax to the Department of Revenue if the business enterprise fails
to comply with the terms and conditions of the certification, and pay all
penalties and interest on that exempted tax as determined by the
Department of Revenue. The certificate of eligibility for exemption shall be presented by the
business enterprise to its supplier when making the initial purchase of
machinery and equipment for which an exemption is granted by Section 1m or
Section 1n of this Act, or both, together with a certification by the
business enterprise that the machinery and equipment is exempt from
taxation under Section 1m or 1n of this Act.  The exempt status, if any, of
each subsequent purchase shall be indicated on the face of the purchase order.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 94-793, eff. 5-19-06.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1m">
            <num>1m</num>
            <heading>Subject to the provisions of Section 1k of this Act,
machinery and equipment used in the operation of an aircraft maintenance
facility as defined in Section 1k, located within an enterprise zone shall
be exempt from the tax imposed by this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The machinery and equipment
exempted by this Section is limited to machinery and equipment used
primarily to maintain, rebuild or repair aircraft used as rolling stock
moving in interstate commerce for hire by the operator of the facility.
The Department of Revenue shall promulgate any rules and regulations
necessary to further define machinery and equipment eligible for exemption
in an aircraft maintenance facility.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 86-1490.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1n">
            <num>1n</num>
            <heading>Subject to the provisions of Section 1k, all tangible
personal property to be used or consumed, within an enterprise zone
established pursuant to the Illinois Enterprise Zone Act, by any aircraft
maintenance facility, directly in the process of maintaining, rebuilding or
repairing aircraft is exempt from the tax imposed by this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The
exemption includes repair and replacement parts for machinery and equipment
used primarily in the process of maintaining, rebuilding or repairing
aircraft, and also includes equipment, fuels, material and supplies for the
maintenance, repair or operation of such machinery or equipment.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 86-1490.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1o">
            <num>1o</num>
            <heading>Aircraft support center exemption</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this Act, &quot;aircraft support center&quot; means a
support center operated by a
carrier for hire that is used primarily for the maintenance,
rebuilding, or repair of aircraft, aircraft parts, and auxiliary equipment,
and which carrier:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will make an investment of $30,000,000 or more at a federal Air Force Base located in this State;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will cause the creation of at least 750 full-time jobs at a joint use military and civilian airport at that federal Air Force Base;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enters into a legally binding agreement with the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity to comply with paragraphs</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within a time period specified in the rules and regulations promulgated by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity  pursuant to this subsection; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is certified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity to be in compliance with paragraphs</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the provisions of this subsection, jet fuel and petroleum
products used or consumed
by any aircraft
support center directly in the process of maintaining, rebuilding, or
repairing aircraft is exempt from the tax imposed by this Act.  The
Department of Revenue shall promulgate any rules necessary to further define
the items eligible for exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1o__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Section is exempt from the provisions of Section 2-70.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 94-793, eff. 5-19-06.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1p">
            <num>1p</num>
            <heading>(Repealed)</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 94-546, eff. 1-1-06. Repealed by P.A. 94-781, eff. 5-19-06.) (35 ILCS 120/1q)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 94-546, eff. 1-1-06. Repealed by P.A. 94-781, eff. 5-19-06.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1q">
            <num>1q</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; Illiana Expressway public private partnership</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each retailer that makes a qualified sale of building materials to be incorporated into the Illiana Expressway as defined in the Public Private Agreements for the Illiana Expressway Act, by remodeling, rehabilitating, or new construction, may deduct receipts from those sales when calculating the tax imposed by this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this Section, &quot;qualified sale&quot; means a sale of building materials that will be incorporated into the Illiana Expressway for which a Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption has been issued by the Illinois Department of Transportation, which has authority over the project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser a copy of the Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption issued by the Illinois Department of Transportation, which has jurisdiction over the project into which the building materials will be incorporated is located. The Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption must contain all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>statement that the project identified in the Certificate meets all the requirements of the Illinois Department of Transportation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location or address of the project; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the signature of the Secretary of the Illinois Department of Transportation, which has authority over the Illiana Expressway or the Secretary's delegate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to meeting the requirements of subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this Act, the retailer must obtain a certificate from the purchaser that contains all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the building materials are being purchased for incorporation into the Illiana Expressway in accordance with the Public Private Agreements for the Illiana Expressway Act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location or address of the project into which the building materials will be incorporated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the building materials being purchased; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purchaser's signature and date of purchase.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1q__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Section is exempt from Section 2-70 of this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 96-913, eff. 6-9-10.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1r">
            <num>1r</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; public-private partnership transportation projects</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each retailer that makes a qualified sale of building materials to be incorporated into a &quot;project&quot; as defined in the Public-Private Partnerships for Transportation Act, by remodeling, rehabilitating, or new construction, may deduct receipts from those sales when calculating the tax imposed by this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this Section, &quot;qualified sale&quot; means a sale of building materials that will be incorporated into a project for which a Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption has been issued by the agency having authority over the project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser a copy of the Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption issued by the agency having jurisdiction over the project into which the building materials will be incorporated is located. The Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption must contain all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>statement that the project identified in the Certificate meets all the requirements of the agency having authority over the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location or address of the project; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the signature of the director of the agency with authority over the project or the director's delegate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to meeting the requirements of subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this Act, the retailer must obtain a certificate from the purchaser that contains all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the building materials are being purchased for incorporation into a project in accordance with the Public-Private Partnerships for Transportation Act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location or address of the project into which the building materials will be incorporated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the building materials being purchased; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purchaser's signature and date of purchase.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1r__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Section is exempt from Section 2-70 of this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-502, eff. 8-23-11.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-1s">
            <num>1s</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; South Suburban Airport public-private partnership</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each retailer that makes a qualified sale of building materials to be incorporated into the South Suburban Airport as defined in the Public-Private Agreements for the South Suburban Airport Act, by remodeling, rehabilitating, or new construction, may deduct receipts from those sales when  calculating the tax imposed by this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this Section, &quot;qualified sale&quot; means a sale  of building materials that will be incorporated into the  South Suburban Airport for which a Certificate of Eligibility for  Sales Tax Exemption has been issued by the Illinois Department  of Transportation, which has authority over the project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser a copy of the Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption issued by the Illinois Department of Transportation, which has jurisdiction over the project into which the building materials will be incorporated is located.  The Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption must contain all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>statement that the project identified in the Certificate meets all the requirements of the Illinois  Department of Transportation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location or address of the project; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the signature of the Secretary of the Illinois Department of Transportation, which has authority over the  South Suburban Airport or the Secretary's delegate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to meeting the requirements of subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this Act, the retailer must obtain a certificate from the purchaser that contains all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the building materials are being purchased for incorporation into the South Suburban Airport in  accordance with the Public-Private Agreements for the  South Suburban Airport Act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location or address of the project into which the building materials will be incorporated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the building materials being purchased; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purchaser's signature and date of purchase.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-1s__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Section is exempt from Section 2-70 of this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 98-109, eff. 7-25-13.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2">
            <num>2</num>
            <heading>Tax imposed</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tax is imposed upon persons engaged in the business of selling at retail, which, on and after January 1, 2025, includes leasing, tangible personal property, including computer software, and including photographs, negatives, and positives that are the product of photoprocessing, but not including products of photoprocessing produced for use in motion pictures for public commercial exhibition. Beginning January 1, 2001, prepaid telephone calling arrangements shall be considered tangible personal property subject to the tax imposed under this Act regardless of the form in which those arrangements may be embodied, transmitted, or fixed by any method now known or hereafter developed. The imposition of the tax under this Act on persons engaged in the business of leasing tangible personal property applies to leases in effect, entered into, or renewed on or after January 1, 2025. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor must remit, for each tax return period, only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. The inclusion of leases in the tax imposed under this Act by Public Act 103-592 does not, however, extend to motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and semitrailers, as defined in Section 1-187 of the Illinois Vehicle Code, that are required to be registered with an agency of this State. The taxation of these items shall continue in effect as prior to the effective date of the changes made to this Section by Public Act 103-592 (i.e., dealers owe retailers' occupation tax, lessors owe use tax, and lessees are not subject to retailers' occupation or use tax). Sales of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electricity delivered to customers by wire;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>natural or artificial gas that is delivered to customers through pipes, pipelines, or mains; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>water that is delivered to customers through pipes, pipelines, or mains are not subject to tax under this Act. The provisions of Public Act 98-583 are declaratory of existing law as to the meaning and scope of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning on January 1, 2021 and through December 31, 2025, a remote retailer is engaged in the occupation of selling at retail in Illinois for purposes of this Act, if:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cumulative gross receipts from sales of tangible personal property to purchasers in Illinois are $100,000 or more; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the retailer enters into 200 or more separate transactions for the sale of tangible personal property to purchasers in Illinois. Remote retailers that meet or exceed the threshold in either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>above shall be liable for all applicable State retailers' and locally imposed retailers' occupation taxes administered by the Department on all retail sales to Illinois purchasers. The remote retailer shall determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether it meets the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of this subsection for the preceding 12-month period. If the retailer meets the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a 12-month period, he or she is considered a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State and is required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act and all retailers' occupation tax imposed by local taxing jurisdictions in Illinois, provided such local taxes are administered by the Department, and to file all applicable returns for one year. At the end of that one-year period, the retailer shall determine whether the retailer met the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the preceding 12-month period. If the retailer met the threshold in either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the preceding 12-month period, it is considered a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State and is required to collect and remit all applicable State and local retailers' occupation taxes and file returns for the subsequent year. If, at the end of a one-year period, a retailer that was required to collect and remit the tax imposed under this Act determines that it did not meet the threshold in either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during the preceding 12-month period, then the retailer shall subsequently determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether the retailer met the threshold of either paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the preceding 12-month period. (b-1) Beginning on January 1, 2026, a remote retailer is engaged in the occupation of selling at retail in Illinois for purposes of this Act if the remote retailer's cumulative gross receipts from sales of tangible personal property to purchasers in Illinois are $100,000 or more. Remote retailers that meet or exceed the threshold in this subsection (b-1) shall be liable for all applicable State and locally imposed retailers' occupation taxes administered by the Department on all retail sales to Illinois purchasers. The remote retailer shall determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and December, whether the remote retailer meets the threshold of this subsection (b-1) for the preceding 12-month period. If the remote retailer meets the threshold for a 12-month period, the remote retailer is considered to be engaged in the occupation of selling at retail in Illinois and is required to remit the tax imposed under this Act and all retailers' occupation tax imposed by local taxing jurisdictions in Illinois, provided such local taxes are administered by the Department, and to file all applicable returns for one year. At the end of the one-year period, the remote retailer shall determine whether the remote retailer met the threshold for the preceding 12-month period. If the retailer met the threshold for the preceding 12-month period, the remote retailer is considered to be engaged in the occupation of selling at retail in Illinois and is required to remit all applicable State and local retailers' occupation taxes and file returns for the subsequent year. If, at the end of a one-year period, a remote retailer that was required to remit the tax imposed under this Act determines that the remote retailer did not meet the threshold during the preceding 12-month period, then the remote retailer shall subsequently determine on a quarterly basis, ending on the last day of March, June, September, and Decembe</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b-1) of this Section so long as the remote retailer has received certification from the marketplace facilitator that the marketplace facilitator is legally responsible for payment of tax on such sales. (b-10) A remote retailer that is required to collect taxes imposed under the Use Tax Act on retail sales made to Illinois purchasers or a retailer maintaining a place of business in this State that is required to collect taxes imposed under the Use Tax Act on retail sales made to Illinois purchasers shall be liable to the Department for such taxes, except when the remote retailer or retailer maintaining a place of business in this State is relieve</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-592, eff. 1-1-25; 103-983, eff. 1-1-25; 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2a">
            <num>2a</num>
            <heading>Registration of retailers</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2a__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of Section 2 who use a certified service provider to file their returns under this Act. Such expedited registration process shall allow the Department to register a taxpayer based upon the same registration information required by the Streamlined Sales Tax Governing Board for states participating in the Streamlined Sales Tax Project. The Department may deny a certificate of registration to any applicant if a person who is named as the owner, a partner, a manager or member of a limited liability company, or a corporate officer of the applicant on the application for the certificate of registration is or has been named as the owner, a partner, a manager or member of a limited liability company, or a corporate officer on the application for the certificate of registration of another retailer that</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2a__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is in default for moneys due under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department or (ii) fails to file any return, on or before the due date prescribed for filing that return (including any extensions of time granted by the Department), that the retailer is required to file under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. For purposes of this paragraph only, in determining whether a person is in default for moneys due, the Department shall include only amounts established as a final liability within the 23 years prior to the date of the Department's notice of denial of a certificate of registration. The Department may require an applicant for a certificate of registration hereunder to, at the time of filing such application, furnish a bond from a surety company authorized to do business in the State of Illinois, or an irrevocable bank letter of credit or a bond signed by 2 personal sureties who have filed, with the Department, sworn statements disclosing net assets equal to at least 3 times the amount of the bond to be required of such applicant, or a bond secured by an assignment of a bank account or certificate of deposit, stocks or bonds, conditioned upon the applicant paying to the State of Illinois all moneys becoming due under this Act and under any other State tax law or municipal or county tax ordinance or resolution under which the certificate of registration that is issued to the applicant under this Act will permit the applicant to engage in business without registering separately under such other law, ordinance or resolution. In making a determination as to whether to require a bond or other security, the Department shall take into consideration whether the owner, any partner, any manager or member of a limited liability company, or a corporate officer of the applicant is or has been the owner, a partner, a manager or member of a limited liability company, or a corporate officer of another retailer that is </p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-319, eff. 1-1-24; 103-592, eff. 1-1-25; 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2b">
            <num>2b</num>
            <heading>The Department may, after notice and a hearing as
provided herein,
revoke the certificate of registration of any person who violates any of
the provisions of this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Before revocation of a certificate of
registration the Department shall, within 90 days after non-compliance
and at least 7 days prior to the date of the
hearing, give the person so accused notice in writing of the charge against
him or her, and on the date designated shall conduct a hearing upon
this matter.  The lapse of such 90 day period shall not preclude the
Department from conducting revocation proceedings at a later date if
necessary.  Any hearing held under this Section shall be conducted by the Director of
Revenue or by any officer or employee of the Department designated, in
writing, by the Director of Revenue. Upon the hearing of any such proceeding, the Director of Revenue, or any
officer or employee of the Department designated, in writing, by the
Director of Revenue, may administer oaths and the Department may procure by
its subpoena the attendance of witnesses and, by its subpoena duces tecum,
the production of relevant books and papers. Any circuit court, upon application
either of the accused or of the
Department, may, by order duly entered, require the attendance of witnesses
and the production of relevant books and papers, before the Department in
any hearing relating to the revocation of certificates of registration.
Upon refusal or neglect to obey the order of the court, the court may
compel obedience thereof by proceedings for contempt. The Department may, by application to any circuit court,
obtain an injunction
restraining any person who engages in the
business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State
without a certificate of registration (either because the certificate
of registration has been revoked or because of a failure to obtain a
certificate of registration in the first instance) from engaging in such
business until such person, as if he or she were a new applicant for
a certificate of registration, shall comply with all of the conditions,
restrictions and requirements of Section 2a of this Act and qualify for and
obtain a
certificate of registration. Upon refusal or neglect to obey the order of
the court, the court may compel obedience
thereof by proceedings for contempt. It shall not be a defense in a proceeding before the Department to
revoke a certificate of registration issued under the Act, or in any action
by the Department to collect any tax due under this Act, that the holder of
the certificate is a party to an installment payment agreement under
Section 2a of this Act if the liability which is the basis of the
revocation proceeding, or the tax that is sought to be collected: (1) was
incurred after the date of the agreement was approved by the Department;
or (2) was incurred prior to the date the agreement was approved by the
Department, but was not included in the agreement; or (3) was included in
the agreement, but the taxpayer is in default of the agreement.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 86-338; 86-383; 86-1028.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2c">
            <num>2c</num>
            <heading>Resales of tangible personal property</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If the purchaser is not registered with the Department as a taxpayer, but claims to be a reseller of the tangible personal property in such a way that such resales are not taxable under this Act or under some other tax law which the Department may administer, such purchaser (except in the case of an out-of-State purchaser who will always resell and deliver the property to his customers outside Illinois) shall apply to the Department for a resale number. Such applicant shall state facts which will show the Department why such applicant is not liable for tax under this Act or under some other tax law which the Department may administer on any of his resales and shall furnish such additional information as the Department may reasonably require. Upon approval of the application, the Department shall assign a resale number to the applicant and shall certify such number to him. The Department may cancel any such number which is obtained through misrepresentation, or which is used to make a purchase tax-free when the purchase in fact is not a purchase for resale, or which no longer applies because of the purchaser's having discontinued the making of tax exempt resales of the property. The Department may restrict the use of the number to one year at a time or to some other definite period if the Department finds it impracticable or otherwise inadvisable to issue such numbers for indefinite periods. Except as provided hereinabove in this Section, a sale shall be made tax-free on the ground of being a sale for resale if the purchaser has an active registration number or resale number from the Department and furnishes that number to the seller in connection with certifying to the seller that any sale to such purchaser is nontaxable because of being a sale for resale. On and after January 1, 2025, a sale to a lessor of tangible personal property who is subject to the tax on leases implemented by this amendatory Act of the 103rd General Assembly, for the purpose of leasing that property, shall be made tax-free on the ground of being a sale for resale, provided the other provisions of this paragraph are met. Failure to present an active registration number or resale number and a certification to the seller that a sale is for resale creates a presumption that a sale is not for resale. This presumption may be rebutted by other evidence that all of the seller's sales are sale for resale, or that a particular sale is a sale for resale.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-592, eff. 1-1-25 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2d">
            <num>2d</num>
            <heading>Tax prepayment by motor fuel retailer</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person engaged in the business of selling motor fuel at
retail, as defined in the Motor Fuel Tax Law, and who is not a
licensed distributor or supplier, as defined in the Motor Fuel Tax Law,
shall prepay to his or her distributor, supplier, or other reseller of
motor fuel a portion of the tax imposed by this Act if the distributor,
supplier, or other reseller of motor fuel is registered under Section 2a or
Section 2c of this Act.  The prepayment requirement provided for in this
Section does not apply to liquid propane gas.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning on July 1, 2000 and through December 31, 2000, the Retailers'
Occupation Tax paid to the distributor, supplier,
or other reseller shall be an amount equal to $0.01 per
gallon of the motor fuel, except gasohol as defined in Section 2-10 of
this Act which shall be an amount equal to $0.01 per gallon,
purchased from the distributor, supplier, or other reseller.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before July 1, 2000 and then beginning on January 1, 2001 and through June
30, 2003,
the Retailers' Occupation Tax paid
to the distributor, supplier, or other reseller shall be an amount equal to
$0.04 per gallon
of the motor fuel, except gasohol as defined in Section 2-10 of this Act which
shall be an
amount equal to $0.03 per gallon, purchased from the distributor, supplier, or
other
reseller.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning July 1, 2003 and through December 31, 2010, the Retailers' Occupation Tax paid
to
the
distributor, supplier, or other reseller shall be an amount equal to $0.06 per
gallon of the
motor fuel, except gasohol as defined in Section 2-10 of this Act which shall
be an
amount equal to $0.05 per gallon, purchased from the distributor, supplier, or
other
reseller.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning on January 1, 2011 and thereafter, the Retailers' Occupation Tax paid to the distributor, supplier, or other reseller shall be at the rate established by the Department under this subsection.  The rate shall be established by the Department on January 1 and July 1 of each year using the average selling price, as defined in Section 1 of this Act, per gallon of motor fuel sold in the State during the previous 6 months and multiplying that amount by 6.25% to determine the cents per gallon rate.  Beginning on January 1, 2024 and through December 31, 2028,  in the case of gasohol, as defined in Section 3-40 of the Use Tax Act, the rate shall be 90% of the rate established by the Department under this subsection for motor fuel.  Beginning on January 1, 2024 and through December 31, 2028, in the case of mid-range ethanol blends, as defined in Section 3-44.3 of the Use Tax Act, the rate shall be 80% of the rate established by the Department under this subsection for motor fuel. The Department shall provide persons subject to this Section notice of the rate established under this subsection at least 20 days prior to each January 1 and July 1.  Publication of the established rate on the Department's internet website shall constitute sufficient notice under this Section.  The Department may use data derived from independent surveys conducted or accumulated by third parties to determine the average selling price per gallon of motor fuel sold in the State.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person engaged in the business of selling motor fuel at retail shall
be entitled to a credit against tax due under this Act in an amount equal
to the tax paid to the distributor, supplier, or other reseller.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-2d__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every distributor, supplier, or other reseller registered as provided in
Section 2a or Section 2c of this Act shall remit the prepaid tax on all
motor fuel that is due from any person engaged in the business of selling
at retail motor fuel with the returns filed under Section 2f or Section 3
of this Act, but the vendors discount provided in Section 3 shall not apply
to the amount of prepaid tax that is remitted. Any distributor or supplier
who fails to properly collect and remit the tax shall be liable for the
tax.  For purposes of this Section, the prepaid tax is due on invoiced
gallons sold during a month by the 20th day of the following month.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-9, eff. 6-7-23.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2e">
            <num>2e</num>
            <heading>Every such distributor or supplier shall deliver a statement
of tax paid to each purchaser and the Department of Revenue not later
than the 20th day of the month following the month during which a
transaction occurred, showing: the number of gallons of motor fuel sold or
distributed during the preceding month to that purchaser; identifying the
purchaser to whom it was sold or distributed, including the purchaser's tax
registration number; and the amount collected from the purchaser</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 87-14.) (35 ILCS 120/2f) (from Ch. 120, par. 441f)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 87-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2f">
            <num>2f</num>
            <heading>Resellers of motor fuel shall file a return by
the 20th of the month following the month during which a transaction occurred
showing an itemized statement of the amount of motor fuel sold, distributed and used
by the reseller, identifying the purchaser to whom it was sold
including the purchaser's tax registration number, the amount of tax
collected from the purchaser, or delivery point if
the motor fuel was delivered to an unregistered purchaser outside this State,
name and address and the total quantity of motor fuel sold or transferred
to each purchaser in the preceding calendar month and such other information
as the Department may reasonably require</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 87-14.) (35 ILCS 120/2g) (from Ch. 120, par. 441g)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 87-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2g">
            <num>2g</num>
            <heading>All provisions of Sections 4 through 13</heading>
            <content>
              <p>5 of this Act shall
apply, as far as practicable, to returns filed pursuant to Section 2f.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 87-895.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2h">
            <num>2h</num>
            <heading>For purposes of this Act, a corporation, limited liability
company, society, association, foundation or institution organized and operated
exclusively for educational purposes shall include:  all tax-supported public
schools; private schools which offer systematic instruction in useful branches
of learning by methods common to public schools and which compare favorably in
their scope and intensity with the course of study presented in tax-supported
schools; licensed day care centers as defined in Section 2</heading>
            <content>
              <p>09 of the Child Care
Act of 1969 which are operated by a not for profit corporation, society,
association, foundation, institution or organization; vocational
or technical schools or institutes organized and operated exclusively to
provide a course of study of not less than 6 weeks duration and designed
to prepare individuals to follow a trade or to pursue a manual, technical,
mechanical, industrial, business or commercial occupation. However, a corporation, limited liability company, society, association,
foundation or institution organized  and operated for the purpose of offering
professional, trade or business seminars of short duration, self-improvement or
personality development courses, courses which are avocational or recreational
in nature, courses pursued entirely by open circuit television or radio,
correspondence courses, or courses which do not provide specialized training
within a specific vocational or technical field shall not be considered to be
organized and operated exclusively for educational purposes.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-480.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2i">
            <num>2i</num>
            <heading>Notwithstanding any other provision to the contrary, any person
who is required to file a bond pursuant to any provision of this Act and
who has continuously complied with all provisions of this Act for 24 or
more consecutive months, shall no longer be required to comply with the
bonding provisions of this Act so long as such person continues his compliance
with the provisions of this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 84-1408.) (35 ILCS 120/2j)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 84-1408.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-2j">
            <num>2j</num>
            <heading>Sorbent purchasing reports</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Illinois businesses that purchase sorbents for use in mercury control, as described in 35 Ill. Adm.  Code 225, shall file a monthly report with the Department stating the amount of sorbent purchased during the previous month, the purchase price of the sorbent, the amount of State occupation and use taxes paid on the purchase of the sorbent (whether to the selling retailer or directly to the Department of Revenue pursuant to a direct pay permit), and any other information the Department may reasonably require. In sales of sorbents between related parties, the purchase price of the sorbent must have been determined in an arms-length transaction. The report shall be filed with the Department on or before the 20th day of each month following a month in which sorbents were purchased, on a form provided by the Department. However, no report need be filed in a month when the taxpayer made no reportable purchases of sorbents in the previous month. The Department shall provide a monthly summary of these reports to the Illinois Environmental Protection Agency. Upon request, the Illinois Environmental Protection Agency shall provide the Department with a list of Illinois businesses that are subject to 35 Ill. Adm. Code 225.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-95, eff. 7-12-11.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-3">
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>Except as provided in this Section, on or before the twentieth day of each calendar month, every person engaged in the business of selling, which, on and after January 1, 2025, includes leasing, tangible personal property at retail in this State during the preceding calendar month shall file a return with the Department, stating: 1</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The name of the seller; 2. His residence address and the address of his principal place of business and the address of the principal place of business (if that is a different address) from which he engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State; 3. Total amount of receipts received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter, as the case may be, from sales of tangible personal property, and from services furnished, by him during such preceding calendar month or quarter; 4. Total amount received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter on charge and time sales of tangible personal property, and from services furnished, by him prior to the month or quarter for which the return is filed; 5. Deductions allowed by law; 6. Gross receipts which were received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter and upon the basis of which the tax is imposed, including gross receipts on food for human consumption that is to be consumed off the premises where it is sold (other than alcoholic beverages, food consisting of or infused with adult use cannabis, soft drinks, and food that has been prepared for immediate consumption) which were received during the preceding calendar month or quarter and upon which tax would have been due but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700; 7. The amount of credit provided in Section 2d of this Act; 8. The amount of tax due, including the amount of tax that would have been due on food for human consumption that is to be consumed off the premises where it is sold (other than alcoholic beverages, food consisting of or infused with adult use cannabis, soft drinks, and food that has been prepared for immediate consumption) but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700; 9. The signature of the taxpayer; and 10. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor must remit for each tax return period only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. On and after January 1, 2018, except for returns required to be filed prior to January 1, 2023 for motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, with respect to retailers whose annual gross receipts average $20,000 or more, all returns required to be filed pursuant to this Act shall be filed electronically. On and after January 1, 2023, with respect to retailers whose annual gross receipts average $20,000 or more, all returns required to be filed pursuant to this Act, including, but not limited to, returns for motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, shall be filed electronically. Retailers who demonstrate that they do not have access to the Internet or demonstrate hardship in filing electronically may petition the Department to waive the electronic filing requirement. If a taxpayer fails to sign a return within 30 days after the proper notice and demand for signature by the Department, the return shall be considered valid and any amount shown to be due on the return shall be deemed assessed. Each return shall be accompanied by the statement of prepaid tax issued pursuant to Section 2e for which credit is claimed. Prior to October 1, 2003 and on and after September 1, 2004, a retailer may accept a Manufacturer's Purchase Credit certification from a purchaser in satisfaction of Use Tax as provided in Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act if the purchaser provides the appropriate documentation as required by Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act. A Manufacturer's Purchase Credit certification, accepted by a retailer prior to October 1, 2003 and on and after September 1, 2004 as provided in Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act, may be used by that retailer to satisfy Retailers' Occupation Tax liability in the amount claimed in the certification, not to exceed 6.25% of the receipts subject to tax from a qualifying purchase. A Manufacturer's Purchase Credit reported on any original or amended return filed under this Act after October 20, 2003 for reporting periods prior to September 1, 2004 shall be disallowed. Manufacturer's Purchase Credit reported on annual returns due on or after January 1, 2005 will be disallowed for periods prior to September 1, 2004. No Manufacturer's Purchase Credit may be used after September 30, 2003 through August 31, 2004 to satisfy any tax liability imposed under this Act, including any audit liability. Beginning on July 1, 2023 and through December 31, 2032, a retailer may accept a Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit certification from an air common carrier-purchaser in satisfaction of Use Tax on aviation fuel as provided in Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act if the purchaser provides the appropriate documentation as required by Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act. A Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit certification accepted by a retailer in accordance with this paragraph may be used by that retailer to satisfy Retailers' Occupation Tax liability (but not in satisfaction of penalty or interest) in the amount claimed in the certification, not to exceed 6.25% of the receipts subject to tax from a sale of aviation fuel. In addition, for a sale of aviation fuel to qualify to earn the Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit, retailers must retain in their books and records a certification from the producer of the aviation fuel that the aviation fuel sold by the retailer and for which a sustainable aviation fuel purchase credit was earned meets the definition of sustainable aviation fuel under Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act. The documentation must include detail sufficient for the Department to determine the number of gallons of sustainable aviation fuel sold. The Department may require returns to be filed on a quarterly basis. If so required, a return for each calendar quarter shall be filed on or before the twentieth day of the calendar month following the end of such calendar quarter. The taxpayer shall also file a return with the Department for each of the first 2 months of each calendar quarter, on or before the twentieth day of the following calendar month, stating: 1. The name of the seller; 2. The address of the principal place of business from which he engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State; 3. The total amount of taxable receipts received by him during the preceding calendar month from sales of tangible personal property by him during such preceding calendar month, including receipts from charge and time sales, but less all deductions allowed by law; 4. The amount of credit provided in Section 2d of this Act; 5. The amount of tax due; and 6. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. Every person engaged in the business of selling aviation fuel at retail in this State during the preceding calendar month shall, instead of reporting and paying tax as otherwise required by this Section, report and pay such tax on a separate aviation fuel tax return. The requirements related to the return shall be as otherwise provided in this Section. Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Act to the contrary, retailers selling aviation fuel shall file all aviation fuel tax returns and shall make all aviation fuel tax payments by electronic means in the manner and form required by the Department. For purposes of this Section, &quot;aviation fuel&quot; means jet fuel and aviation gasoline. Beginning on October 1, 2003, any person who is not a licensed distributor, importing distributor, or manufacturer, as defined in the Liquor Control Act of 1934, but is engaged in the business of selling, at retail, alcoholic liquor shall file a statement with the Department of Revenue, in a format and at a time prescribed by the Department, showing the total amount paid f</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-9, eff. 6-7-23; 103-154, eff. 6-30-23; 103-363, eff. 7-28-23; 103-592, Article 75, Section 75-20, eff. 1-1-25; 103-592, Article 110, Section 110-20, eff. 6-7-24; 103-605, eff. 7-1-24; 103-1055, eff. 12-20-24; 104-6, Article 5, Section 5-25, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-3">
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>Except as provided in this Section, on or before the twentieth day of each calendar month, every person engaged in the business of selling, which, on and after January 1, 2025, includes leasing, tangible personal property at retail in this State during the preceding calendar month shall file a return with the Department, stating: 1</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The name of the seller; 2. His residence address and the address of his principal place of business and the address of the principal place of business (if that is a different address) from which he engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State; 3. Total amount of receipts received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter, as the case may be, from sales of tangible personal property, and from services furnished, by him during such preceding calendar month or quarter; 4. Total amount received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter on charge and time sales of tangible personal property, and from services furnished, by him prior to the month or quarter for which the return is filed; 5. Deductions allowed by law; 6. Gross receipts which were received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter and upon the basis of which the tax is imposed, including gross receipts on food for human consumption that is to be consumed off the premises where it is sold (other than alcoholic beverages, food consisting of or infused with adult use cannabis, soft drinks, and food that has been prepared for immediate consumption) which were received during the preceding calendar month or quarter and upon which tax would have been due but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700; 7. The amount of credit provided in Section 2d of this Act; 8. The amount of tax due, including the amount of tax that would have been due on food for human consumption that is to be consumed off the premises where it is sold (other than alcoholic beverages, food consisting of or infused with adult use cannabis, soft drinks, and food that has been prepared for immediate consumption) but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700; 9. The signature of the taxpayer; and 10. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor must remit for each tax return period only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. On and after January 1, 2018, except for returns required to be filed prior to January 1, 2023 for motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, with respect to retailers whose annual gross receipts average $20,000 or more, all returns required to be filed pursuant to this Act shall be filed electronically. On and after January 1, 2023, with respect to retailers whose annual gross receipts average $20,000 or more, all returns required to be filed pursuant to this Act, including, but not limited to, returns for motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, shall be filed electronically. Retailers who demonstrate that they do not have access to the Internet or demonstrate hardship in filing electronically may petition the Department to waive the electronic filing requirement. If a taxpayer fails to sign a return within 30 days after the proper notice and demand for signature by the Department, the return shall be considered valid and any amount shown to be due on the return shall be deemed assessed. Each return shall be accompanied by the statement of prepaid tax issued pursuant to Section 2e for which credit is claimed. Prior to October 1, 2003 and on and after September 1, 2004, a retailer may accept a Manufacturer's Purchase Credit certification from a purchaser in satisfaction of Use Tax as provided in Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act if the purchaser provides the appropriate documentation as required by Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act. A Manufacturer's Purchase Credit certification, accepted by a retailer prior to October 1, 2003 and on and after September 1, 2004 as provided in Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act, may be used by that retailer to satisfy Retailers' Occupation Tax liability in the amount claimed in the certification, not to exceed 6.25% of the receipts subject to tax from a qualifying purchase. A Manufacturer's Purchase Credit reported on any original or amended return filed under this Act after October 20, 2003 for reporting periods prior to September 1, 2004 shall be disallowed. Manufacturer's Purchase Credit reported on annual returns due on or after January 1, 2005 will be disallowed for periods prior to September 1, 2004. No Manufacturer's Purchase Credit may be used after September 30, 2003 through August 31, 2004 to satisfy any tax liability imposed under this Act, including any audit liability. Beginning on July 1, 2023 and through December 31, 2032, a retailer may accept a Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit certification from an air common carrier-purchaser in satisfaction of Use Tax on aviation fuel as provided in Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act if the purchaser provides the appropriate documentation as required by Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act. A Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit certification accepted by a retailer in accordance with this paragraph may be used by that retailer to satisfy Retailers' Occupation Tax liability (but not in satisfaction of penalty or interest) in the amount claimed in the certification, not to exceed 6.25% of the receipts subject to tax from a sale of aviation fuel. In addition, for a sale of aviation fuel to qualify to earn the Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit, retailers must retain in their books and records a certification from the producer of the aviation fuel that the aviation fuel sold by the retailer and for which a sustainable aviation fuel purchase credit was earned meets the definition of sustainable aviation fuel under Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act. The documentation must include detail sufficient for the Department to determine the number of gallons of sustainable aviation fuel sold. The Department may require returns to be filed on a quarterly basis. If so required, a return for each calendar quarter shall be filed on or before the twentieth day of the calendar month following the end of such calendar quarter. The taxpayer shall also file a return with the Department for each of the first 2 months of each calendar quarter, on or before the twentieth day of the following calendar month, stating: 1. The name of the seller; 2. The address of the principal place of business from which he engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State; 3. The total amount of taxable receipts received by him during the preceding calendar month from sales of tangible personal property by him during such preceding calendar month, including receipts from charge and time sales, but less all deductions allowed by law; 4. The amount of credit provided in Section 2d of this Act; 5. The amount of tax due; and 6. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. Every person engaged in the business of selling aviation fuel at retail in this State during the preceding calendar month shall, instead of reporting and paying tax as otherwise required by this Section, report and pay such tax on a separate aviation fuel tax return. The requirements related to the return shall be as otherwise provided in this Section. Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Act to the contrary, retailers selling aviation fuel shall file all aviation fuel tax returns and shall make all aviation fuel tax payments by electronic means in the manner and form required by the Department. For purposes of this Section, &quot;aviation fuel&quot; means jet fuel and aviation gasoline. Beginning on October 1, 2003, any person who is not a licensed distributor, importing distributor, or manufacturer, as defined in the Liquor Control Act of 1934, but is engaged in the business of selling, at retail, alcoholic liquor shall file a statement with the Department of Revenue, in a format and at a time prescribed by the Department, showing the total amount paid f</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-9, eff. 6-7-23; 103-154, eff. 6-30-23; 103-363, eff. 7-28-23; 103-592, Article 75, Section 75-20, eff. 1-1-25; 103-592, Article 110, Section 110-20, eff. 6-7-24; 103-605, eff. 7-1-24; 103-1055, eff. 12-20-24; 104-6, Article 25, Section 25-20, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-3">
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>Except as provided in this Section, on or before the twentieth day of each calendar month, every person engaged in the business of selling, which, on and after January 1, 2025, includes leasing, tangible personal property at retail in this State during the preceding calendar month shall file a return with the Department, stating: 1</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The name of the seller; 2. His residence address and the address of his principal place of business and the address of the principal place of business (if that is a different address) from which he engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State; 3. Total amount of receipts received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter, as the case may be, from sales of tangible personal property, and from services furnished, by him during such preceding calendar month or quarter; 4. Total amount received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter on charge and time sales of tangible personal property, and from services furnished, by him prior to the month or quarter for which the return is filed; 5. Deductions allowed by law; 6. Gross receipts which were received by him during the preceding calendar month or quarter and upon the basis of which the tax is imposed, including gross receipts on food for human consumption that is to be consumed off the premises where it is sold (other than alcoholic beverages, food consisting of or infused with adult use cannabis, soft drinks, and food that has been prepared for immediate consumption) which were received during the preceding calendar month or quarter and upon which tax would have been due but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700; 7. The amount of credit provided in Section 2d of this Act; 8. The amount of tax due, including the amount of tax that would have been due on food for human consumption that is to be consumed off the premises where it is sold (other than alcoholic beverages, food consisting of or infused with adult use cannabis, soft drinks, and food that has been prepared for immediate consumption) but for the 0% rate imposed under Public Act 102-700; 9. The signature of the taxpayer; and 10. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. In the case of leases, except as otherwise provided in this Act, the lessor must remit for each tax return period only the tax applicable to that part of the selling price actually received during such tax return period. On and after January 1, 2018, except for returns required to be filed prior to January 1, 2023 for motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, with respect to retailers whose annual gross receipts average $20,000 or more, all returns required to be filed pursuant to this Act shall be filed electronically. On and after January 1, 2023, with respect to retailers whose annual gross receipts average $20,000 or more, all returns required to be filed pursuant to this Act, including, but not limited to, returns for motor vehicles, watercraft, aircraft, and trailers that are required to be registered with an agency of this State, shall be filed electronically. Retailers who demonstrate that they do not have access to the Internet or demonstrate hardship in filing electronically may petition the Department to waive the electronic filing requirement. If a taxpayer fails to sign a return within 30 days after the proper notice and demand for signature by the Department, the return shall be considered valid and any amount shown to be due on the return shall be deemed assessed. Each return shall be accompanied by the statement of prepaid tax issued pursuant to Section 2e for which credit is claimed. Prior to October 1, 2003 and on and after September 1, 2004, a retailer may accept a Manufacturer's Purchase Credit certification from a purchaser in satisfaction of Use Tax as provided in Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act if the purchaser provides the appropriate documentation as required by Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act. A Manufacturer's Purchase Credit certification, accepted by a retailer prior to October 1, 2003 and on and after September 1, 2004 as provided in Section 3-85 of the Use Tax Act, may be used by that retailer to satisfy Retailers' Occupation Tax liability in the amount claimed in the certification, not to exceed 6.25% of the receipts subject to tax from a qualifying purchase. A Manufacturer's Purchase Credit reported on any original or amended return filed under this Act after October 20, 2003 for reporting periods prior to September 1, 2004 shall be disallowed. Manufacturer's Purchase Credit reported on annual returns due on or after January 1, 2005 will be disallowed for periods prior to September 1, 2004. No Manufacturer's Purchase Credit may be used after September 30, 2003 through August 31, 2004 to satisfy any tax liability imposed under this Act, including any audit liability. Beginning on July 1, 2023 and through December 31, 2032, a retailer may accept a Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit certification from an air common carrier-purchaser in satisfaction of Use Tax on aviation fuel as provided in Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act if the purchaser provides the appropriate documentation as required by Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act. A Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit certification accepted by a retailer in accordance with this paragraph may be used by that retailer to satisfy Retailers' Occupation Tax liability (but not in satisfaction of penalty or interest) in the amount claimed in the certification, not to exceed 6.25% of the receipts subject to tax from a sale of aviation fuel. In addition, for a sale of aviation fuel to qualify to earn the Sustainable Aviation Fuel Purchase Credit, retailers must retain in their books and records a certification from the producer of the aviation fuel that the aviation fuel sold by the retailer and for which a sustainable aviation fuel purchase credit was earned meets the definition of sustainable aviation fuel under Section 3-87 of the Use Tax Act. The documentation must include detail sufficient for the Department to determine the number of gallons of sustainable aviation fuel sold. The Department may require returns to be filed on a quarterly basis. If so required, a return for each calendar quarter shall be filed on or before the twentieth day of the calendar month following the end of such calendar quarter. The taxpayer shall also file a return with the Department for each of the first 2 months of each calendar quarter, on or before the twentieth day of the following calendar month, stating: 1. The name of the seller; 2. The address of the principal place of business from which he engages in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State; 3. The total amount of taxable receipts received by him during the preceding calendar month from sales of tangible personal property by him during such preceding calendar month, including receipts from charge and time sales, but less all deductions allowed by law; 4. The amount of credit provided in Section 2d of this Act; 5. The amount of tax due; and 6. Such other reasonable information as the Department may require. Every person engaged in the business of selling aviation fuel at retail in this State during the preceding calendar month shall, instead of reporting and paying tax as otherwise required by this Section, report and pay such tax on a separate aviation fuel tax return. The requirements related to the return shall be as otherwise provided in this Section. Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Act to the contrary, retailers selling aviation fuel shall file all aviation fuel tax returns and shall make all aviation fuel tax payments by electronic means in the manner and form required by the Department. For purposes of this Section, &quot;aviation fuel&quot; means jet fuel and aviation gasoline. Beginning on October 1, 2003, any person who is not a licensed distributor, importing distributor, or manufacturer, as defined in the Liquor Control Act of 1934, but is engaged in the business of selling, at retail, alcoholic liquor shall file a statement with the Department of Revenue, in a format and at a time prescribed by the Department, showing the total amount paid f</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-9, eff. 6-7-23; 103-154, eff. 6-30-23; 103-363, eff. 7-28-23; 103-592, Article 75, Section 75-20, eff. 1-1-25; 103-592, Article 110, Section 110-20, eff. 6-7-24; 103-605, eff. 7-1-24; 103-1055, eff. 12-20-24; 104-6, Article 35, Section 35-35, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-4">
            <num>4</num>
            <heading>As soon as practicable after any return is filed, the Department shall examine such return and shall, if necessary, correct such return according to its best judgment and information</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If the correction of a return results in an amount of tax that is understated on the taxpayer's return due to a mathematical error, the Department shall notify the taxpayer that the amount of tax in excess of that shown on the return is due and has been assessed. The term &quot;mathematical error&quot; means arithmetic errors or incorrect computations on the return or supporting schedules. No such notice of additional tax due shall be issued on and after each July 1 and January 1 covering gross receipts received during any month or period of time more than 3 years prior to such July 1 and January 1, respectively. Such notice of additional tax due shall not be considered a notice of tax liability nor shall the taxpayer have any right of protest. In the event that the return is corrected for any reason other than a mathematical error, any return so corrected by the Department shall be prima facie correct and shall be prima facie evidence of the correctness of the amount of tax due, as shown therein. In correcting transaction by transaction reporting returns provided for in Section 3 of this Act, it shall be permissible for the Department to show a single corrected return figure for any given period of a calendar month instead of having to correct each transaction by transaction return form individually and having to show a corrected return figure for each of such transaction by transaction return forms. In making a correction of transaction by transaction, monthly or quarterly returns covering a period of 6 months or more, it shall be permissible for the Department to show a single corrected return figure for any given 6-month period. For sales sourced under this Act to the Illinois location to which the tangible personal property is shipped or delivered or at which possession is taken by the purchaser, if the taxpayer fails to provide the information, schedules, or supporting documents necessary to determine such location, the Department shall, in lieu of imposing a penalty for an unprocessable return under the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act, assess tax on the gross receipts of such sales at the rate of 15%. Instead of requiring the person filing such return to file an amended return, the Department may simply notify him of the correction or corrections it has made. Proof of such correction by the Department may be made at any hearing before the Department or the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal or in any legal proceeding by a reproduced copy or computer print-out of the Department's record relating thereto in the name of the Department under the certificate of the Director of Revenue. If reproduced copies of the Department's records are offered as proof of such correction, the Director must certify that those copies are true and exact copies of records on file with the Department. If computer print-outs of the Department's records are offered as proof of such correction, the Director must certify that those computer print-outs are true and exact representations of records properly entered into standard electronic computing equipment, in the regular course of the Department's business, at or reasonably near the time of the occurrence of the facts recorded, from trustworthy and reliable information. Such certified reproduced copy or certified computer print-out shall without further proof, be admitted into evidence before the Department or in any legal proceeding and shall be prima facie proof of the correctness of the amount of tax due, as shown therein. If the tax computed upon the basis of the gross receipts as fixed by the Department is greater than the amount of tax due under the return or returns as filed, the Department shall (or if the tax or any part thereof that is admitted to be due by a return or returns, whether filed on time or not, is not paid, the Department may) issue the taxpayer a notice of tax liability for the amount of tax claimed by the Department to be due, together with a penalty in an amount determined in accordance with Section 3-3 of the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act. Provided, that if the incorrectness of any return or returns as determined by the Department is due to negligence or fraud, said penalty shall be in an amount determined in accordance with Section 3-5 or Section 3-6 of the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act, as the case may be. If the notice of tax liability is not based on a correction of the taxpayer's return or returns, but is based on the taxpayer's failure to pay all or a part of the tax admitted by his return or returns (whether filed on time or not) to be due, such notice of tax liability shall be prima facie correct and shall be prima facie evidence of the correctness of the amount of tax due, as shown therein. Proof of such notice of tax liability by the Department may be made at any hearing before the Department or the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal or in any legal proceeding by a reproduced copy of the Department's record relating thereto in the name of the Department under the certificate of the Director of Revenue. Such reproduced copy shall without further proof, be admitted into evidence before the Department or in any legal proceeding and shall be prima facie proof of the correctness of the amount of tax due, as shown therein. If the person filing any return dies or becomes a person under legal disability at any time before the Department issues its notice of tax liability, such notice shall be issued to the administrator, executor or other legal representative, as such, of such person. Except in case of a fraudulent return, or in the case of an amended return (where a notice of tax liability may be issued on or after each January 1 and July 1 for an amended return filed not more than 3 years prior to such January 1 or July 1, respectively), no notice of tax liability shall be issued on and after each January 1 and July 1 covering gross receipts received during any month or period of time more than 3 years prior to such January 1 and July 1, respectively. If, before the expiration of the time prescribed in this Section for the issuance of a notice of tax liability, both the Department and the taxpayer have consented in writing to its issuance after such time, such notice may be issued at any time prior to the expiration of the period agreed upon. The period so agreed upon may be extended by subsequent agreements in writing made before the expiration of the period previously agreed upon. The foregoing limitations upon the issuance of a notice of tax liability shall not apply to the issuance of a notice of tax liability with respect to any period of time prior thereto in cases where the Department has, within the period of limitation then provided, notified the person making the return of a notice of tax liability even though such return, with which the tax that was shown by such return to be due was paid when the return was filed, had not been corrected by the Department in the manner required herein prior to the issuance of such notice, but in no case shall the amount of any such notice of tax liability for any period otherwise barred by this Act exceed for such period the amount shown in the notice of tax liability theretofore issued. If, when a tax or penalty under this Act becomes due and payable, the person alleged to be liable therefor is out of the State, the notice of tax liability may be issued within the times herein limited after his coming into or return to the State; and if, after the tax or penalty under this Act becomes due and payable, the person alleged to be liable therefor departs from and remains out of the State, the time of his or her absence is no part of the time limited for the issuance of the notice of tax liability; but the foregoing provisions concerning absence from the State shall not apply to any case in which, at the time when a tax or penalty becomes due under this Act, the person allegedly liable therefor is not a resident of this State. The time limitation period</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 103-9, eff. 1-1-24; 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5">
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>In case any person engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail fails to file a return when and as herein required, but thereafter, prior to the Department's issuance of a notice of tax liability under this Section, files a return and pays the tax, he shall also pay a penalty in an amount determined in accordance with Section 3-3 of the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>In case any person engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail files the return at the time required by this Act but fails to pay the tax, or any part thereof, when due, a penalty in an amount determined in accordance with Section 3-3 of the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act shall be added thereto. In case any person engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail fails to file a return when and as herein required, but thereafter, prior to the Department's issuance of a notice of tax liability under this Section, files a return but fails to pay the entire tax, a penalty in an amount determined in accordance with Section 3-3 of the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act shall be added thereto. In case any person engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail fails to file a return, the Department shall determine the amount of tax due from him according to its best judgment and information, which amount so fixed by the Department shall be prima facie correct and shall be prima facie evidence of the correctness of the amount of tax due, as shown in such determination. In making any such determination of tax due, it shall be permissible for the Department to show a figure that represents the tax due for any given period of 6 months instead of showing the amount of tax due for each month separately. Proof of such determination by the Department may be made at any hearing before the Department or in any legal proceeding by a reproduced copy or computer print-out of the Department's record relating thereto in the name of the Department under the certificate of the Director of Revenue. If reproduced copies of the Department's records are offered as proof of such determination, the Director must certify that those copies are true and exact copies of records on file with the Department. If computer print-outs of the Department's records are offered as proof of such determination, the Director must certify that those computer print-outs are true and exact representations of records properly entered into standard electronic computing equipment, in the regular course of the Department's business, at or reasonably near the time of the occurrence of the facts recorded, from trustworthy and reliable information. Such certified reproduced copy or certified computer print-out shall, without further proof, be admitted into evidence before the Department or in any legal proceeding and shall be prima facie proof of the correctness of the amount of tax due, as shown therein. The Department shall issue the taxpayer a notice of tax liability for the amount of tax claimed by the Department to be due, together with a penalty of 30% thereof. For sales sourced under this Act to the Illinois location to which the tangible personal property is shipped or delivered or at which possession is taken by the purchaser, if the taxpayer fails to provide the information, schedules, or supporting documents necessary to determine such location, the Department shall, in lieu of imposing a penalty for an unprocessable return under the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act, assess tax on the gross receipts of such sales at the rate of 15%. However, where the failure to file any tax return required under this Act on the date prescribed therefor (including any extensions thereof), is shown to be unintentional and nonfraudulent and has not occurred in the 2 years immediately preceding the failure to file on the prescribed date or is due to other reasonable cause the penalties imposed by this Act shall not apply. The taxpayer or the taxpayer's legal representative may, within 60 days after such notice, file a protest to such notice of tax liability with the Department and request a hearing thereon. The Department shall give notice to such person or the legal representative of such person of the time and place fixed for such hearing, and shall hold a hearing in conformity with the provisions of this Act, and pursuant thereto shall issue a final assessment to such person or to the legal representative of such person for the amount found to be due as a result of such hearing. On and after July 1, 2013, protests concerning matters that are under the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal shall be filed with the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal in accordance with the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012, and hearings concerning those matters shall be held before the Tribunal in accordance with that Act. With respect to protests filed with the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal, the Tribunal shall give notice to that person or the legal representative of that person of the time and place fixed for a hearing, and shall hold a hearing in conformity with the provisions of this Act and the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012; and pursuant thereto the Department shall issue a final assessment to such person or to the legal representative of such person for the amount found to be due as a result of the hearing. With respect to protests filed with the Department prior to July 1, 2013 that would otherwise be subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal, the taxpayer may elect to be subject to the provisions of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012 at any time on or after July 1, 2013, but not later than 30 days after the date on which the protest was filed. If made, the election shall be irrevocable. If a protest to the notice of tax liability and a request for a hearing thereon is not filed within 60 days after such notice, such notice of tax liability shall become final without the necessity of a final assessment being issued and shall be deemed to be a final assessment. After the issuance of a final assessment, or a notice of tax liability which becomes final without the necessity of actually issuing a final assessment as hereinbefore provided, the Department, at any time before such assessment is reduced to judgment, may (subject to rules of the Department) grant a rehearing (or grant departmental review and hold an original hearing if no previous hearing in the matter has been held) upon the application of the person aggrieved. Pursuant to such hearing or rehearing, the Department shall issue a revised final assessment to such person or his legal representative for the amount found to be due as a result of such hearing or rehearing. Except in case of failure to file a return, or with the consent of the person to whom the notice of tax liability is to be issued, no notice of tax liability shall be issued on and after each July 1 and January 1 covering gross receipts received during any month or period of time more than 3 years prior to such July 1 and January 1, respectively, except that if a return is not filed at the required time, no notice of tax liability may be issued on and after each July 1 and January 1 for such return filed more than 3 years prior to such July 1 and January 1, respectively. The foregoing limitations upon the issuance of a notice of tax liability shall not apply to the issuance of any such notice with respect to any period of time prior thereto in cases where the Department has, within the period of limitation then provided, notified a person of the amount of tax computed even though the Department had not determined the amount of tax due from such person in the manner required herein prior to the issuance of such notice, but in no case shall the amount of any such notice of tax liability for any period otherwise barred by this Act exceed for such period the amount shown in the notice theretofore issued. If, when a tax or penalty under this Act becomes due and payable, the person alleged to be liable therefor is out of the State, the notice of tax liability may be issued within the times herein limited after his or her coming into or return to the State; and if, after the tax or penalty under this Act becomes due and payable, the person alleged to</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5a">
            <num>5a</num>
            <heading>The Department shall have a lien for the tax herein imposed or any
portion thereof, or for any penalty provided for in this Act, or for any
amount of interest which may be due as provided for in Section 5 of this
Act, upon all the real and personal property of any person to whom a
final assessment or revised final assessment has been issued as provided in
this Act, or whenever a return is filed without payment of the tax or
penalty shown therein to be due, including all such property of such
persons acquired after receipt of such assessment or filing of such return</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The taxpayer is liable for the filing fee imposed by the Department for
filing the lien and the filing fee imposed by the Department to 
release the lien. The filing fees shall be paid to the Department in
addition to payment of the tax, penalty, and interest included in the amount of
the lien. However, where the lien arises because of the issuance of a final
assessment or revised final assessment by the Department, such lien shall
not attach and the notice hereinafter referred to in this Section shall not
be filed until all proceedings in court for review of such final assessment
or revised final assessment have terminated or the time for the taking
thereof has expired without such proceedings being instituted. Upon the granting of a rehearing or departmental review pursuant to
Section 4 or Section 5 of this Act after a lien has attached, such lien
shall remain in full force except to the extent to which the final
assessment may be reduced by a revised final assessment following such
rehearing or review. The lien created by the issuance of a final assessment shall terminate
unless a notice of lien is filed, as provided in Section 5b hereof,
within 3 years from the date all proceedings in court for the review of
such final assessment have terminated or the time for the taking thereof
has expired without such proceedings being instituted, or (in the case of a
revised final assessment issued pursuant to a rehearing or departmental
review) within 3 years from the date all proceedings in court for the
review of such revised final assessment have terminated or the time for the
taking thereof has expired without such proceedings being instituted; and
where the lien results from the filing of a return without payment of the
tax or penalty shown therein to be due, the lien shall terminate unless a
notice of lien is filed, as provided in Section 5b hereof, within 3 years
from the date when such return is filed with the Department: Provided that
the time limitation period on the Department's right to file a notice of
lien shall not run (1) during any period of time in which the order of any
court has the effect of enjoining or restraining the Department from filing
such notice of lien, or (2) during the term of a repayment plan that taxpayer has entered into with the Department, as long as taxpayer remains in compliance with the terms of the repayment plan. If the Department finds that a taxpayer is about to depart from the
State, or to conceal himself or his property, or to do any other act
tending to prejudice or to render wholly or partly ineffectual proceedings
to collect such tax unless such proceedings are brought without delay, or
if the Department finds that the collection of the amount due from any
taxpayer will be jeopardized by delay, the Department shall give the
taxpayer notice of such findings and shall make demand for immediate return
and payment of such tax, whereupon such tax shall become immediately due
and payable. If the taxpayer, within 5 days after such notice (or within
such extension of time as the Department may grant), does not comply with
such notice or show to the Department that the findings in such notice are
erroneous, the Department may file a notice of jeopardy assessment lien in
the State Tax Lien Registry and shall notify the taxpayer of such filing.
Such jeopardy assessment lien shall have the same scope and effect as the
statutory lien hereinbefore provided for in this Section. If the taxpayer believes that he does not owe some or all of the tax for
which the jeopardy assessment lien against him has been filed, or that no
jeopardy to the revenue in fact exists, he may protest within 20 days after
being notified by the Department of the filing of such jeopardy assessment
lien and request a hearing, whereupon the Department shall hold a hearing
in conformity with the provisions of this Act and, pursuant thereto, shall
notify the taxpayer of its findings as to whether or not such jeopardy
assessment lien will be released. If not, and if the taxpayer is aggrieved
by this decision, he  may file an action for judicial review
of such final
determination of the Department in accordance with Section 12 of this Act
and the Administrative Review Law. On and after July 1, 2013, protests concerning matters that are subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal shall be filed with the  Tribunal, and hearings on those matters shall be held before the Tribunal in accordance with the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012.  The Tribunal shall
notify the taxpayer of its findings as to whether or not such jeopardy
assessment lien will be released. If not, and if the taxpayer is aggrieved
by this decision, he  may file an action for judicial review
of such final
determination of the Department in accordance with Section 12 of this Act
and the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012. With respect to protests filed with the Department prior to July 1, 2013 that would otherwise be subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal, the taxpayer may elect to be subject to the provisions of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012 at any time on or after July 1, 2013, but not later than 30 days after the date on which the protest was filed.  If made, the election shall be irrevocable. If, pursuant to such hearing (or after an independent determination of
the facts by the Department without a hearing), the Department or the Tribunal determines
that some or all of the tax covered by the jeopardy assessment lien is not
owed by the taxpayer, or that no jeopardy to the revenue exists, or if on
judicial review the final judgment of the court is that the taxpayer does
not owe some or all of the tax covered by the jeopardy assessment lien
against him, or that no jeopardy to the revenue exists, the Department
shall release its jeopardy assessment lien to the extent of such finding of
nonliability for the tax, or to the extent of such finding of no jeopardy
to the revenue. The Department shall also release its jeopardy assessment lien against
the taxpayer whenever the tax and penalty covered by such lien, plus any
interest which may be due, are paid
and the taxpayer has paid the Department in cash or by guaranteed remittance
an amount representing the filing fee for the lien and the filing fee for the
release of that lien. The Department shall file that release of lien in the State Tax Lien Registry. Nothing in this Section shall be construed to give the Department a
preference over the rights of any bona fide purchaser, holder of a
security interest, mechanics lienholder, mortgagee, or judgment lien
creditor arising prior to the filing of a regular
notice of lien or a notice of jeopardy assessment lien in the State Tax Lien Registry: Provided, however, that the word &quot;bona fide&quot;, as used in this
Section shall not include any mortgage of real or personal property or any
other credit transaction that results in the mortgagee or the holder of the
security acting as trustee for unsecured creditors of the taxpayer
mentioned in the notice of lien who executed such chattel or real property
mortgage or the document evidencing such credit transaction. Such lien
shall be inferior to the lien of general taxes, special assessments and
special taxes heretofore or hereafter levied by any political subdivision
of this State. In case title to land to be affected by the notice of lien or notice of
jeopardy assessment lien is registered under the provisions of &quot;An Act
concerning land titles&quot;, approved May 1, 1897, as amended, such notice
shall also be filed in the State Tax Lien Registry, and the
Department shall not have a preference over the rights of any bona fide
purchaser, mortgagee, judgment creditor or other lien holder arising prior
to the registration of such notice: Provided, however, that the word &quot;bona
fide&quot; </p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-22, eff. 1-1-18 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5b">
            <num>5b</num>
            <heading>State Tax Lien Index</heading>
            <content>
              <p>The Department of Revenue shall maintain a State Tax Lien Index of all tax liens filed in the State Tax Lien Registry as provided for by the State Tax Lien Registration Act. A notice of lien may be filed after the issuance of a revised final
assessment pursuant to a rehearing or departmental review under Section 4
or Section 5 of this Act. When the lien obtained pursuant to this Act has been satisfied
and the taxpayer has paid the Department in cash or by guaranteed remittance
an amount representing the filing fee for the lien and the filing fee for the
release of that lien,
the Department shall issue a release
of lien and file that release of lien in the State Tax Lien Registry. The release of lien shall contain in legible letters a
statement as
follows: FOR THE PROTECTION OF THE OWNER, THIS RELEASE SHALL BE FILED IN THE STATE TAX LIEN REGISTRY. When a certificate of complete or partial release of lien issued by the
Department is filed in the State Tax Lien Registry, the Department of Revenue shall permanently attach the certificate of release to the notice
of lien or notice of jeopardy assessment lien and shall enter the
certificate of release and the date in the &quot;State Tax Lien Index&quot; on the
line where the notice of lien or notice of jeopardy assessment lien is
entered.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-22, eff. 1-1-18 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5c">
            <num>5c</num>
            <heading>Upon payment by the taxpayer to the Department in cash or by guaranteed
remittance of an amount representing the filing fee for the lien and the filing
fee for the release of that lien,
the Department shall issue a certificate of complete or partial
release of the lien
and file that complete or partial release of lien in the State Tax Lien Registry: (a) to the extent that the fair market value of any property subject to the lien exceeds the amount of the lien plus the amount of all prior liens upon such property; (b) to the extent that such lien shall become unenforceable; (c) to the extent that the amount of such lien is paid by the retailer whose property is subject to such lien, together with any interest which may become due under Section 5 of this Act between the date when the notice of lien is filed and the date when the amount of such lien is paid; (d) to the extent that there is furnished to the Department on a form to be approved and with a surety or sureties satisfactory to the Department a bond that is conditioned upon the payment of the amount of such lien, together with any interest which may become due under Section 5 of this Act after the notice of lien is filed, but before the amount thereof is fully paid; (e) to the extent and under the circumstances specified in Section 5a of this Act in the case of jeopardy assessment liens; (f) to the extent to which an assessment is reduced pursuant to a rehearing or departmental review under Section 4 or Section 5 of this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>A certificate of complete or partial release of any lien shall be held
conclusive that the lien upon the property covered by the certificate is
extinguished to the extent indicated by such certificate.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-22, eff. 1-1-18 .</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5d">
            <num>5d</num>
            <heading>The Department is not required to furnish any bond nor to
make a deposit for or pay any costs or fees of any court or officer thereof
in any judicial proceedings under this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever a
certified copy of a judgment or order for attachment, issued from any
court for the enforcement or collection of any liability created by this
Act, is levied by any sheriff or coroner upon any personal property, and
such property is claimed by any person other than the
judgment debtor or the defendant in the attachment, or is
claimed by the judgment debtor or defendant in the attachment as exempt
from enforcement of a judgment thereon by virtue of the
exemption laws of this State, then the person making such claim shall give
notice in writing of his or her claim and of his or her intention to prosecute
the claim, to the sheriff or coroner within 10 days after the making of the
levy. On receiving such notice, the sheriff or coroner shall proceed in
accordance with Part 2 of Article XII of the Code of Civil Procedure, as
amended. The giving of such notice within the 10 day period is a condition precedent
to any judicial action against the sheriff or coroner for wrongfully
levying, seizing or selling the property and any such person who fails to
give such notice within that time is barred from bringing any judicial
action against such sheriff or coroner for injury or damages to or
conversion of the property.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 83-1362.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5e">
            <num>5e</num>
            <heading>In addition to any other remedy provided for by the laws of this
State,
and provided that no hearing or proceedings for review provided by this
Act shall be pending, and the time for the taking thereof shall have expired,
the Department may foreclose in the circuit court any
lien on real property for any tax or penalty imposed by this Act to the
same extent and in the same manner as in the enforcement of other liens</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Provided that such proceedings to foreclose shall not be instituted more
than 20 years after the filing of the notice of lien under the provisions of
Section 5b hereof, except that the time limitation period on the
Department's right to commence any such foreclosure proceeding shall not
run during any period of time in which a court order has the
effect of enjoining or restraining the Department from commencing such
foreclosure proceeding.  The process, practice and procedure for such
foreclosure shall be the same as provided in the Civil Practice Law, as
amended.  The provisions of this amendatory Act of 1984 shall apply to any lien
which has not expired before the effective date of this amendatory Act of 1984.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 83-1416.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5f">
            <num>5f</num>
            <heading>In addition to any other remedy provided for by the laws of
this State, if the tax imposed by this Act is not paid within the time
required by this Act, the Department, or some person designated by it,
may cause a demand to be made on the taxpayer for the payment of the
tax</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If the tax remains unpaid for 10 days after demand has been made
and no proceedings have been taken for review, the Department may issue
a warrant directed to the sheriff of any county of the State or to any
State officer authorized to serve process, commanding the sheriff or
other officer to levy upon property and rights to property (whether real
or personal, tangible or intangible) of the taxpayer, without exemption,
found within his or her jurisdiction, for the
payment of the amount of unpaid tax with the added penalties, interest
and the cost of executing the warrant.  The term &quot;levy&quot; includes the power
of distraint and seizure by any means.  In any case in which the warrant
to levy has been issued, the sheriff or other person to whom the warrant
was directed may seize and sell such property or rights to property.  Such
warrant shall be returned
to the Department together with the money collected by virtue of the
warrant within the time specified in the warrant, which may not be less
than 20 nor more than 90 days from the date of the warrant. The sheriff
or other officer to whom such warrant is directed shall proceed in the same
manner as is
prescribed by law for proceeding
against property to enforce
judgments which are entered by a circuit court of this State,
and is entitled to the same fees for his or her
services in executing the warrant, to be collected in the same manner.
The Department, or some officer, employee or agent designated by it, may
bid for and purchase any such property sold. No proceedings for a levy under this Section may be commenced more
than 20 years after the latest date for filing of the notice of lien
under Section 5b of
this Act, without regard to whether such notice was actually filed. Any officer or employee of the Department designated in writing by the
Director is authorized to serve process under this Section to levy upon
accounts or other intangible assets of a taxpayer held by a financial
organization, as defined by Section 1501 of the Illinois Income Tax Act.
In addition to any other provisions of this Section, any officer or
employee of the Department designated in writing by the Director may levy
upon the following property and rights to property belonging to a taxpayer:
contractual payments, accounts and notes receivable and other evidences of
debt, and interest on bonds, by serving a notice of levy on the person
making such payment.  Levy shall not be made until the Department has
caused a demand to be made on the taxpayer in the manner provided above.
In addition to any other provisions of this Section, any officer or
employee of the Department designated in writing by the Director, may levy
upon the salary, wages, commissions and bonuses of any employee, including officers, employees, or elected officials of
the
United States
as authorized by Section 5520a of the Government Organization and Employees
Act (5 U.S.C. 5520a), but not upon the salary or wages of officers, employees,
or elected officials of any state other than this State, by serving a notice of
levy on the employer.  Levy shall not be made until the Department has
caused a demand to be made on the employee in the manner provided above.
The provisions of Section 12-803 of the Code of Civil Procedure relating
to maximum compensation subject to collection under wage deduction orders
shall apply to all levies made upon compensation under this Section.
To the extent of the amount due on the levy, the employer or other person
making payments to the taxpayer shall hold any non-exempt wages or other
payments due or which subsequently come due.  The levy or balance due
thereon is a lien on wages or other payments due at the time of the service
of the notice of levy, and such lien shall continue as to subsequent
earnings and other payments until the total amount due upon the levy is
paid, except that such lien on subsequent earnings or other payments shall
terminate sooner if the employment relationship is terminated or if the
notice of levy is rescinded or modified.  The employer or other person
making payments to the taxpayer shall file, on or before the return dates
stated in the notice of levy (which shall not be more often than bimonthly)
a written answer under oath to interrogatories, setting forth the amount
due as wages or other payments to the taxpayer for the payment periods
ending immediately prior to the appropriate return date.  A lien obtained
hereunder shall have priority over any subsequent lien obtained pursuant to
Section 12-808 of the Code of Civil Procedure, except that liens for the
support of a spouse or dependent children shall have priority over all
liens obtained hereunder. In any case where property or rights to property have been seized by an
officer of the Illinois Department of Law Enforcement, or successor agency
thereto, under the authority of
a warrant to levy issued by the Department of Revenue, the Department of
Revenue may take possession of and may sell such property or rights to
property and the Department of Revenue may contract with third persons to
conduct sales of such property or rights to the property. In the conduct of
such sales, the Department of Revenue shall proceed in the same manner as
is prescribed by law for proceeding against property to enforce judgments
which are entered by a circuit court of this State. If, in the Department's
opinion, no offer to purchase at such sale is acceptable and the State's
interest would be better served by retaining the property for sale at a
later date, then the Department may decline to accept any bid and may
retain the property for sale at a later date.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 89-399, eff. 8-20-95.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5g">
            <num>5g</num>
            <heading>Except as to any sale had by virtue of a judgment of
foreclosure in accordance with Article XV of the Code of Civil Procedure,
whenever any real estate has been or is sold at a judicial sale
or a sale for the enforcement of a judgment and such real estate is then
subject to a tax lien or
notice of tax lien in favor of the Department, as hereinbefore provided,
and which is junior or inferior to the lien so enforced or foreclosed by
or through that sale, the right to redeem in any manner under or by
virtue of such tax lien or claim for tax lien from such sale or from the
lien so foreclosed or enforced terminates at the end of 12 months from
the date upon which there is filed for record in the office of the
recorder for the county in which the lands so sold are
situated, if such lands are unregistered, or in the office of the
Registrar of Titles for such county, if such lands are registered, a
certified copy of the original or duplicate recorded or registered
certificate of such sale, such certified copy being endorsed by the
Director of Revenue showing service of a copy of such certificate upon
him or her, and upon such service it shall be the duty of such officer to make
such endorsement</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Service may be by United States
registered or certified mail.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 84-1462.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5i">
            <num>5i</num>
            <heading>Any person who incurs tax liability under this Act, and who
removes from this State or conceals his whereabouts, shall be deemed
thereby to appoint the Secretary of State of Illinois his agent for service
of process or notice in any judicial or administrative proceeding under
this Act</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Such process or notice shall be served by the Department on the
Secretary of State by leaving, at the office of the Secretary of State at
least 15 days before the return day of such process or notice, a true and
certified copy thereof, and by sending to the taxpayer by registered or
certified mail, postage prepaid, a like and true certified copy, with an
endorsement thereon of the service upon said Secretary of State, addressed
to such taxpayer at his last known address. Service of process or notice in the manner provided for in this Section,
under the circumstances specified in this Section, shall be of the same
force and validity as if served upon the taxpayer personally within this
State. Proof of such service upon the taxpayer in this State through the
Secretary of State as his agent and by mailing to the last known address of
the taxpayer may be made in such judicial or administrative proceeding by
the affidavit of the Director of Revenue, or by his duly authorized
representative who made such service, with a copy of the process or notice
that was so served attached to such affidavit.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1961, p. 1918.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5j">
            <num>5j</num>
            <heading>If any taxpayer, outside the usual course of his business, sells or
transfers the major part of any one or more of (A) the stock of goods which
he is engaged in the business of selling, or (B) the furniture or fixtures,
(C) the machinery and equipment, or (D) the real property, of
any business that is subject to the
provisions of this Act, the purchaser or transferee of such asset shall,
no later than 10 business days prior to the sale or transfer, file a
notice of sale or transfer of business assets with the Department disclosing the
name and address of the seller
or transferor, the name and address of the purchaser or transferee, the
date of the sale or transfer, a copy of the sales contract and financing
agreements which shall include a description of the property sold, the
amount of the purchase price or a statement of other consideration for
the sale or transfer, the terms for payment of the purchase price, and
such other information as the Department
may reasonably require</heading>
            <content>
              <p>If the purchaser or transferee fails to file the
above described notice of sale with the Department within the prescribed
time, the purchaser or transferee shall be personally liable for the amount
owed hereunder by the seller or transferor to the Department up to the
amount of the reasonable value of the property acquired by the purchaser or
transferee. The seller or transferor shall pay the Department
the amount of tax, penalty and interest (if any) due from him under this
Act up to the date of the payment of tax. The seller or
transferor, or the purchaser
or transferee, at least 10 business days before the date of the sale or transfer,
may notify the Department of the intended sale or transfer and request the
Department to audit the books and records of the seller or transferor, or
to do whatever else may be necessary to determine how much the seller or
transferor owes to the Department hereunder up to the date of the sale or
transfer. The Department shall take such steps as may be appropriate to
comply with such request. Any order issued by the Department pursuant to this Section to withhold
from the purchase price shall be issued within 10 business days after the Department
receives notification of a sale as provided in this Section.
The purchaser or transferee shall withhold such portion of
the purchase price
as may be directed by the Department, but not to exceed a
minimum amount varying by type of business, as determined by the Department
pursuant to regulations, plus twice the outstanding unpaid liabilities and
twice the average liability of preceding filings times the number of
unfiled returns,
to cover the amount of all tax, penalty and interest due and unpaid by the
seller or transferor under this Act or, if the payment of money or property
is not involved, shall withhold the performance of the condition that
constitutes the consideration for the sale or transfer.  Within 60
business days after issuance of the initial order to
withhold, the Department shall provide written notice to the purchaser or
transferee of the actual amount of all taxes, penalties and interest then
due and whether or not additional amounts may become due as a result of
unfiled returns, pending assessments and audits not completed.  The
purchaser or transferee shall continue to withhold the amount directed to
be withheld by the initial order or such lesser amount as is specified by
the final withholding order or to withhold the performance of the condition
which constitutes the consideration for the sale or transfer
 until the
purchaser or transferee receives from the Department a certificate showing
that such tax,
penalty and interest have been paid or a certificate from the Department
showing that no tax, penalty or interest is due from the seller or
transferor under this Act. The purchaser or transferee is relieved of any duty to continue to withhold from the
purchase price and of any liability for tax, penalty or interest due
hereunder from the seller or transferor if the Department fails to notify
the purchaser or transferee in the manner provided herein of the amount
to be withheld within 10 business days after the sale
or transfer has been reported to the Department or within 60 business days after
issuance of the initial order to withhold, as the case may be.
The Department shall have the right to determine amounts claimed on an
estimated basis to allow for non-filed periods, pending assessments and
audits not completed, however the purchaser or transferee shall be
personally liable only for the actual amount due when determined. If the seller or transferor fails to pay the tax, penalty and interest
(if any) due from him hereunder and the Department makes timely claim
therefor against the purchaser or transferee as hereinabove provided, then
the purchaser or transferee shall pay the amount so withheld from the
purchase price to the Department. If the purchaser or transferee fails to
comply with the requirements of this Section, the purchaser or transferee
shall be personally liable to the Department for the amount owed hereunder
by the seller or transferor to the Department up to the amount of the
reasonable value of the property acquired by the purchaser or transferee. Any person who shall acquire any property or rights thereto which, at
the time of such acquisition, is subject to a valid lien in favor of the
Department shall be personally liable to the Department for a sum equal to
the amount of taxes secured by such lien but not to exceed the reasonable
value of such property acquired by him.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-1171, eff. 1-4-19.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5k">
            <num>5k</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; enterprise zone</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each retailer who makes a qualified sale of building
materials
to be incorporated into real estate in an enterprise zone
established by a county or municipality under the Illinois Enterprise Zone
Act
by remodeling,
rehabilitation or new construction, may deduct receipts from such sales
when calculating the tax imposed by this Act.
For purposes of this Section, before July  1, 2013, &quot;qualified sale&quot; means a sale of building
materials that will be incorporated into real estate as part of a building
project for which a Certificate of Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption has been
issued by the administrator of the enterprise zone in which the building
project is located, and on and after July  1, 2013, &quot;qualified sale&quot; means a sale of building materials that will be incorporated into real estate as part of a building project for which an Enterprise Zone Building Materials Exemption Certificate has been issued to the purchaser by the Department. A construction contractor or other entity shall not make tax-free purchases unless it has an active Exemption Certificate issued by the Department at the time of the purchase.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before July  1, 2013, to document the exemption allowed under this Section, the
retailer must obtain from the purchaser a copy of the Certificate of
Eligibility for Sales Tax Exemption issued by the administrator of the
enterprise zone into which the building materials will be incorporated. On and after July  1, 2013, to document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser the certification required under subsection</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the construction contractor or other entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and number of the enterprise zone;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and location or address of the building project in the enterprise zone;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the estimated amount of the exemption for each construction contractor or other entity for which a request for Exemption Certificate is made, based on a stated estimated average tax rate and the percentage of the contract that consists of materials;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the period of time over which supplies for the project are expected to be purchased; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other reasonable information as the Department may require, including, but not limited to FEIN numbers, to determine if the contractor or other entity, or any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity,  is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. The Department shall issue the Enterprise Zone Building Materials Exemption Certificates within 3 business days after receipt of request from the zone administrator.  This requirement does not apply in circumstances where the Department, for reasonable cause, is unable to issue the Exemption Certificate within 3 business days.  The Department may refuse to issue an Exemption Certificate if the owner, any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department.  The Enterprise Zone Building Materials Exemption Certificate shall contain language stating that if the construction contractor or other entity who is issued the Exemption Certificate makes a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section or allows another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have be</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>made a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section or allowed another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have been paid by the retailer under this Act as well as any applicable local retailers' occupation tax on the purchase that was not eligible for the exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition, the retailer must obtain certification from the purchaser that
contains:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5k__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the building materials are being purchased for incorporation into real estate located i</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-905, eff. 8-7-12; 98-109, eff. 7-25-13.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5l">
            <num>5l</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; High Impact Business</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning January 1, 1995, each retailer who makes a sale of
building materials that will be incorporated into a High Impact Business
location as designated by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity
under Section 5.5 of the Illinois Enterprise Zone Act may deduct receipts from
such sales when calculating only the 6.25% State rate of tax
imposed by this Act. Beginning on the effective date of this amendatory Act of
1995, a retailer may also deduct receipts from such sales when calculating any
applicable local taxes. However, until the effective date of this amendatory
Act of 1995, a retailer may file claims for credit or refund to recover the
amount of any applicable local tax paid on such sales. No retailer who is
eligible for the deduction or credit
under Section 5k of this Act for making a sale of building materials to be
incorporated into real estate in an enterprise zone by rehabilitation,
remodeling or new construction shall be eligible for the deduction or
credit authorized under this Section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On and after July 1, 2013, in addition to any other requirements to document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser the purchaser's High Impact Business Building Materials Exemption Certificate number issued by the Department. A construction contractor or other entity shall not make tax-free purchases unless it has an active Exemption Certificate issued by the Department at the time of purchase. Upon request from the designated High Impact Business, the Department shall issue a High Impact Business Building Materials Exemption Certificate for each construction contractor or other entity identified by the designated High Impact Business.  The Department shall make the Exemption Certificates available to each construction contractor or other entity and the designated High Impact Business.  The request for Building Materials Exemption Certificates from the designated High Impact Business to the Department must include the following information:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the construction contractor or other entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and location or address of the designated High Impact Business;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the estimated amount of the exemption for each construction contractor or other entity for which a request for Exemption Certificate is made, based on a stated estimated average tax rate and the percentage of the contract that consists of materials;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the period of time over which supplies for the project are expected to be purchased; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other reasonable information as the Department may require, including but not limited to FEIN numbers, to determine if the contractor or other entity, or any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity,  is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. The Department shall issue the High Impact Business Building Materials Exemption Certificates within 3 business days after receipt of request from the designated High Impact Business.  This requirement does not apply in circumstances where the Department, for reasonable cause, is unable to issue the Exemption Certificate within 3 business days.  The Department may refuse to issue an Exemption Certificate if the owner, any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department.  The High Impact Business Building Materials Exemption Certificate shall contain language stating that if the construction contractor or other entity who is issued the Exemption Certificate makes a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section or allows another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the </p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>made a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section or allowed another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have been paid by the retailer under this Act as well as any applicable local retailers' occupation tax on the purchase that was not eligible for the exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in this Section, for High Impact Businesses for which projects are already in existence and for which construction contracts are already in place on July 1, 2013, the request for High Impact Business Building Materials Exemption Certificates from the High Impact Business to the Department for these pre-existing construction contractors and other entities must include the information required under subsection</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-5l__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-905, eff. 8-7-12; 98-109, eff. 7-25-13.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5m">
            <num>5m</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; REV Illinois projects</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Each retailer who makes a sale of building materials that will be incorporated into a REV Illinois Project for which a certificate of exemption has been issued by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity under Section 105 of the Reimagining Energy and Vehicles in Illinois Act may deduct receipts from those sales when calculating any State or local use and occupation taxes. No retailer who is eligible for the deduction or credit under Section 5k of this Act related to enterprise zones or Section 5l of this Act related to High Impact Businesses for a given sale shall be eligible for the deduction or credit authorized under this Section for that same sale. To document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser the purchaser's REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption certificate number issued by the Department and a certification that contains: (1)  a statement that the building materials are being purchased for incorporation into a REV Illinois Project; (2)  the location or address of the real estate into which the building materials will be incorporated; (3)  the name and address of the construction contractor or other entity; (4)  a description of the building materials being purchased; (5)  the purchaser's REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate number issued by the Department of Revenue; and (6)  the purchaser's signature and date of purchase. A construction contractor or other entity shall not make tax-free purchases under this Section unless it has an active REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate issued by the Department at the time of purchase. Upon request from the certified manufacturer, the Department shall issue a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate for each construction contractor or other entity identified by the certified manufacturer. The Department shall make the REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificates available to each construction contractor or other entity identified by the certified manufacturer and to the certified manufacturer. The request for REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificates under this Section must include the following information: (1) the name and address of the construction contractor or other entity; (2) the name and location or address of the building project site; (3) the estimated amount of the exemption for each construction contractor or other entity for which a request for a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate is made, based on a stated estimated average tax rate and the percentage of the contract that consists of materials; (4) the period of time over which supplies for the project are expected to be purchased; and (5) other reasonable information as the Department may require, including but not limited to FEIN numbers, to determine if the contractor or other entity, or any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity, is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. The Department shall issue the REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificates within 3 business days after receipt of the request from the certified manufacturer. This requirement does not apply in circumstances where the Department, for reasonable cause, is unable to issue the Exemption Certificate within 3 business days. The Department may refuse to issue a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate if the owner, any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. The REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate shall contain language stating that if the construction contractor or other entity who is issued the Exemption Certificate makes a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section or allows another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have been paid by the retailer under this Act as well as any applicable local retailers' occupation tax on the purchase that is not eligible for the exemption. The Department, in its discretion, may require that the request for REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificates be submitted electronically. The Department may, in its discretion, issue the Exemption Certificates electronically. The REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate number shall be designed in such a way that the Department can identify from the unique number on the Exemption Certificate issued to a given construction contractor or other entity, the name of the REV Illinois project site and the construction contractor or other entity to whom the Exemption Certificate is issued. The REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate shall contain an expiration date, which shall be no more than 5 years after the date of issuance. At the request of the certified manufacturer, the Department may renew a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate. After the Department issues Exemption Certificates for a given REV Illinois project site, the certified manufacturer may notify the Department of additional construction contractors or other entities that are eligible for a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate. Upon receiving such a notification and subject to the other provisions of this Section, the Department shall issue a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate to each additional construction contractor or other entity so identified. A certified manufacturer may ask the Department to rescind a REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate previously issued by the Department to a construction contractor or other entity working at that certified manufacturer's REV Illinois project site if that REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate has not yet expired. Upon receiving such a request and subject to the other provisions of this Section, the Department shall issue the rescission of the REV Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate to the construction contractor or other entity identified by the certified manufacturer and provide a copy of the rescission to the construction contractor or other entity and to the certified manufacturer. If the Department of Revenue determines that a construction contractor or other entity that was issued an Exemption Certificate under this Section made a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section or allowed another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have been paid by the retailer under this Act as well as any applicable local retailers' occupation tax on the purchase that was not eligible for the exemption. This Section is exempt from the provisions of Section 2-70. As used in this Section, &quot;certified manufacturer&quot; means a person certified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunit</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 102-669, eff. 11-16-21; 102-1125, eff. 2-3-23; 103-712, eff. 7-19-24.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-5n">
            <num>5n</num>
            <heading>Building materials exemption; microchip and semiconductor manufacturing</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Each retailer who makes a sale of building materials that will be incorporated into real estate in a qualified facility for which a certificate of exemption has been issued by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity under Section 110-105 of the Manufacturing Illinois Chips for Real Opportunity (MICRO) Act, may deduct receipts from such sales when calculating any State or local use and occupation taxes. No retailer who is eligible for the deduction or credit under Section 5k of this Act related to enterprise zones or Section 5l of this Act related to High Impact Businesses for a given sale shall be eligible for the deduction or credit authorized under this Section for that same sale. To document the exemption allowed under this Section, the retailer must obtain from the purchaser the purchaser's exemption certificate number issued by the Department and a certification that contains: (1)  a statement that the building materials are being purchased for incorporation into real estate in a qualified facility; (2)  the location or address of the real estate into which the building materials will be incorporated; (3)  the name and address of the construction contractor or other entity; (4)  a description of the building materials being purchased; (5)  the purchaser's MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate number issued by the Department of Revenue; and (6)  the purchaser's signature and date of purchase. A construction contractor or other entity shall not make tax-free purchases unless it has an active exemption certificate issued by the Department at the time of purchase. Upon request from a person that has been certified by the Department of Commerce and Economic Opportunity under the Manufacturing Illinois Chips for Real Opportunity (MICRO) Act, the Department shall issue a MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate for each construction contractor or other entity identified by the person so certified. The Department shall make the MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificates available to each construction contractor or other entity as well as the person certified under the Manufacturing Illinois Chips for Real Opportunity (MICRO) Act. The request for MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificates must include the following information: (1) the name and address of the construction contractor or other entity; (2) the name and location or address of the building project site; (3) the estimated amount of the exemption for each construction contractor or other entity for which a request for an exemption certificate is made, based on a stated estimated average tax rate and the percentage of the contract that consists of materials; (4) the period of time over which supplies for the project are expected to be purchased; and (5) other reasonable information as the Department may require, including but not limited to FEIN numbers, to determine if the contractor or other entity, or any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity, is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. The Department shall issue the exemption certificate within 3 business days after receipt of request. This requirement does not apply in circumstances where the Department, for reasonable cause, is unable to issue the exemption certificate within 3 business days. The Department may refuse to issue an  exemption certificate under this Section if the owner, any partner, or a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, any manager or member, of the construction contractor or other entity is or has been the owner, a partner, a corporate officer, and in the case of a limited liability company, a manager or member, of a person that is in default for moneys due to the Department under this Act or any other tax or fee Act administered by the Department. The MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate shall contain language stating that, if the construction contractor or other entity who is issued the exemption certificate makes a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section or allows another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that is not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have been paid by the retailer under this Act as well as any applicable local retailers' occupation tax on the purchase that is not eligible for the exemption. The Department, in its discretion, may require that the request for a MICRO Illinois Exemption Certificate be submitted electronically. The Department may, in its discretion, issue the exemption certificates electronically. The MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate number shall be designed in such a way that the Department can identify from the unique number on the exemption certificate issued to a given construction contractor or other entity, the name of the entity to whom the exemption certificate is issued. The MICRO Illinois Building Materials Exemption Certificate shall contain an expiration date, which shall be no more than 5 years after the date of issuance. At the request of the entity to whom the exemption certificate is issued, the Department may renew an exemption certificate issued under this Section. After the Department issues exemption certificates under this Section, the certified entity may notify the Department of additional construction contractors or other entities eligible for an exemption certificate under this Section. Upon such a notification and subject to the other provisions of this Section, the Department shall issue an exemption certificate to each additional qualified construction contractor or other entity so identified. A certified entity may notify the Department to rescind an exemption certificate previously issued by the Department that has not yet expired. Upon such a notification and subject to the other provisions of this Section, the Department shall rescind the exemption certificate. If the Department of Revenue determines that a construction contractor or other entity that was issued an exemption certificate under this Section made a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section or allowed another person to make a tax-exempt purchase, as described in this Section, that was not eligible for exemption under this Section, then, in addition to any tax or other penalty imposed, the construction contractor or other entity is subject to a penalty equal to the tax that would have been paid by the retailer under this Act as well as any applicable local retailers' occupation tax on the purchase that was not eligible for the exemption. This Section is exempt from the provisions of Section 2-70.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 102-700, eff. 4-19-22; 103-712, eff. 7-19-24.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-6">
            <num>6</num>
            <heading>Credit memorandum or refund</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-6__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that the claimant bore the burden of such amount and has not been relieved thereof nor reimbursed therefor and has not shifted such burden directly or indirectly through inclusion of such amount in the price of the tangible personal property sold by him or her or in any manner whatsoever; and that no understanding or agreement, written or oral, exists whereby he or she or his or her legal representative may be relieved of the burden of such amount, be reimbursed therefor or may shift the burden thereof; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-6__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that he or she or his or her legal representative has repaid unconditionally such amount to his or her vendee</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who bore the burden thereof and has not shifted such burden directly or indirectly, in any manner whatsoever;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who, if he or she has shifted such burden, has repaid unconditionally such amount to his own vendee; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who is not entitled to receive any reimbursement therefor from any other source than from his or her vendor, nor to be relieved of such burden in any manner whatsoever. No credit may be allowed or refund made for any amount paid by or collected from any claimant unless it appears that the claimant has unconditionally repaid, to the purchaser, any amount collected from the purchaser and retained by the claimant with respect to the same transaction under the Use Tax Act. Any credit or refund that is allowed under this Section shall bear interest at the rate and in the manner specified in the Uniform Penalty and Interest Act. In case the Department determines that the claimant is entitled to a refund, such refund shall be made only from the Aviation Fuel Sales Tax Refund Fund or from such appropriation as may be available for that purpose, as appropriate. If it appears unlikely that the amount available would permit everyone having a claim allowed during the period covered by such appropriation or from the Aviation Fuel Sales Tax Refund Fund, as appropriate, to elect to receive a cash refund, the Department, by rule or regulation, shall provide for the payment of refunds in hardship cases and shall define what types of cases qualify as hardship cases. If a retailer who has failed to pay retailers' occupation tax on gross receipts from retail sales is required by the Department to pay such tax, such retailer, without filing any formal claim with the Department, shall be allowed to take credit against such retailers' occupation tax liability to the extent, if any, to which such retailer has paid an amount equivalent to retailers' occupation tax or has paid use tax in error to his or her vendor or vendors of the same tangible personal property which such retailer bought for resale and did not first use before selling it, and no penalty or interest shall be charged to such retailer on the amount of such credit. However, when such credit is allowed to the retailer by the De</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 104-6, eff. 6-16-25.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-6a">
            <num>6a</num>
            <heading>Claims for credit or refund shall be prepared and filed upon forms
provided by the Department</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Each claim shall state: (1) The name and
principal business address of the claimant; (2) the period covered by the
claim; (3) the total amount of credit or refund claimed, giving in detail
the net amount of taxable receipts reported each month or other return
period used by the claimant as the basis for filing returns in the period
covered by the claim; (4) the total amount of tax paid for each return
period; (5) receipts upon which tax liability is admitted for each return
period; (6) the amount of receipts on which credit or refund is claimed for
each return period; (7) the tax due for each return period as corrected;
(8) the amount of credit or refund claimed for each return period; (9)
reason or reasons why the amount, for which the claim is filed, is alleged
to have been paid in error; (10) a list of the evidence (documentary or
otherwise) which the claimant has available to establish his compliance
with Section 6 as to bearing the burden of the tax for which he seeks
credit or refund; (11) payments or parts thereof (if any) included in the
claim and paid by the claimant under protest; (12) sufficient information
to identify any suit which involves this Act, and to which the claimant is
a party, and (13) such other information as the Department may reasonably
require. Where the claimant is a corporation or limited liability company,
the claim filed on behalf of such corporation or limited liability company
shall be signed by the president, vice-president, secretary or treasurer, by
the properly accredited agent of such corporation, or by a manager, member, or
properly accredited agent of the limited liability company. A claim for credit or refund shall be considered to have been filed with
the Department on the date upon which it is received by the Department.
Upon receipt of any claim for credit or refund filed under this Act, any
officer or employee of the Department, authorized in writing by the
Director of Revenue to acknowledge receipt of such claims on behalf of the
Department, shall execute on behalf of the Department, and shall deliver or
mail to the claimant or his duly authorized agent, a written receipt,
acknowledging that the claim has been filed with the Department, describing
the claim in sufficient detail to identify it and stating the date upon
which the claim was received by the Department. Such written receipt shall
be prima facie evidence that the Department received the claim described in
such receipt and shall be prima facie evidence of the date when such claim
was received by the Department. In the absence of such a written receipt,
the records of the Department as to when the claim was received by the
Department, or as to whether or not the claim was received at all by the
Department, shall be deemed to be prima facie correct upon these questions
in the event of any dispute between the claimant (or his legal
representative) and the Department concerning these questions.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 88-480.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-6b">
            <num>6b</num>
            <heading>As soon as practicable after a claim for credit or refund is filed,
the Department shall examine the same and determine the amount of credit or
refund to which the claimant or the taxpayer's legal representative, in the
event that the taxpayer has died or become incompetent, is entitled and shall,
by its Notice of Tentative Determination of Claim, notify the claimant or his
legal representative of such determination, which determination shall be prima
facie correct</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Proof of such determination by the Department may be made at any
hearing before the Department or in any legal proceeding by a reproduced copy
of the Department's record relating thereto, in the name of the Department
under the certificate of the Director of Revenue. Such reproduced copy shall,
without further proof, be admitted into evidence before the Department or in
any legal proceeding and shall be prima facie proof of the correctness of the
Department's determination, as shown therein. If such claimant, or the legal
representative of a deceased or incompetent taxpayer, within 60 days after
the Department's Notice of Tentative Determination of Claim, files a
protest thereto and requests a hearing thereon, the Department shall give
notice to such claimant, or the legal representative of a deceased taxpayer,
or a taxpayer who is under legal disability of the time and place fixed for
such hearing, and shall hold a hearing in conformity with the provisions of
this Act, and pursuant thereto shall issue its Final Determination of the
amount, if any, found to be due as a result of such hearing, to such claimant,
or the legal representative of a deceased taxpayer, or a taxpayer who is under
legal disability. The Department's Final Determination may be reviewed by the
proper Circuit Court, in the same manner, within the same time, upon the same
terms and conditions and to the same extent, as provided by Section 12 of this
Act. In any case in which there has been an erroneous refund of
tax payable under this Act, a notice of tax liability may be issued at any
time within 3 years from the making of that refund, or within 5 years from
the making of that refund if it appears that any part of the refund was
induced by fraud or the misrepresentation of a material fact.  The amount
of any proposed assessment set forth in the notice shall be limited to the
amount of the erroneous refund.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 87-876; 87-879; 88-45.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-6c">
            <num>6c</num>
            <heading>If a protest to the Department's Notice of Tentative Determination
of
Claim is not filed within 60 days and a request for a hearing
thereon is
not made as provided in Section 6b of this Act, the said Notice shall
thereupon become and operate as a Final Determination; and, if the
Department's Notice of Tentative Determination, upon becoming a Final
Determination, indicates no amount due to the claimant, or, upon issuance
of a credit memorandum or refund for the amount, if any, found by the
Department to be due, the claim in all its aspects shall be closed and no
longer open to protest, hearing, judicial review, or by any other
proceeding or action whatever, either before the Department or in any court
of this State</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Claims for credit or refund hereunder must be filed with and
initially determined by the Department, the remedy herein provided being
exclusive; and no court shall have jurisdiction to determine the merits of
any claim except upon review as provided herein.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 90-491, eff. 1-1-98.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-6d">
            <num>6d</num>
            <heading>Deduction for uncollectible debt</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A retailer is relieved from liability for any tax that becomes due and payable if the tax is represented by amounts that are found to be worthless or uncollectible, have been charged off as bad debt on the retailer's books and records in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles, and have been claimed as a deduction pursuant to Section 166 of the Internal Revenue Code on the income tax return filed by the retailer. A retailer that has previously paid such a tax may, under rules and regulations adopted by the Department, take as a deduction the amount charged off by the retailer. If these accounts are thereafter, in whole or in part, collected by the retailer, the amount collected shall be included in the first return filed after the collection, and the tax shall be paid with the return.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With respect to the payment of taxes on purchases made through a private-label credit card:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If consumer accounts or receivables are found to be worthless or uncollectible, the retailer may claim a deduction on a return in an amount equal to, or may obtain a refund of, the tax remitted by the retailer on the unpaid balance due if: (A) the accounts or receivables have been charged off as bad debt on the lender's books and records on or after January 1, 2016; (B) the accounts or receivables have been claimed as a          deduction pursuant to Section 166 of the Internal Revenue Code on the          federal income tax return filed by the lender; and (C) a deduction was not previously claimed and a refund was not previously allowed on that portion of the account or receivable.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If the retailer or the lender subsequently collects, in whole or in part, the accounts or receivables for which a deduction or refund has been granted under paragraph</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For purposes of the deduction or refund allowable under this Section,     the limitations period for claiming the deduction or refund shall be the same     as the limitations period set forth in Section 6 of this Act for filing a claim for     credit, and shall commence on the date that the account or receivable has     been claimed as a bad debt deduction pursuant to Section 166 of the Internal     Revenue Code on the federal income tax return filed by the     lender, regardless of the date on which the sale of the tangible personal     property actually occurred.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The deduction or refund allowed under this Section: (A) does not apply to credit sale transaction amounts resulting from purchases of titled property; (B) includes only those credit sale transaction amounts that represent purchases from the retailer whose name or logo appears on the private-label credit card used to make those purchases; (C)  may only be          taken by the taxpayer, or its successors, that filed the return and          remitted tax on the original sale on which the deduction or refund claim is          based; and (D) includes all credit sale transaction amounts eligible under paragraph  (B) that are outstanding with respect to the specific private-label credit card account or receivable at the time the account or receivable is charged off, regardless of the date the credit sale transaction actually occurred.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The retailer and lender shall maintain adequate books, records, or other documentation supporting the charge off of the accounts or receivables for which a deduction was taken or a refund was claimed under this Section.  A retailer claiming a deduction or refund for bad debts from purchases made using a private label credit card shall meet the same standard of documentation as a retailer that claims a deduction or refund for bad debts that are from purchases made not using a private label credit card.  For purposes of computing the deduction or refund, payments on the accounts or receivables shall be prorated against the amounts outstanding on the account.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this Section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>&quot;Retailer&quot; means a person who holds himself or herself out as being engaged (or who habitually engages) in selling tangible personal property at retail with respect to such sales and includes a retailer's affiliates.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>&quot;Lender&quot; means a person, or an affiliate, assignee, or transferee of that person, who owns or has owned a private-label credit card account or an interest in a private-label credit card receivable that the person: (A) purchased directly from a retailer who remitted the tax imposed under this Act; (B) originated pursuant to that person's contract with the retailer who remitted the tax imposed under this Act; or (C) acquired from a third party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>&quot;Private-label credit card&quot; means a charge card or credit card that carries, refers to, or is branded with the name or logo of a retailer and may only be used to make purchases from that retailer or that retailer's affiliates.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>&quot;Affiliate&quot; means an entity affiliated under Section 1504 of the Internal Revenue Code, or an entity that would be an affiliate under that Section had the entity been a corporation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-6d__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Section is exempt from the provisions of Section 2-70 of this Act, Section 3-90 of the Use Tax Act, Section 3-55 of the Service Use Tax Act, Section 3-55 of the Service Occupation Tax Act, and any other provision of law  that provides that an exemption, credit, or  deduction automatically sunsets after a specified period of time after the effective date of the Public Act creating the exemption, credit, or deduction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 99-217, eff. 7-31-15.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-7">
            <num>7</num>
            <heading>Every person engaged in the business of selling tangible personal
property at retail in this State shall keep records and books of all sales
of tangible personal property, together with invoices, bills of lading,
sales records, copies of bills of sale, inventories prepared as of December
31 of each year or otherwise annually as has been the custom in the
specific trade and other pertinent papers and documents</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who
is engaged in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail
in this State and who, in connection with such business, also engages in
other activities (including, but not limited to, engaging in a service
occupation) shall keep such additional records and books of all such
activities as will accurately reflect the character and scope of such
activities and the amount of receipts realized therefrom.
The Department may adopt rules that establish requirements, including record
forms and formats, for records required to be kept and maintained by taxpayers.
For purposes of this Section, &quot;records&quot; means all data maintained by the
taxpayer, including data on paper, microfilm, microfiche or any type of
machine-sensible data compilation. All books and records and other papers and documents which are required
by this Act to be kept shall be kept in the English language
and shall, at all times during business hours of the day, be subject to
inspection by the Department or its duly authorized agents and employees. To support deductions made on the tax return form, or authorized under
this Act, on account of receipts from isolated or occasional sales of
tangible personal property, on account of receipts from sales of tangible
personal property for resale, on account of receipts from sales to
governmental bodies or other exempted types of purchasers, on account of
receipts from sales of tangible personal property in interstate commerce,
and on account of receipts from any other kind of transaction that is not
taxable under this Act, entries in any books, records or other pertinent
papers or documents of the taxpayer in relation thereto shall be in detail
sufficient to show the name and address of the taxpayer's customer in each
such transaction, the character of every such transaction, the date of
every such transaction, the amount of receipts realized from every such
transaction and such other information as may be necessary to establish the
non-taxable character of such transaction under this Act. Except in the case of a sale to a purchaser who will always resell and
deliver the property to his customers outside Illinois, anyone claiming
that he has made a nontaxable sale for resale in some form as tangible
personal property shall also keep a record of the purchaser's registration
number or resale number with the Department. It shall be presumed that all sales of tangible personal property are
subject to tax under this Act until the contrary is established, and the
burden of proving that a transaction is not taxable hereunder shall be upon
the person who would be required to remit the tax to the Department if such
transaction is taxable. In the course of any audit or investigation or
hearing by the Department with reference to a given taxpayer, if the
Department finds that the taxpayer lacks documentary evidence needed to
support the taxpayer's claim to exemption from tax hereunder, the
Department is authorized to notify the taxpayer in writing to produce such
evidence, and the taxpayer shall have 60 days subject to the right in the
Department to extend this period either on request for good cause shown or
on its own motion from the date when such notice is sent to the taxpayer by
certified or registered mail (or delivered to the taxpayer if the notice is
served personally) in which to obtain and produce such evidence for the
Department's inspection, failing which the matter shall be closed, and the
transaction shall be conclusively presumed to be taxable hereunder. Books and records and other papers reflecting gross receipts received
during any period with respect to which the Department is authorized to
issue notices of tax liability as provided by Sections 4 and 5 of this
Act shall be preserved until the expiration of such period unless the
Department, in writing, shall authorize their destruction or disposal prior
to such expiration. Any person who fails to keep books and records or fails to produce books and records for examination, as required by this Section and the rules adopted by the Department, is liable to pay to the Department, for deposit into the Tax Compliance and Administration Fund, a penalty of $1,000 for the first failure to keep books and records or produce books and records for examination and a penalty of $3,000 for each subsequent failure to keep books and records or produce books and records for examination as required by this Section and the rules adopted by the Department. The penalties imposed under this Section shall not apply if the taxpayer shows that he or she acted with ordinary business care and prudence. The Department may adopt rules to administer the penalties under this Section.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 100-940, eff. 8-17-18.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-8">
            <num>8</num>
            <heading>For the purpose of administering and enforcing the provisions of
this Act, the Department, or any officer or employee of the Department
designated, in writing, by the Director thereof, may hold investigations
and hearings not otherwise delegated to the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal concerning any matters covered by this Act and may examine any
books, papers, records or memoranda bearing upon the sales of tangible
personal property or services of any such person, and may require the
attendance of such person or any officer or employee of such person, or of
any person having knowledge of such business, and may take testimony and
require proof for its information</heading>
            <content>
              <p>In the conduct of any investigation or
hearing, neither the Department nor any officer or employee thereof shall
be bound by the technical rules of evidence, and no informality in any
proceeding, or in the manner of taking testimony, shall invalidate any
order, decision, rule or regulation made or approved or confirmed by the
Department. The Director of Revenue, or any officer or employee of the
Department authorized by the Director thereof, shall have power to
administer oaths to such persons. The books, papers, records and memoranda
of the Department, or parts thereof, may be proved in any hearing,
investigation, or legal proceeding by a reproduced copy thereof under the
certificate of the Director of Revenue. Such reproduced copy shall, without
further proof, be admitted into evidence before the Department or in any
legal proceeding.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-9">
            <num>9</num>
            <heading>No person shall be excused from testifying or from producing any
books, papers, records or memoranda in any investigation or upon any
hearing not otherwise delegated to the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal, when ordered to do so by the department or any officer or employee
thereof, upon the ground that the testimony or evidence, documentary or
otherwise, may tend to incriminate him or subject him to a criminal
penalty, but no person shall be prosecuted or subjected to any criminal
penalty for, or on account of, any transaction made or thing concerning
which he may testify or produce evidence, documentary or otherwise, before
the department or an officer or employee thereof; provided, that such
immunity shall extend only to a natural person who, in obedience to a
subpoena, gives testimony under oath or produces evidence, documentary or
otherwise, under oath</heading>
            <content>
              <p>No person so testifying shall be exempt from
prosecution and punishment for perjury committed in so testifying.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-10">
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>The Department or any officer or employee of the Department
designated, in writing, by the Director thereof, shall at its or his or
her own instance, or on the written request of any other party to the proceeding,
issue subpoenas requiring the attendance of and the giving of testimony by
witnesses, and subpoenas duces tecum requiring the production of books,
papers, records or memoranda</heading>
            <content>
              <p>All subpoenas and subpoenas duces tecum
issued under the terms of this Act may be served by any person of full age.
The fees of witnesses for attendance and travel shall be the same as the
fees of witnesses before the circuit court of this State; such fees to be
paid when the witness is excused from further attendance. When the witness
is subpoenaed at the instance of the Department or any officer or employee
thereof, such fees shall be paid in the same manner as other expenses of
the Department, and when the witness is subpoenaed at the instance of any
other party to any such proceeding the Department may require that the cost
of service of the subpoena or subpoena duces tecum and the fee of the
witness be borne by the party at whose instance the witness is summoned. In
such case, the Department, in its discretion, may require a deposit to
cover the cost of such service and witness fees. A subpoena or subpoena
duces tecum issued as aforesaid shall be served in the same manner as a
subpoena issued out of a court. Any circuit court of this State, upon the
application of the Department or any officer or employee thereof, or upon
the application of any other party to the proceeding, may, in its
discretion, compel the attendance of witnesses, the production of books,
papers, records or memoranda and the giving of testimony before the
Department or any officer or employee thereof conducting an investigation
or holding a hearing authorized by this Act, by an attachment for contempt,
or otherwise, in the same manner as production of evidence may be compelled
before the court. The Department or any officer or employee thereof, or any other party in
an investigation or hearing before the Department, may cause the
depositions of witnesses within the State to be taken in the manner
prescribed by law for like depositions in civil actions in courts of this
State, and to that end compel the attendance of witnesses and the
production of books, papers, records or memoranda.</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 83-334.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-11">
            <num>11</num>
            <heading>All information received by the Department from returns filed
under this Act, or from any investigation conducted under this Act, shall
be confidential, except for official purposes, and any person, including a third party as defined in the Local Government Revenue Recapture Act, who divulges
any such information in any manner, except in accordance with a proper
judicial order or as otherwise provided by law, including the Local Government Revenue Recapture Act, shall be guilty of a Class
B misdemeanor with a fine not to exceed $7,500</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act prevents the Director of Revenue from publishing or
making available to the public the names and addresses of persons filing
returns under this Act, or reasonable statistics concerning the operation
of the tax by grouping the contents of returns so the information in any
individual return is not disclosed. Nothing in this Act prevents the Director of Revenue from divulging to
the United States Government or the government of any other state, or any
officer or agency thereof, for exclusively official purposes, information
received by the Department in administering this Act, provided that such
other governmental agency agrees to divulge requested tax information to
the Department. The Department's furnishing of information derived from a taxpayer's
return or from an investigation conducted under this Act to the surety on a
taxpayer's bond that has been furnished to the Department under this Act,
either to provide notice to such surety of its potential liability under
the bond or, in order to support the Department's demand for payment from
such surety under the bond, is an official purpose within the meaning of
this Section. The furnishing upon request of information obtained by the Department
from returns filed under this Act or investigations conducted under this
Act to the Illinois Liquor Control Commission for official use is deemed to
be an official purpose within the meaning of this Section. Notice to a surety of potential liability shall not be given unless the
taxpayer has first been notified, not less than 10 days prior thereto, of
the Department's intent to so notify the surety. The furnishing upon request of the Auditor General, or his authorized agents,
for official use, of returns filed and information related thereto under
this Act is deemed to be an official purpose within the meaning of this
Section. Where an appeal or a protest has been filed on behalf of a taxpayer, the
furnishing upon request of the attorney for the taxpayer of returns filed
by the taxpayer and information related thereto under this Act is deemed
to be an official purpose within the meaning of this Section. The furnishing of financial information to a municipality or county, upon request of the chief executive officer thereof, is an official purpose within the meaning of this Section,
provided the municipality or county agrees in
writing to the requirements of this Section. Information provided to municipalities and counties under this paragraph shall be limited to: (1)  the business name; (2) the business address; (3) the standard classification number assigned to the business; (4) net revenue distributed to the requesting municipality or county that is directly related to the  requesting municipality's or county's local share of the proceeds under the Use Tax Act, the Service Use Tax Act, the Service Occupation Tax Act, and the Retailers' Occupation Tax Act distributed from the Local Government Tax Fund, and, if applicable, any locally imposed retailers' occupation tax or service occupation tax; and (5) a listing of all businesses within the requesting municipality or county by account identification number and address.  On and after July 1, 2015, the furnishing of financial information to municipalities and counties under this paragraph may be by electronic means. If the Department may furnish financial information to a municipality or county under this paragraph, then the chief executive officer of the municipality or county may, in turn, provide that financial information to a third party pursuant to the Local Government Revenue Recapture Act.  However, the third party shall agree in writing to the requirements of this Section and meet the requirements of the Local Government Revenue Recapture Act. Information so provided shall be subject to all confidentiality provisions
of this Section.  The written agreement shall provide for reciprocity,
limitations on access, disclosure, and procedures for requesting information. For the purposes of furnishing financial information to a municipality or county under this Section, &quot;chief executive officer&quot; means the mayor of a city, the village board president of a village, the mayor or president of an incorporated town, the county executive of a county that has adopted the county executive form of government, the president of the board of commissioners of Cook County, or the chairperson of the county board or board of county commissioners of any other county. The Department may make available to the Board of Trustees of any Metro
East Mass Transit District information contained on transaction reporting
returns required to be filed under Section 3 of this Act that report sales made
within the boundary of the taxing authority of that Metro East Mass Transit
District, as provided in Section 5.01 of the Local Mass Transit District Act.
The disclosure shall be made pursuant to a written agreement between the
Department and the Board of Trustees of a Metro East Mass Transit District,
which is an official purpose within the meaning of this Section.  The written
agreement between the Department and the Board of Trustees of a Metro East
Mass Transit District shall provide for reciprocity, limitations on access,
disclosure, and procedures for requesting information.  Information so provided
shall be subject to all confidentiality provisions of this Section. The Director may make available to any State agency, including the
Illinois Supreme Court, which licenses persons to engage in any occupation,
information that a person licensed by such agency has failed to file
returns under this Act or pay the tax, penalty and interest shown therein,
or has failed to pay any final assessment of tax, penalty or interest due
under this Act.
The Director may make available to any State agency, including the Illinois
Supreme
Court, information regarding whether a bidder, contractor, or an affiliate of a
bidder or
contractor has failed to collect and remit Illinois Use tax on sales into
Illinois, or any tax
under this Act or pay the tax, penalty, and interest shown therein, or has
failed to pay any
final assessment of tax, penalty, or interest due under this Act, for the
limited purpose of
enforcing bidder and contractor certifications. The Director may make available
to units
of local government and school districts that require bidder and contractor
certifications,
as set forth in Sections 50-11 and 50-12 of the Illinois Procurement Code,
information
regarding whether a bidder, contractor, or an affiliate of a bidder or
contractor has failed
to collect and remit Illinois Use tax on sales into Illinois, file returns under
this Act, or
pay the tax, penalty, and interest shown therein, or has failed to pay any final
assessment
of tax, penalty, or interest due under this Act, for the limited purpose of
enforcing bidder
and contractor certifications. For purposes of this Section, the term
&quot;affiliate&quot; means any
entity that (1) directly, indirectly, or constructively controls another
entity,
(2) is directly,
indirectly, or constructively controlled by another entity, or (3) is subject
to
the control of
a common entity. For purposes of this Section, an entity controls another
entity
if it owns,
directly or individually, more than 10% of the voting securities of that
entity.
As used in
this Section, the term &quot;voting security&quot; means a security that (1) confers upon
the holder
the right to vote for the election of members of the board of directors or
similar governing
body of the business or (2) is convertible into, or entitles the holder to
receive upon its
exercise, a security that confers such a right to vote. A general partnership
interest is a
voting security. The Director may make available to any State agency, including the
Illinois
Supreme Court, units of local government, and school districts, information
regarding
whether a bidder o</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 101-10, eff. 6-5-19; 101-628, eff. 6-1-20; 102-558, eff. 8-20-21; 102-941, eff. 7-1-22.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-11a">
            <num>11a</num>
            <heading>The Illinois Administrative Procedure Act is hereby expressly
adopted and shall apply to all administrative rules and procedures of the
Department of Revenue under this Act, except that (1) paragraph (b) of Section
5-10 of the Illinois Administrative Procedure Act does not apply to final
orders, decisions and opinions of the Department, (2) subparagraph (a)2 of
Section 5-10 of the Illinois Administrative Procedure Act does not apply to
forms established by the Department for use under this Act, and (3) the
provisions of Section 10-45 of the Illinois Administrative Procedure Act
regarding proposals for decision are excluded and not applicable to the
Department under this Act to the extent Section 10-45 applies to hearings not otherwise delegated to the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.) (35 ILCS 120/12) (from Ch. 120, par. 451)</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-12">
            <num>12</num>
            <heading>The Department is authorized to make, promulgate and enforce such
reasonable rules and regulations relating to the administration and
enforcement of the provisions of this Act as may be deemed expedient</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever notice is required by this Act, such notice may be given by
United States registered or certified mail, addressed to the person
concerned at his last known address, and proof of such mailing shall be
sufficient for the purposes of this Act.  Notice of any hearing provided for
by this Act shall be so given not less than 7 days prior to the day fixed
for the hearing. Following the initial contact of a person represented by
an attorney, the
Department shall not contact the person concerned but shall only
contact the attorney representing the person concerned. All hearings provided for in this Act with respect to or concerning a
taxpayer having his or her principal place of business in this State other
than in Cook County shall be held at the Department's office nearest to the
location of the taxpayer's principal place of business: Provided that if
the taxpayer has his or her principal place of business in Cook County, such
hearing shall be held in Cook County; and provided, further, that if the
taxpayer does not have his or her principal place of business in this
State, such hearing shall be held in Sangamon County. The Circuit Court of the County wherein the taxpayer has his or her principal
place of business, or of Sangamon County in those cases where the taxpayer
does not have his or her principal place of business in this State, shall have
power to review all final administrative decisions of the Department in
administering the provisions of this Act: Provided that if the
administrative proceeding which is to be reviewed judicially is a claim for
refund proceeding commenced in accordance with Section 6 of this Act and
Section 2a of &quot;An Act in relation to the payment and disposition of moneys
received by officers and employees of the State of Illinois by virtue of
their office or employment&quot;, approved June 9, 1911, as amended, the
Circuit Court having jurisdiction of the action for judicial review under
this Section and under the Administrative Review Law, as amended, shall
be the same court that entered the temporary restraining order or preliminary
injunction which is provided for in Section 2a of &quot;An Act in relation
to the payment and disposition of moneys received by officers and employees
of the State of Illinois by virtue of their office or employment&quot;, and
which enables such claim proceeding to be processed and disposed of as a
claim for refund proceeding rather than as a claim for credit proceeding. The provisions of the Administrative Review Law, and the rules adopted
pursuant thereto, shall apply to and govern all proceedings for the
judicial review of final administrative decisions of the Department
hereunder, except with respect to protests and hearings held before the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal.  The provisions of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal Act of 2012, and the rules adopted
pursuant thereto, shall apply to and govern all proceedings for the
judicial review of administrative decisions of the Department that are subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal.  The term &quot;administrative decision&quot; is defined as in Section
3-101 of the Code of Civil Procedure. Except with respect to decisions that are subject to the jurisdiction of the Illinois Independent Tax Tribunal, any person filing an action under the Administrative Review Law to review
a final
assessment or revised final assessment issued by the Department under this
Act shall, within 20 days after filing the complaint, file a bond with good
and sufficient surety or sureties residing in this State or licensed to do
business in this State or, instead of the bond, obtain an order from the court
imposing a lien upon
the plaintiff's property as hereinafter provided.
If the
person filing the complaint fails to comply with this bonding requirement
within 20 days after filing the complaint, the Department shall file a motion
to
dismiss and the court shall dismiss the action unless the person filing the
action complies with the bonding requirement set out in this provision within
30 days after the filing of the Department's motion to dismiss.  Upon dismissal of any
complaint for failure to comply with the jurisdictional
prerequisites herein set forth, the court is empowered to and shall enter
judgment against the taxpayer and in favor of the Department in the amount of
the final
assessment or revised final assessment, together with any interest which
may have accrued since the
Department issued the final assessment or revised final assessment, and for
costs, which judgment is enforceable
as other judgments for the payment of money.  The lien
provided for in this Section shall not be applicable to the real property
of a corporate surety duly licensed to do business in this State.  The
amount of such bond shall be fixed and approved by the court, but shall not
be less than the amount of the tax and penalty claimed to be due by the
Department in its final assessment or revised final assessment to the
person filing such bond, plus the amount of interest due from such person
to the Department at the time when the Department issued its final
assessment to such person.  Such bond shall be executed to the Department of
Revenue and shall be conditioned on the taxpayer's payment within 30 days
after termination of the proceedings for judicial review of the amount of
tax and penalty and interest found by the court to be due in such
proceedings for judicial review.  Such bond, when filed and approved, shall,
from such time until 2 years after termination of the proceedings for
judicial review in which the bond is filed, be a lien against the real
estate situated in the county in which the bond is filed, of the person
filing such bond, and of the surety or sureties on such bond, until the
condition of the bond has been complied with or until the bond has been
canceled as hereinafter provided.  If the person filing any such bond fails
to keep the condition thereof, such bond shall thereupon be forfeited, and
the Department may institute an action upon such bond in
its own name for the
entire amount of the bond and costs.  Such action upon the bond shall be in
addition to any other remedy provided for herein.  If the person filing such
bond complies with the condition thereof, or if, in the proceedings for
judicial review in which such bond is filed, the court determines that no
amount of tax or penalty or interest is due, such bond shall be canceled. If the court finds in a particular case that the plaintiff cannot
procure and furnish a satisfactory surety or sureties for the kind of bond
required herein, the court may relieve the plaintiff of the obligation of
filing such bond, if, upon the timely application for a lien in lieu
thereof and accompanying proof therein submitted, the court is satisfied
that any such lien imposed would operate to secure the assessment in the
manner and to the degree as would a bond. Upon a finding that such lien
applied for would secure the assessment at issue, the court shall enter an
order, in lieu of such bond,
subjecting the plaintiff's real and personal property (including
subsequently acquired property), situated in the county in which such order
is entered, to a lien in favor of the Department.  Such lien shall be for
the amount of the tax and penalty claimed to be due by the Department in
its final assessment or revised final assessment, plus the amount of
interest due from such person to the Department at the time when the
Department issued its final assessment to such person, and shall continue
in full force and effect until the termination of the proceedings for
judicial review, or until the plaintiff pays, to the Department, the tax
and penalty and interest to secure which the lien is given, whichever
happens first.  In the exercise of its discretion, the court may impose a
lien regardless of the ratio of the </p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1129, eff. 8-28-12; 98-463, eff. 8-16-13.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-13">
            <num>13</num>
            <heading>Criminal penalties</heading>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the amount due is under $300, any person engaged
in the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this
State who fails to file a return, or who files a fraudulent return, or
any officer, employee or agent of a corporation, member, employee or
agent of a partnership, or manager, member, agent, or employee of a limited
liability company engaged in the business of selling tangible personal
property at retail in this State who, as such officer, employee, agent,
manager, or member is under a duty to file a return, or any officer, agent or
employee of a corporation, member, agent, or employee of a partnership, or
manager, member, agent, or employee of a limited liability company engaged in
the business of selling tangible personal property at retail in this State who
files or causes to be filed or signs or causes to be signed a fraudulent
return filed on behalf of such corporation or limited liability company, or
any accountant or other agent who knowingly enters false information on the
return of any taxpayer under this Act, is guilty of a Class 4 felony. Any person who or any officer or director of any corporation, partner or
member of any partnership, or manager or member of a limited liability company
that:</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>violates Section 2a of this Act or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>fails to keep books and
records, or fails to produce books and records as required by Section 7 or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>willfully violates a rule or regulation of the Department for the
administration and enforcement of this Act is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor.
Any person, manager or member of a limited liability company, or officer or
director of any corporation who engages in the business of selling tangible
personal property at retail after the certificate of registration of that
person, corporation, limited liability company, or partnership has been revoked
is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor.  Each day such person, corporation, or
partnership is engaged in business without a certificate of registration or
after the certificate of registration of that person, corporation, or
partnership has been revoked constitutes a separate offense. Any purchaser who obtains a registration number or resale number from
the Department through misrepresentation, or who represents to a seller
that such purchaser has a registration number or a resale number from the
Department when he knows that he does not, or who uses his registration
number or resale number to make a seller believe that he is buying tangible
personal property for resale when such purchaser in fact knows that this is
not the case is guilty of a Class 4 felony. Any distributor, supplier or other reseller of motor fuel registered
pursuant to Section 2a or 2c of this Act who fails to collect the prepaid
tax on invoiced gallons of motor fuel sold or who fails to deliver a statement
of tax paid to the purchaser or to the Department as required by Sections
2d and 2e of this Act, respectively, shall be guilty of a Class A misdemeanor
if the amount due is under $300, and a Class 4 felony if the amount due
is $300 or more. When the amount due is under $300, any person who accepts money
that is due to the Department under this Act from a taxpayer for the purpose of
acting as the taxpayer's agent to make the payment to the Department, but who
fails to remit such payment to the Department when due is guilty of a Clas</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the offense of sales tax evasion under this Act when he knowingly attempts in any manner to evade or defeat the tax imposed on him or on any other person, or the payment thereof, and he commits an affirmative act in furtherance of the evasion.  For purposes of this Section, an &quot;affirmative act in furtherance of the evasion&quot; means an act designed in whole or in part to</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>conceal, misrepresent, falsify,  or manipulate any material fact or (ii) tamper with or destroy documents or materials related to a person's tax liability under this Act.  Two or more acts of sales tax evasion may be charged as a single count in any indictment, information, or complaint and the amount of tax deficiency may be aggregated for purposes of determining the amount of tax which is attempted to be or is evaded and the period between the first and last acts may be alleged as the date of the offense.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the amount of tax, the assessment or payment of which is attempted to be or is evaded is less than $500 a person is guilty of a Class 4 felony.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the amount of tax, the assessment or payment of which is attempted to be or is evaded is $500 or more but less than $10,000, a person is guilty of a Class 3 felony.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the amount of tax, the assessment or payment of which is attempted to be or is evaded is $10,000 or more but less than $100,000, a person is guilty of a Class 2 felony.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="sec_35-120-13__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the amount of tax, the assessment or payment of which is attempted to be or is evaded is $100</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: P.A. 97-1074, eff. 1-1-13; 97-1150, eff. 1-25-13; 98-352, eff. 1-1-14.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-120-14">
            <num>14</num>
            <heading>This Act shall be known as the &quot;Retailers' Occupation Tax
Act&quot; and the tax herein imposed shall be in addition to all other
occupation or privilege taxes imposed by the State of Illinois or by any
municipal corporation or political subdivision thereof</heading>
            <content>
              <p>(Source: Laws 1933, p. 924.) This site is maintained for the Illinois General Assembly by the
                        Legislative Information System, 705 Stratton Building, Springfield, Illinois 6270</p>
            </content>
            <authorialNote marker="source">
              <p>Source: Laws 1933, p. 924.</p>
            </authorialNote>
          </section>
        </article>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>